<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="forTextViewChittas"> 89 OR 121 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS (citta)</string>


    <string name="buttonAbhidhammaChetasika">\n <b>52 \n mental factors\n(chetasika)</b> \n</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt">1 \ncontact \n(phassa)</string>
    <string name="universal">Ethically Variable \n Universal 7</string>
    <string name="sometime">Ethically Variable \n Occasional 6</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_harakteristika">Characteristic</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_function">Function</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_proyavlenie">Manifestation</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_prichina">The immediate cause</string>

    <string name="text_for_kontakt"><b>CONTACT (phassa):</b> The word phassa comes from the verb
phusati, meaning "to touch", but contact should not
be understood as a simple physical effect of an object on
the physical ability [touch]. Rather, it
is a mental factor through which consciousness mentally "touches"
an object that has just appeared, thereby initiating
a whole cognitive event.</string>

    <string name="text_for_kontakt_harakteristika"><b>CHARACTERISTIC:</b> touch</string>
    <string name="text_for_kontakt_function"><b>FUNCTION:</b> the collision of consciousness and object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_kontakt_proyavlenie"><b>MANIFESTATION:</b> the coincidence of consciousness with sensory ability.</string>
    <string name="text_for_kontakt_prichina"><b>THE IMMEDIATE CAUSE:</b> the object field that has come into focus.</string>

    <string name="button_chuvstvo">2 \nfeeling \n(vedana)</string>

    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo">FEELING (vedana): Feeling is the mental factor
that the object feels, it is the emotional tone
in which the object is experienced. The Pali word Vedana
does not mean emotion (which is a complex phenomenon
involving a set of accompanying mental factors),
it is the most elementary emotional quality of experience, which
can be pleasant, painful or neutral. \n While other mental factors
outlive the object only indirectly, the feeling experiences it
directly and completely. In this regard, other mental factors
they are compared to the cook who prepares a dish for the king
and only tastes it during cooking, while the
feeling is compared to the king himself, who enjoys
this food as much as he wants.</string>

    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: Sensitivity</string>
    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_function">FUNCTION: experiencing, or enjoying the desired object directly.</string>
    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION:  savoring associated mental factors.</string>
    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: contact.</string>

    <string name="button_vospriyatie">3 \nPerception \n(saňňā)</string>

    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie">PERCEPTION (saññā): His mode of action is comparable
to the carpenterёs recognition of certain types of wood by means of marks placed [earlier] on each of them.</string>

    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: distinguishing the qualities of an object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_function">FUNCTION: recognition of what was perceived earlier.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: interpretation of an object through previously perceived features.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: the object as it appears to perception.</string>

    <string name="button_volenie">4 \nVolition \n(chetanā)</string>

    <string name="text_for_volenie">WOLITION (chetanā): Chetanā - from the same root as
and citta, is a mental factor that deals with the actualization of the goal, that is, with the voluntary or
volitional aspect of cognition. Therefore it is translated as “will.” The comments explain
that chetana organizes the associated mental factors in the process of their influence on the object.
         As the main student repeats
your own lesson and also forces other students
repeat their lessons, and the will, starting to work in relation to its object, also forces the associated
mental states to perform their own tasks.
Volition is the most important mental factor in the generation of kamma, since it is volition that determines
ethical quality of action.</string>

    <string name="text_for_volenie_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTICS: state of volition.</string>
    <string name="text_for_volenie_function">FUNCTION: accumulate (kamma).</string>
    <string name="text_for_volenie_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: coordination.</string>
    <string name="text_for_volenie_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: associated conditions.</string>

    <string name="button_odnonapravlennost">5 \nUnidirectionality \n(ekaggatā)</string>

    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost">ONE-DIRECTIONALITY (ekaggatā): This is unification
mind on the object. Although this factor reaches its expressiveness only in the jhanas, where it functions as a factor
jhānas, the Abhidhamma teaches that the germ of this ability
to mental unification is present in all types of consciousness, even the most rudimentary.
In them it functions as the factor which fixes the mind on the object. </string>

    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: non-wandering or non-distraction.</string>
    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_function">FUNCTION: collect, or combine, associated states.</string>
    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: like peace.</string>
    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: happiness</string>

    <string name="button_jivitindriya">6 \nMental life-controlling ability \n(jivitindriya)</string>

    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya">JIVITINRIYA: There are two types of control
life-faculties: mental, which animates associated mental states, and physical, which
animates material phenomena. But as cetasika
This means only the mental life-controlling ability.</string>

    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTICS: maintaining associated mental states.</string>
    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_function">FUNCTION: to cause associated mental states to occur.</string>
    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: establishing the presence of associated mental states.</string>
    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: mental states that need to be maintained.</string>

    <string name="buttonAbhidhammaChetasikaEtichVerFakt">13 \n Ethically Verifiable Mental Factors \n(Annasamānachetasika)</string>

    <string name="button_vnimanie">7 \nAttention \n(manasikara)</string>

    <string name="text_for_vnimanie">ATTENTION (manasikāra): this is mental
the factor responsible for directing the mind towards an object, whereby the object becomes presented to the consciousness.
     Attention - how
the ship`s rudder, which guides it to its destination,
or like a charioteer who sends well-trained
horses (i.e. associated states) towards their destination (object). Mental factor
manasikāra must be distinguished from vitakka: at that time
how manasikāra directs the accompanying mental
factors to an object, Vittaka applies them to the object. Manasikāra is an obligatory cognitive factor,
         present in all states of consciousness; vitakka - special
alised factor that is not mandatory for
process of cognition.</string>

    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTICS: leading (sārana) of associated mental states towards an object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_function">FUNCTION: bind associated states to an object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: manifests itself as a confrontation with the object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: object.</string>
    <string name="buttonChetasikaKontaktKombinaciya">Association with consciousness</string>
    <string name="textButtonChittas"> \n <b>89 or 121 \n types of consciousness \n (chitta) </b> \n</string>

    <string name="text_for_chittas">
        The Pali word "chitta" comes from the verb
root chiti - “to know, to know.” \n Commentators define citta in three ways: as an agent, as an instrument
and as an activity. As an agent, citta is that which cognizes the object (āramman am cinteti ti cittam). \n As an instrument, citta is that by which the accompanying mental factors cognize the object (etena chintenti ti
chittam). \n As the activity of citta itself is nothing other than
as a process of cognition of an object (chintanamattam chittam). \n
The third definition, given in terms of activity, is considered the most appropriate of them; that is, citta is fundamentally the activity, or process, of cognition, or knowledge, of an object. It is not an agent or a tool,
having actual existence in itself, separate from activity or cognition. Definitions in terms of agent and instrument are proposed to refute the misconception of those who believe that the permanent personality, or ego, is the agent and instrument of knowledge. Buddhist thinkers through
These definitions indicate that it is not the personality that carries out the act of cognition, but citta, or consciousness. This citta
is nothing more than an act of cognition, and this act is necessarily temporary, marked by emergence and disappearance. \n
While citta has the sole characteristic of knowing the object, a characteristic which remains the same in all its various manifestations, the Abhidhamma distinguishes different types of citta. These
the types, also called cittas, number eighty-nine, or, if classified more closely, one hundred and twenty-one. What we usually think about
as consciousness, is in fact a series of cittas - instantaneous acts of consciousness,
        occurring in such rapid succession that we are unable to notice the individual moments of their occurrence,
        belonging to different types. The Abhidhamma not only distinguishes these types of consciousness,
        but, more importantly, it also shows them in a certain ordered system, a single and closely intertwined whole.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_chitta_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: knowledge of the object
(vijānana).</string>
    <string name="text_for_chitta_function">FUNCTION: to be a “forerunner” (pubbangama)
mental factors, in the sense that citta predominates
above them and always accompanied by them.</string>
    <string name="text_for_chitta_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: the way in which it appears to the experience of the meditator is
         it is a continuous connectedness of processes (sandhana).</string>
    <string name="text_for_chitta_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: mental-material (nāmarupa),
         because consciousness cannot arise
one, in the complete absence of mental factors and material phenomena.</string>

    <string name="text_for_chittasiki">
        CHETASIKAS are mental phenomena that occur in direct connection with chitta,
         or consciousness, and will perform more specific tasks in the general act of cognition, thereby helping the chitta.
         Mental factors cannot arise without citta,
         just as citta cannot be completely separated from mental factors.
         But, despite the fact that functionally these two types of realities are independent,
         Chitta is considered as the main one because mental factors help in the knowledge of the object
         depending on citta, which is the main cognitive element. \n
The relationship between the Citta and the Cetasikas is comparable to the relationship between a king and his retinue.
         Although they say: “The king is coming,” the king does not come alone, he always comes accompanied by his assistants.
         Likewise, whenever citta arises, it never arises alone,
         and always accompanied by his retinue - a cetasik.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_eticheski_veriabelnie">
         ETHICALLY VARIABLE FACTORS (annasamānachetasika): \n\n
         The first two categories of mental factors are the seven universal mental factors
         and six that occur from time to time - united under the title annasamāna,
         conventionally translated here as “ethically variable.”
         The expression literally means "in common with others."
         The non-beautiful cittas are called “other” (anna) in relation to the beautiful cittas,
         and the beautiful cittas are called “other” in relation to the cittas that are not beautiful.
         The thirteen cetasikas of the first two categories are common (samāna) both for the beautiful,
         so for non-beautiful cittas, and accept the ethical quality transferred to the citta by other cetasikas,
         namely, the roots associated with it (hetu).
         In wholesome cittas they become wholesome, in unwholesome cittas they become unwholesome,
         and in kammically indefinite cittas they become kammically indefinite.
         For this reason they are called “common with others,” that is, ethically variable. \n\n
    </string>

    <string name="button_vitakka">1 \nInitial Application \n(vitakka)</string>
    <string name="text_for_mentalnie_faktori_sometime1">
    INITIAL APPLICATION (vitakka):
    The mental factor vitakka is also presented in the discussion of the jhānas,
    where it is presented as the first of the five jhānic factors. Vitakka is the application of the mind to the object.
    Its characteristic is the directing of the mind onto the object. Its function is to strike
    and thresh the object. It is manifested as the leading of the mind onto the object.
    Although no proximate cause is mentioned in the commentaries, the object itself can be understood as its proximate cause.
    Ordinarily, vitakka simply applies the mind to the object. But when this mental factor is cultivated through concentration, it becomes a jhāna factor.
    In this case, it is called appanā— "absorption of the mind in the object."
    Vitakka is also called saṅkappa— "intention"— and as such is distinguished as micchāsaṅkappa, or wrong
    intention, and sammāsaṅkappa, or right intention.
    The latter is the second factor of the Noble Eightfold Path.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_harakteristika_sometime1">
        CHARACTERISTIC: the directing of the mind onto the object.
    </string>
    <string name="text_for_function_sometime1">
        FUNCTION: to strike and thresh the object.
    </string>
    <string name="text_for_proyavlenie_sometime1">
        MANIFESTATION: It is manifested as the leading of the mind onto the object.
    </string>
    <string name="text_for_prichina_sometime1">
        PROXIMATE CAUSE: the object itself can be understood as its proximate cause.
    </string>
    <string name="text_for_button_associaciya_sometime1">
    ASSOCIATED WITH 55 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS: \n\n
    8 — consciousnesses rooted in GREED \n
    2 — consciousnesses rooted in HATRED \n
    2 — consciousnesses rooted in DELUSION \n
    1 — unwholesome-resultant receiving consciousness \n
    1 — unwholesome-resultant investigating consciousness \n
    1 — wholesome-resultant receiving consciousness \n
    1 — wholesome-resultant investigating consciousness \n
    1 — wholesome-resultant investigating consciousness accompanied by joy \n
    1 — five-door adverting consciousness \n
    1 — mind-door adverting consciousness \n
    1 — smile-producing consciousness \n
    8 — great wholesome consciousnesses \n
    8 — great resultant consciousnesses \n
    8 — great functional consciousnesses \n
    1 — wholesome first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — resultant first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — functional first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — stream-entry path first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — stream-entry fruition first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — once-returning path first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — once-returning fruition first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — non-returning path first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — non-returning fruition first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — arahatship path first jhāna consciousness \n
    1 — arahatship fruition first jhāna consciousness \n\n
    NOT ASSOCIATED WITH: \n\n
    the two sets of fivefold sensory consciousness (-10) \n
    32 path and fruition consciousnesses of the 2nd, 3rd, 4th, and 5th jhānas (-32) \n
    12 consciousnesses of the 2nd, 3rd, 4th, and 5th jhānas (wholesome, functional, resultant) (-12) \n
    12 immaterial-sphere consciousnesses (wholesome, functional, resultant) (-12)
</string>

    <string name="button_vichara">2 \nSustained Application \n(vicāra)</string>
    <string name="text_for_mentalnie_faktori_sometime2">
    SUSTAINED APPLICATION (vicāra):
    Vicāra, which is also a jhāna factor, has the characteristic of continued pressure on the object
    in the sense of examining it.
    While they often occur together, initial application is the first impact of the mind in the sense of
    grossness and the beginning stage, similar to the striking of a bell. Sustained application is the act
    of keeping the mind anchored in the sense that it is subtle, and its individual essence is continued
    pressure, similar to the humming of the bell.
    Initial application is the mind’s intervention at the moment of first emergence, like a bird
    spreading its wings to take flight, or a bee diving toward a lotus after previously catching its scent.
    The behavior of sustained application is calm, bordering on non-intervention by the mind,
    similar to a bird soaring with outstretched wings after taking flight, or the buzzing of a bee
    over the lotus once it has already dived onto it.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_harakteristika_sometime2">
    CHARACTERISTIC: Continued pressure on the object.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_function_sometime2">
    FUNCTION: Sustained application of associated mental phenomena to the object.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_proyavlenie_sometime2">
    MANIFESTATION: It manifests as the anchoring of these phenomena upon the object.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_prichina_sometime2">
    PROXIMATE CAUSE: The object may be understood as its proximate cause.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_button_associaciya_sometime2">
    ASSOCIATED WITH 66 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS: \n\n
    8 — consciousnesses rooted in GREED \n
    2 — consciousnesses rooted in HATRED \n
    2 — consciousnesses rooted in DELUSION \n
    1 — unwholesome-resultant receiving consciousness \n
    1 — unwholesome-resultant investigating consciousness \n
    1 — wholesome-resultant receiving consciousness \n
    1 — wholesome-resultant investigating consciousness \n
    1 — wholesome-resultant investigating consciousness accompanied by joy \n
    1 — five-door adverting consciousness \n
    1 — mind-door adverting consciousness \n
    1 — smile-producing consciousness \n
    8 — great wholesome consciousnesses \n
    8 — great resultant consciousnesses \n
    8 — great functional consciousnesses \n
    2 — wholesome consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — resultant consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — functional consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — stream-entry path consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — stream-entry fruition consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — once-returning path consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — once-returning fruition consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — non-returning path consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — non-returning fruition consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — arahatship path consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n
    2 — arahatship fruition consciousnesses of the first and second jhānas \n\n
    NOT ASSOCIATED WITH: \n\n
    the two sets of fivefold sensory consciousness (-10) \n
    24 path and fruition consciousnesses of the 3rd, 4th, and 5th jhānas (-24) \n
    9 consciousnesses of the 3rd, 4th, and 5th jhānas (wholesome, functional, resultant) (-9) \n
    12 immaterial-sphere consciousnesses (wholesome, functional, resultant) (-12)
</string>

    <string name="button_adhimokkha">3 \nDecision \n(adhimokkha)</string>
    <string name="text_for_mentalnie_faktori_sometime3">
    DECISION (adhimokkha):
    The word adhimokkha literally means "the releasing of the mind onto the object."
    Therefore, it is translated as "decision" or "resolution."
    Because of its unshakable determination regarding the object, it is compared
    to a stone pillar.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_harakteristika_sometime3">
    CHARACTERISTIC: Conviction.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_function_sometime3">
    FUNCTION: Not groping [meaning the opposite of wandering in the dark "by touch"].
</string>

    <string name="text_for_proyavlenie_sometime3">
    MANIFESTATION: Decisiveness.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_prichina_sometime3">
    PROXIMATE CAUSE: A thing to be convinced of.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_button_associaciya_sometime3">
    ASSOCIATED WITH 78 or 110 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS: \n\n
    Decision arises in all types of consciousness, except for the
    two sets of fivefold sensory consciousness and the consciousness
    accompanied by doubt.
</string>

    <string name="button_viriya">4 \nEnergy \n(viriya)</string>
    <string name="text_for_mentalnie_faktori_sometime4">
    ENERGY (viriya):
    Viriya is the state or action of one who is energetic.
    Just as new logs added to an old house prevent it
    from collapsing, or as strong reinforcements enable a king\'s army to defeat the enemy,
    so too does energy support and assist all associated states and not allow them to retreat.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_harakteristika_sometime4">
    CHARACTERISTIC: supporting, striving, and upholding.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_function_sometime4">
    FUNCTION: to support associated states.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_proyavlenie_sometime4">
    MANIFESTATION: non-collapse.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_prichina_sometime4">
    PROXIMATE CAUSE: a sense of urgency
    (saṃvega) or any grounds for arousing energy,
    that is, whatever prompts energetic action.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_button_associaciya_sometime4">
    ASSOCIATED WITH 73 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS: \n\n
    Energy arises in all types of consciousness except for the five-door-adverting
    consciousness, the two sets of fivefold sense consciousnesses,
    the receiving consciousness, and the investigating consciousness (89 – 16 = 73).
</string>

    <string name="button_piti">5 \nRapture \n(pīti)</string>
    <string name="text_for_mentalnie_faktori_sometime5">
    RAPTURE (pīti):
    It is of five kinds: minor rapture, momentary rapture, showering rapture,
    uplifting rapture, and pervading (thrilling) rapture.
    This fivefold rapture, when realized and cultivated, perfects the twofold serenity:
    serenity of mind and serenity of body. When serenity is realized and cultivated,
    it perfects the twofold happiness: bodily and mental.
    When happiness is realized and cultivated, it perfects the threefold concentration:
    momentary concentration, access concentration, and absorption concentration.
    In this context, rapture refers to pervading rapture,
    which is the root of absorption and arises through development in association with absorption.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_harakteristika_sometime5">
    CHARACTERISTIC: pīti has the characteristic of endearing
    (sampiyāyana).
</string>
    <string name="text_for_function_sometime5">
    FUNCTION: to refresh the body and mind, or its function is to pervade (to the point of thrilling).
</string>
    <string name="text_for_proyavlenie_sometime5">
    MANIFESTATION: It is manifested as delight, elation [or enthusiasm].
</string>
    <string name="text_for_prichina_sometime5">
    PROXIMATE CAUSE: mentality-materiality (nāmarūpa) is its proximate cause.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_button_associaciya_sometime5">
    ASSOCIATED WITH 35 or 51 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS: \n\n
    Rapture arises in all types of consciousness
    except those accompanied by displeasure
    and equanimity, the two sets of fivefold consciousness, and the consciousness of the fourth
    jhāna.
</string>

    <string name="button_chanda">6 \nDesire \n(chanda)</string>
    <string name="text_for_mentalnie_faktori_sometime6">
    DESIRE (chanda):
    Chanda here signifies the desire to act (kattu-kāmatā), that is, to perform an action
or achieve some result.
    This type of desire must be distinguished from desire in a reprehensible sense,
that is, from lobha, greed, and rāga, passion. While
these latter terms are always unwholesome,
chanda is an ethically variable factor which, when
conjoined with wholesome concomitants,
can function as a moral desire
to achieve a worthy goal. Desire should be regarded
as the stretching forth of the mind’s hands towards the object.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_harakteristika_sometime6">
    CHARACTERISTIC: the desire to act.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_function_sometime6">
    FUNCTION: searching for an object.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_proyavlenie_sometime6">
    MANIFESTATION: a need for the object.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_prichina_sometime6">
    PROXIMATE CAUSE: the object is its proximate cause.
</string>
    <string name="text_for_button_associaciya_sometime6">
    ASSOCIATED WITH 69 or 101 TYPES OF CONSCIOUSNESS: \n\n
    Desire arises in all types of consciousness except for the rootless
    and the two types of consciousness accompanied by delusion (89 – 20 = 69).
</string>




    <string name="inProcess">The Abhidhamma section, in development, is being supplemented with material. \n \n Stay tuned for updates.</string>

</resources>