<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="textButtonKamavacharachitani">Consciousness of the sensory environment \n (Kamavacaracittani) - 54</string>
    <string name="textButtonKamavacharamUnwholsome">Unwholesome consciousness \n (Akusalacittāni) – 12</string>
    <string name="textButtonKamavacharamAhetuka">Rootless consciousness \n (Ahetukacittāni) – 18</string>
    <string name="textButtonKamavacharamBeautiful">Beautiful consciousness \n (Sobhanachittāni) - 24</string>

    <string name="textButtonLobhamulachitani">Consciousness rooted in greed \n (Lobhamulachittāni) – 8</string>
    <string name="textButtonDosamulachitani">Consciousness rooted in anger \n (Dosamulachitani) - 2</string>
    <string name="textButtonMohamulachitani">Consciousness rooted in delusion \n (Mohamulachitani) - 2</string>

    <string name="textButton1Lobhamulachitani">1\n
One consciousness accompanied by joy, associated with an erroneous view, arising without prompting. \n \n
Somanassasahagatam dithigatasampayuttam asankharikam ekam.
</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamAhetuka">
ROOTLESS CONSCIOUSNESS (ahetukacittāni): The word ahetuka means “without roots” and denotes those
        types of consciousness that are devoid of mental factors called hetu - “roots”.
        These types, of which there are eighteen in all, do not contain any of the three unwholesome roots -
        greed, anger and delusion - just as they do not contain any of the three bright roots - non-greed,
        non-anger and non-delusion, which can be both beneficial and uncertain. Since the root is the factor that
        helps establish stability in the citta, those cittas that do not have roots are weaker than those that do have them.
        The eighteen cittas in this class are divided into three groups: unwholesome resultants, wholesome resultants.
basic and functional types of consciousness.
</string>

    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitam">CONSCIOUSNESS OF THE SENSORY ENVIRONMENT: The word kāma means both subjective voluptuousness,
         that is, the passionate desire for sensory pleasures, as well as objective sensory,
         that is, the five external sensory objects - visible forms, sounds, smells, tastes and objects of touch. \n
         Kāmabhumi is the sensory plane of existence, which includes eleven dimensions - the four sorrowful regions,
         the world of human beings and the six sensory heavens. \n
         Sensory-sphere consciousness includes all the cittas that have their corresponding areas on the sensory plane of existence,
         despite the fact that they can also arise on other planes.</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamUnwholsome">UNWELLFUL CONSCIOUSNESS: In the process of analyzing unwholesome consciousness, the Abhidhamma first classifies it according to the type of root that is most significant in it (mula, hetu), be it greed (lobha), anger (dosa)
or delusion (moha). Greed and anger, according to the Abhidhamma, are mutually exclusive; they cannot arise in the same citta. Therefore, those states of consciousness in which greed is the main root,
called “cittas rooted in greed”, there are eight of them in total. Those states in which anger predominates are called “cittas rooted in anger”; there are two such states in total. The third unwholesome root, delusion, is present in every unwholesome consciousness. Thus, in the cittas rooted in greed and rooted in anger, there is also
and error as the underlying root. However, there are types of consciousness in which delusion arises without the accompaniment of greed or anger. These cittas, of which there are only two, are called “consciousness with complete delusion” or “cittas rooted in delusion.”</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamBeautiful">
         Beautiful consciousness (sobhanacittāni): Beautiful consciousness includes all cittas, “excluding those that are unwholesome,” that is, the twelve types of unwholesome consciousness, and excluding the “rootless”—eighteen types, completely devoid of roots. This type of consciousness is called beautiful because it is accompanied by beautiful mental factors (cetasikas). \n
It is necessary to understand that the beautiful (sobhana) has a wider spectrum than the wholesome (kusala). The beautiful includes all the beneficial cittas, as well as the resultant and functional cittas, which have beautiful mental factors. The last [resultant and functional] cittas are not wholesome, they are kammically indeterminate (abyākata). The beautiful ones include the twenty-four sense-sphere cittas, as well as all the subtle-material cittas, the immaterial-sphere cittas, and the supramundane cittas. Those cittas that are not beautiful are called asobhana - "non-beautiful."
     </string>

    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamUnwholsomeLobha">CONSCIOUSNESS ROOT IN GREED (lobhamulachittāni):
Abhidhamma begins analysis of three classes
unwholesome consciousness with differentiation of various
cittas rooted in greed, since greed is always
mentioned first among the unwholesome roots. The Pali word lobha includes all variations of greed, ranging from intense passion or greed to mild sympathies.
pathy and affection. Consciousness rooted in greed is divided into eight types based on three principles of dichotomization. The first principle is the accompanying feeling (vedana), be it a feeling of joy or tranquility; the second is the presence or absence of an erroneous view; third - analysis of what arose
citta with or without prompting. By rearranging these three differences, eight different types of consciousness are obtained.
    ASSOCIATED WITH ERROROUS VIEW (ditt higatasampayutta):\n

Having divided the consciousness rooted in greed into two classes, on the basis of feeling - accompanied by joy or tranquility - the text again divides the same
consciousness based on its connection with the erroneous view. The word ditthi means view, and unless qualified by the prefix sammā "correct", it usually means an erroneous view.
(micchā dit t hi)16. The erroneous view accompanies the consciousness rooted in greed in the form of belief, belief,
opinions or rationalizations. The look can either enhance
the attachment from which this consciousness arises,
providing it with rational justification, or by itself
to be an object of affection. The erroneous view is associated
in total with four types of consciousness - two accompanied by joy and two accompanied by calm. The other four types are dissociated
from an erroneous view (dit t higatavippayutta) - in that
sense that greed operates in them without any accompanying justification provided by any view. \n \n

WITHOUT PROCESS (asankharika): \n
The third principle
The differentiation of consciousness rooted in greed is the presence or absence of motivation. Polysemous word
sankhara is used here in an Abhidhamma-specific manner
in the sense of inducing, inciting, stimulating (payoga) or using a special technique (upāya).
This urge can be imposed by other beings,
or it can come from within. The means used may be physical, verbal or purely mental.
Urge is bodily when someone urges us
by bodily means, causing certain types of consciousness that can result in corresponding actions.
It is verbal when the means used is
it is the command of another or the power of persuasion. And it`s mental
when - either through reflection or by volitional decision - we, despite internal resistance, commit
a deliberate effort aimed at generating certain types of consciousness. The urge may be associated
with both unwholesome and beneficial states
consciousness, as will be shown below. Consciousness arising
spontaneously, without prompting or the use of special
techniques is called “without prompting.” That consciousness that arises with impulse or the use of special techniques is called “arising with impulse.”
(sasankhārika). In a class of consciousness rooted in greed,
four types are those that arise without prompting, or
spontaneous, and four types - arising with motivation,
or forced.
    </string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamUnwholsomeDosa">
Consciousness rooted in anger (dosamulachittāni): \n \n
The second class of unwholesome consciousness analyzed by the Abhidhamma is that rooted in anger, the second of the three unwholesome roots. This consciousness is of two types, distinguished only as arising without prompting or with prompting. Unlike consciousness rooted in greed, which
may occur with different types of feelings - with joy or
calm, the consciousness rooted in anger arises
with only one type of feeling - dissatisfaction. Yet again,
Unlike the mind rooted in greed, the mind rooted in anger does not arise with wrong view.
Although wrong view can motivate acts of anger, according to the Abhidhamma, it does not arise simultaneously with anger, in the same citta, but arises earlier, in a different type of citta. \n \n
Accompanied by discontent (domanassahagata):
The feeling that accompanies states of consciousness rooted in anger is dissatisfaction. The Pali word domanassa, derived from du "bad" and manas "mind", means an unpleasant mental feeling. This feeling accompanies
only consciousness rooted in anger, and such consciousness is necessarily accompanied by this feeling. Thus, dissatisfaction, or an unpleasant mental feeling, is always unwholesome. In this respect, domanassa differs from an unpleasant bodily feeling, which is kammically indefinite, as well as from joy and tranquility, which can
be wholesome, unwholesome and indefinite. \n \n
Associated with disgust (patighasampayutta):
While the consciousness rooted in greed is clearly
image is said to be accompanied by greed, the consciousness rooted in anger (dosa) is expressed by the synonymous term “aversion” (pat igha). Pat igha includes all degrees of disgust, from violent rage to mild irritation. This word literally means "to strike against", which shows the mental
a position of resistance, denial or destruction. \n \n
Although discontent and disgust always accompany
each other, their qualities must be distinguished. Discontent
(domanassa) is the experience of an unpleasant feeling, and disgust (pat igha) is the mental attitude of ill will or irritation. In terms of the five clusters, dissatisfaction is included in the cluster of feelings (vedanākkhandha), while
while disgust is included in the accumulation of mental formations (sankhārakkhandha).
</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamUnwholsomeMoha">
        CONSCIOUSNESS ROOT IN MISTAKE (mohamulachittāni): \n \n
This last class of unwholesome consciousness includes
those cittas in which the other two unwholesome roots - greed and anger - are absent. Usually the presence of a delusion
also leads to the emergence of greed and anger. But, despite the fact that delusion is always present as a root
in the cittas accompanied by greed and anger, its functions
there are secondary. However, in these last two types of unwholesome consciousness, only delusion is present as the unwholesome root, and therefore they are classified as minds rooted in delusion. Since the function delusions are especially obvious in these two types of consciousness, they also described as a consciousness containing complete delusion
(momuhachitta), where the Pali word momukha is a strengthening of the word moha "delusion". There are two types of consciousness, in which the delusion is especially pronounced: one is associated with doubt, the other with anxiety. \n \n
Accompanied by tranquility (upekkhāsahagata): \n \n
When a consciousness rooted in delusion arises,
then, even if the desired object is present, it is not perceived as desired, and therefore the pleasant mental feeling (somanassa) does not arise. Likewise, an unwanted object is not experienced as such and, therefore, an unpleasant mental feeling (domanassa) also does not arise. Moreover, when the mind is clouded by doubt or worry, it is unable to form a definite positive or negative evaluation of an object and therefore cannot
be associated with a pleasant or painful feeling.
For this reason the feeling accompanying these two cittas is neutral, that is, calmness (upekkhā). \n \n

Associated with doubt (vicikicchāsampayutta): \n \n
Commentators give two etymological explanations for the word vicikicchha: \n
1) frustration from confused thoughts and \n
2) absence \n
the cure lies in knowledge. Both these explanations show that vicikicchā, doubt, means confusion, skepticism or indecision due to the prevalence of error. Chitta associated with doubt is the first type of consciousness rooted in error. \n \n

Associated with anxiety (uddhachcasampayutta): \n \n
Worry is anxiety, mental distraction or agitation, and the citta infected with this restlessness is the second type of consciousness, rooted in delusion. According to the Abhidhamma, the mental factor is restlessness
is found in all twelve unwholesome cittas, but in the remaining eleven cittas its strength (satti) is relatively weak and its function is secondary. One-
but in this latter type of consciousness anxiety becomes
the main factor. Therefore, only this type is described as consciousness associated with anxiety. It should be noted that to the description of these two cittas, which are rooted in delusion, no qualification is added in terms of arising with and without prompting. Commentators have offered various explanations for this omission.
The Vibhavini-tika and Mahā-tika [-commentary] on the Visuddhimagga hold that the distinction in terms of impulse is omitted because both of these alternatives are not applicable [in this case]. They claim that since these
the two cittas lack natural sharpness and cannot be described as arising without prompting; and since it is not the case that anyone deliberately tries to cause them, they cannot be described as arising from impulse. Lady Sayadaw, however, rejects this position, arguing that these cittas are exclusively arising without prompting. He claims:
"Since these two cittas occur naturally in beings
Thus, by their own real nature, they do not require motivation or special techniques to arise. They always arise without difficulty or difficulty. That`s why
they are purely unprompted, and this must be considered as the reason why the distinction
the type of motivation is not mentioned here.”
    </string>
</resources>