<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="textButtonLokutara"><b>Supramundane Consciousness (Lokuttaracittāni) — 8 </b></string>

    <string name="textDiscribeLokutarachitani">SUPRAMUNDANE CONSCIOUSNESS (Lokuttaracittāni):
        — is the consciousness that pertains to the process of transcending (uttara) the world (loka), which consists of the five
aggregates of clinging. This type of consciousness leads to liberation from saṃsāra, the cycle of birth and death, and to the attainment of
Nibbāna — the cessation of suffering. There are eight
supramundane cittas. These cittas correspond to the four stages
of Enlightenment — stream-entry, once-returning, non-returning, and Arahantship.
        Each stage includes two types of consciousness: path consciousness (maggacitta)
        and fruit consciousness (phalacitta). All supramundane cittas take as their object the unconditioned reality,
Nibbāna, but they differ as path and fruit according to their functions.
        Path consciousness has the function of eradicating (or irreversibly weakening) defilements;
        fruit consciousness has the function of experiencing the degree of liberation
        attained through the corresponding path. Path consciousness
is a kusalacitta, a wholesome state; fruit consciousness
is a vipākacitta, a resultant state.
Each path consciousness arises only once and lasts
for only a single mind-moment; it never repeats in the mind-stream of the one who has attained it.
        The corresponding fruit consciousness
arises immediately after the path moment and lasts for two or three
mind-moments. Subsequently, it can be repeated and, with practice, in a supramundane absorption
        called "attainment of fruition" (phalasamāpatti), it can last for many mind-moments.
The paths and fruits are attained through a meditation method called "development of insight"
(vipassanābhāvanā). This type of meditation involves strengthening
the faculty of wisdom (paññā). Through sustained attention to the changing phenomena of mind and matter, the meditator learns
to discern their true qualities of impermanence, suffering, and non-self.
        When these insights reach full maturity, they culminate in the paths and fruits.
    </string>

    <string name="forTextViewLokutara">8 SUPRAMUNDANE CONSCIOUSNESSES (Lokuttaracittāni)</string>

</resources>