<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="textButtonKamavacharachitani">Consciousness of the sensory environment \n (Kamavacaracittani) - 54</string>
    <string name="textButtonKamavacharamUnwholsome">Unwholesome consciousness \n (Akusalacittāni) – 12</string>
    <string name="textButtonLobhamulachitani">Consciousness rooted in greed \n (Lobhamulachittāni) – 8</string>
    <string name="textButton1Lobhamulachitani">1\n
One consciousness accompanied by joy, associated with an erroneous view, arising without prompting. \n \n
Somanassasahagatam dithigatasampayuttam asankharikam ekam.
</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitam">CONSCIOUSNESS OF THE SENSORY ENVIRONMENT: The word kāma means both subjective voluptuousness,
         that is, the passionate desire for sensory pleasures, as well as objective sensory,
         that is, the five external sensory objects - visible forms, sounds, smells, tastes and objects of touch. \n
         Kāmabhumi is the sensory plane of existence, which includes eleven dimensions - the four sorrowful regions,
         the world of human beings and the six sensory heavens. \n
         Sensory-sphere consciousness includes all the cittas that have their corresponding areas on the sensory plane of existence,
         despite the fact that they can also arise on other planes.</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamUnwholsome">UNWELLFUL CONSCIOUSNESS: In the process of analyzing unwholesome consciousness, the Abhidhamma first classifies it according to the type of root that is most significant in it (mula, hetu), be it greed (lobha), anger (dosa)
or delusion (moha). Greed and anger, according to the Abhidhamma, are mutually exclusive; they cannot arise in the same citta. Therefore, those states of consciousness in which greed is the main root,
called “cittas rooted in greed”, there are eight of them in total. Those states in which anger predominates are called “cittas rooted in anger”; there are two such states in total. The third unwholesome root, delusion, is present in every unwholesome consciousness. Thus, in the cittas rooted in greed and rooted in anger, there is also
and error as the underlying root. However, there are types of consciousness in which delusion arises without the accompaniment of greed or anger. These cittas, of which there are only two, are called “consciousness with complete delusion” or “cittas rooted in delusion.”</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKamavacharachitamUnwholsomeLobha">CONSCIOUSNESS ROOT IN GREED (lobhamulachittāni):
Abhidhamma begins analysis of three classes
unwholesome consciousness with differentiation of various
cittas rooted in greed, since greed is always
mentioned first among the unwholesome roots. The Pali word lobha includes all variations of greed, ranging from intense passion or greed to mild sympathies.
pathy and affection. Consciousness rooted in greed is divided into eight types based on three principles of dichotomization. The first principle is the accompanying feeling (vedana), be it a feeling of joy or tranquility; the second is the presence or absence of an erroneous view; third - analysis of what arose
citta with or without prompting. By rearranging these three differences, eight different types of consciousness are obtained.</string>
</resources>