<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="textButtonLokutara"><b>Supramundane Consciousness (Lokuttaracittāni) — 8 </b></string>

    <string name="textDiscribeLokutarachitani">SUPRAMUNDANE CONSCIOUSNESS (Lokuttaracittāni):
        — is the consciousness that pertains to the process of transcending (uttara) the world (loka), which consists of the five
aggregates of clinging. This type of consciousness leads to liberation from saṃsāra, the cycle of birth and death, and to the attainment of
Nibbāna — the cessation of suffering. There are eight
supramundane cittas. These cittas correspond to the four stages
of Enlightenment — stream-entry, once-returning, non-returning, and Arahantship.
        Each stage includes two types of consciousness: path consciousness (maggacitta)
        and fruit consciousness (phalacitta). All supramundane cittas take as their object the unconditioned reality,
Nibbāna, but they differ as path and fruit according to their functions.
        Path consciousness has the function of eradicating (or irreversibly weakening) defilements;
        fruit consciousness has the function of experiencing the degree of liberation
        attained through the corresponding path. Path consciousness
is a kusalacitta, a wholesome state; fruit consciousness
is a vipākacitta, a resultant state.
Each path consciousness arises only once and lasts
for only a single mind-moment; it never repeats in the mind-stream of the one who has attained it.
        The corresponding fruit consciousness
arises immediately after the path moment and lasts for two or three
mind-moments. Subsequently, it can be repeated and, with practice, in a supramundane absorption
        called "attainment of fruition" (phalasamāpatti), it can last for many mind-moments.
The paths and fruits are attained through a meditation method called "development of insight"
(vipassanābhāvanā). This type of meditation involves strengthening
the faculty of wisdom (paññā). Through sustained attention to the changing phenomena of mind and matter, the meditator learns
to discern their true qualities of impermanence, suffering, and non-self.
        When these insights reach full maturity, they culminate in the paths and fruits.
    </string>

    <string name="textDiscribeLokutaraWholsome">
        Path consciousness is a kusalacitta, a wholesome state.
    </string>
    <string name="textDiscribeLokutaraResult">
        Fruit consciousness is a vipākacitta, a resultant state.
    </string>



    <string name="forTextViewLokutara">8 SUPRAMUNDANE CONSCIOUSNESSES (Lokuttaracittāni)</string>

    <string name="textButtonLokutaraWholsome">
        \n <b>Supramundane Wholesome Consciousness \n (Lokuttara-kusalacittāni) — 4</b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButtonLokutaraResult">
        \n <b>Supramundane Resultant Consciousness \n (Lokuttara-vipākacittāni) — 4</b> \n
    </string>

    <string name="forTextViewZagolovokLokutaraWholsome">
        4 SUPRAMUNDANE WHOLESOME CONSCIOUSNESSES
    </string>
    <string name="forTextViewZagolovokLokutaraResult">
        4 SUPRAMUNDANE RESULTANT CONSCIOUSNESSES
</string>




    <string name="textButton1LokutaraWholsome">
        <b> 1 \n Path consciousness of stream-entry. \n\n
         Sotāpatti-maggacittam. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton2LokutaraWholsome">
        <b> 2 \n Path consciousness of once-returning. \n\n
         Sakadāgāmi-maggacittam. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton3LokutaraWholsome">
        <b> 3 \n Path consciousness of non-returning. \n\n
         Anāgāmi-maggacittam. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton4LokutaraWholsome">
        <b> 4 \n Path consciousness of Arahantship. \n\n
         Arahatta-maggacittaṃ cā ti. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton5LokutaraWholsome">
        <b> These various classes of consciousness, which thus number 89,
            are divided by the wise into 121.</b>
    </string>

    <string name="textButton1LokutaraResult">
    <b> 1 \n Fruit consciousness of stream-entry. \n\n
     Sotāpatti-phalacittam. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton2LokutaraResult">
    <b> 2 \n Fruit consciousness of once-returning. \n\n
     Sakadāgāmi-phalacittam. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton3LokutaraResult">
    <b> 3 \n Fruit consciousness of non-returning. \n\n
     Anāgāmi-phalacittam. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton4LokutaraResult">
    <b> 4 \n Fruit consciousness of Arahantship. \n\n
     Arahatta-phalacittaṃ cā ti. </b>
    </string>
    <string name="textButton5LokutaraResult">
    <b> These various classes of consciousness, which thus number 89,
        are divided by the wise into 121.</b>
    </string>



    <string name="textLokutaraWholsome1">
    Path consciousness of stream-entry (sotāpattimaggacitta):
    Entering the irreversible path to liberation is called stream-entry, and the citta that experiences this
    attainment is the path consciousness of stream-entry. The stream
    (sota) is the Noble Eightfold Path, consisting
    of eight factors: right view, right intention, right speech, right action, right
    livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right concentration.
    Just as the stream of the river Ganges flows continuously from the Himalayas to the ocean,
    so the supramundane Noble Eightfold Path flows continuously from
    the arising of right view to the attainment of Nibbāna.
    Although worldly wholesome cittas of virtuous worldlings can also arise through the factors of the Eightfold Path,
    these factors do not have a clear predetermination, as a worldling can change their character and
    turn away from the Dhamma. But in a noble disciple who has
    attained the experience of stream-entry, the path factors become predetermined in
    their destination and flow like a stream leading to Nibbāna.
    The path consciousness of stream-entry has the function of cutting off
    the first three fetters, which are: "personality belief" or wrong view of
    self, doubt in the Three Jewels, and clinging to rites and ceremonies
    with the belief that they can lead to liberation. Further,
    it cuts off all greed, hatred, and delusion that had sufficient power
    to lead to rebirth in an existence lower than the human one. This
    citta also irreversibly eliminates five other cittas, namely: the four cittas rooted in greed
    associated with wrong view, and the citta rooted in delusion
    associated with doubt. One who has experienced stream-entry is guaranteed to attain final
    liberation within a maximum of seven lifetimes and will never
    be reborn in the woeful planes of existence.
</string>
    <string name="textLokutaraWholsome2">
        Path consciousness of once-returning (sakadāgāmimaggacitta):
        This citta is the consciousness associated
with the Noble Eightfold Path that gives access
to the plane of the once-returner. Although this citta does not eradicate any fetters,
        it weakens the grossest forms of sensory desire and ill will. A being
        who has reached this stage will be reborn in this world one more time at most
before attaining liberation.
    </string>
    <string name="textLokutaraWholsome3">
        Path consciousness of non-returning (anāgāmimaggacitta):
One who has reached the third path will never be reborn again
in the sensory plane. If such a person does not attain Arahantship in
        this very life, they will be reborn in a fine-material
world and attain the goal there. The path consciousness of non-returning cuts off the fetters of sensory desire and
         ill will; it also irreversibly suppresses the two cittas rooted in hatred.
    </string>
    <string name="textLokutaraWholsome4">
        Path consciousness of Arahantship (arahattamaggacitta):
An Arahant is a fully liberated person, one
who has destroyed (hata) the enemy (ari) consisting of defilements.
The path consciousness of Arahantship is the citta that leads directly
        to full liberation, to Arahantship. This citta
        destroys the five subtle fetters: desire for fine-material
and immaterial existence, conceit, restlessness,
and ignorance. It also eliminates the remaining types of unwholesome cittas:
        the four rooted in greed, dissociated from views; and the one
        rooted in delusion, associated with restlessness.
    </string>

    <string name="textLokutaraResult1">
    Each path consciousness
    automatically resolves into its corresponding fruit in the same
    cognitive series, immediately following the path. Subsequently, the fruit citta
        can arise many times when the noble disciple enters the meditative attainment of fruition.
    The fruit consciousness, as mentioned earlier, is classified by its type as resultant (vipāka).
        It should be noted that there are no supramundane functional
    (kiriya) cittas. This is because when an Arahant enters the attainment of fruition,
        the cittas that occur in this attainment belong to the class of resultants,
    being the fruits of the supramundane path.
</string>


    <string name="textLokutaraWholsomeKoren1">
    3 ROOTS: \n
    Non-greed \n
    Non-hatred \n
    Non-delusion
    </string>

    <string name="textLokutaraResultKoren1">
    3 ROOTS: \n
    Non-greed \n
    Non-hatred \n
    Non-delusion
    </string>

    <string name="textLokutaraWholsomeFunkciya1">
    FUNCTION: functions as: \n JAVANA
</string>
    <string name="textLokutaraResultFunkciya1">
    FUNCTION: functions as: \n JAVANA
</string>

    <string name="textLokutaraWholsomeKombinaciya1">
    COMBINES WITH \n
        36 CETASIKAS (via 1st jhāna)
        35 CETASIKAS (via 2nd jhāna) absent (vitakka)
        34 CETASIKAS (via 3rd jhāna) absent (vitakka, vicāra)
        33 CETASIKAS (via 4th jhāna) absent (vitakka, vicāra, pīti)
        33 CETASIKAS (via 5th jhāna) absent (vitakka, vicāra, pīti. instead of happiness, equanimity) \n\n

        EXAMPLE OF THE 1ST JHĀNA \n
        UNIVERSALS: \n
        >> 1. Contact (Phassa) \n
        >> 2. Feeling (Vedanā) \n
        >> 3. Perception (Saññā) \n
        >> 4. Volition (Cetanā) \n
        >> 5. One-pointedness (Ekaggatā) \n
        >> 6. Mental life faculty (Jīvitindriya) \n
        >> 7. Attention (Manasikāra) \n\n

        OCCASIONALS: \n
    >> 8. Initial application (Vitakka) \n
    >> 9. Sustained application (Vicāra) \n
    >> 10. Decision (Adhimokkha) \n
    >> 11. Energy (Viriya) \n
    >> 12. Rapture (Pīti) \n
    >> 13. Desire-to-do (Chanda) \n\n

        UNIVERSAL BEAUTIFUL: \n
    >> 14. Faith (Saddhā) \n
    >> 15. Mindfulness (Sati) \n
    >> 16. Moral shame (Hiri) \n
    >> 17. Moral dread (Ottappa) \n
    >> 18. Non-greed (Alobha) \n
    >> 19. Non-hatred (Adosa) \n
    >> 20. Neutrality of mind (Tatramajjhattatā) \n
    >> 21. Tranquility of mental body (Kāyapassaddhi) \n
    >> 22. Tranquility of consciousness (Cittapassaddhi) \n
    >> 23. Lightness of mental body (Kāyalahutā) \n
    >> 24. Lightness of consciousness (Cittalahutā) \n
    >> 25. Malleability of mental body (Kāyamudutā) \n
    >> 26. Malleability of consciousness (Cittamudutā) \n
    >> 27. Wieldiness of mental body (Kāyakammaññatā) \n
    >> 28. Wieldiness of consciousness (Cittakammaññatā) \n
    >> 29. Proficiency of mental body (Kāyapāguññatā) \n
    >> 30. Proficiency of consciousness (Cittapāguññatā) \n
    >> 31. Rectitude of mental body (Kāyujjukatā) \n
    >> 32. Rectitude of consciousness (Cittujjukatā) \n\n

        OCCASIONAL BEAUTIFUL: \n
        ABSTINENCES \n
    >> 33. Right speech (Sammāvācā) \n
    >> 34. Right action (Sammākammanta) \n
    >> 35. Right livelihood (Sammā-ājīva) \n\n

        ILLIMITABLES \n
    >> ABSENT. Compassion (Karuṇā) \n
    >> ABSENT. Altruistic joy (Muditā) \n
    >> 36. Wisdom (Pañña) \n
    </string>
    <string name="textLokutaraResultKombinaciya1">
    COMBINES WITH \n
        36 CETASIKAS (via 1st jhāna)
        35 CETASIKAS (via 2nd jhāna) absent (vitakka)
        34 CETASIKAS (via 3rd jhāna) absent (vitakka, vicāra)
        33 CETASIKAS (via 4th jhāna) absent (vitakka, vicāra, pīti)
        33 CETASIKAS (via 5th jhāna) absent (vitakka, vicāra, pīti. instead of happiness, equanimity) \n\n

        EXAMPLE OF THE 1ST JHĀNA \n
        UNIVERSALS: \n
        >> 1. Contact (Phassa) \n
        >> 2. Feeling (Vedanā) \n
        >> 3. Perception (Saññā) \n
        >> 4. Volition (Cetanā) \n
        >> 5. One-pointedness (Ekaggatā) \n
        >> 6. Mental life faculty (Jīvitindriya) \n
        >> 7. Attention (Manasikāra) \n\n

        OCCASIONALS: \n
    >> 8. Initial application (Vitakka) \n
    >> 9. Sustained application (Vicāra) \n
    >> 10. Decision (Adhimokkha) \n
    >> 11. Energy (Viriya) \n
    >> 12. Rapture (Pīti) \n
    >> 13. Desire-to-do (Chanda) \n\n

        UNIVERSAL BEAUTIFUL: \n
    >> 14. Faith (Saddhā) \n
    >> 15. Mindfulness (Sati) \n
    >> 16. Moral shame (Hiri) \n
    >> 17. Moral dread (Ottappa) \n
    >> 18. Non-greed (Alobha) \n
    >> 19. Non-hatred (Adosa) \n
    >> 20. Neutrality of mind (Tatramajjhattatā) \n
    >> 21. Tranquility of mental body (Kāyapassaddhi) \n
    >> 22. Tranquility of consciousness (Cittapassaddhi) \n
    >> 23. Lightness of mental body (Kāyalahutā) \n
    >> 24. Lightness of consciousness (Cittalahutā) \n
    >> 25. Malleability of mental body (Kāyamudutā) \n
    >> 26. Malleability of consciousness (Cittamudutā) \n
    >> 27. Wieldiness of mental body (Kāyakammaññatā) \n
    >> 28. Wieldiness of consciousness (Cittakammaññatā) \n
    >> 29. Proficiency of mental body (Kāyapāguññatā) \n
    >> 30. Proficiency of consciousness (Cittapāguññatā) \n
    >> 31. Rectitude of mental body (Kāyujjukatā) \n
    >> 32. Rectitude of consciousness (Cittujjukatā) \n\n

        OCCASIONAL BEAUTIFUL: \n
        ABSTINENCES \n
    >> 33. Right speech (Sammāvācā) \n
    >> 34. Right action (Sammākammanta) \n
    >> 35. Right livelihood (Sammā-ājīva) \n\n

        ILLIMITABLES \n
    >> ABSENT. Compassion (Karuṇā) \n
    >> ABSENT. Altruistic joy (Muditā) \n
    >> 36. Wisdom (Pañña) \n
    </string>



</resources>