<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="buttonAbhidhammaChetasika">54 \n mental factors\n(chetasika)</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt">1 \ncontact \n(phassa)</string>
    <string name="universal">Universal 7</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_harakteristika">Characteristic</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_function">Function</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_proyavlenie">Manifestation</string>
    <string name="button_kontakt_prichina">The immediate cause</string>

    <string name="text_for_kontakt"><b>CONTACT (phassa):</b> The word phassa comes from the verb
phusati, meaning "to touch", but contact should not
be understood as a simple physical effect of an object on
the physical ability [touch]. Rather, it
is a mental factor through which consciousness mentally "touches"
an object that has just appeared, thereby initiating
a whole cognitive event.</string>

    <string name="text_for_kontakt_harakteristika"><b>CHARACTERISTIC:</b> touch</string>
    <string name="text_for_kontakt_function"><b>FUNCTION:</b> the collision of consciousness and object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_kontakt_proyavlenie"><b>MANIFESTATION:</b> the coincidence of consciousness with sensory ability.</string>
    <string name="text_for_kontakt_prichina"><b>THE IMMEDIATE CAUSE:</b> the object field that has come into focus.</string>

    <string name="button_chuvstvo">2 \nfeeling \n(vedana)</string>

    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo">FEELING (vedana): Feeling is the mental factor
that the object feels, it is the emotional tone
in which the object is experienced. The Pali word Vedana
does not mean emotion (which is a complex phenomenon
involving a set of accompanying mental factors),
it is the most elementary emotional quality of experience, which
can be pleasant, painful or neutral. \n While other mental factors
outlive the object only indirectly, the feeling experiences it
directly and completely. In this regard, other mental factors
they are compared to the cook who prepares a dish for the king
and only tastes it during cooking, while the
feeling is compared to the king himself, who enjoys
this food as much as he wants.</string>

    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: Sensitivity</string>
    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_function">FUNCTION: experiencing, or enjoying the desired object directly.</string>
    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION:  savoring associated mental factors.</string>
    <string name="text_for_chuvstvo_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: contact.</string>

    <string name="button_vospriyatie">3 \nPerception \n(saňňā)</string>

    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie">PERCEPTION (saññā): His mode of action is comparable
to the carpenterёs recognition of certain types of wood by means of marks placed [earlier] on each of them.</string>

    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: distinguishing the qualities of an object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_function">FUNCTION: recognition of what was perceived earlier.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: interpretation of an object through previously perceived features.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vospriyatie_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: the object as it appears to perception.</string>

    <string name="button_volenie">4 \nVolition \n(chetanā)</string>

    <string name="text_for_volenie">WOLITION (chetanā): Chetanā - from the same root as
and citta, is a mental factor that deals with the actualization of the goal, that is, with the voluntary or
volitional aspect of cognition. Therefore it is translated as “will.” The comments explain
that chetana organizes the associated mental factors in the process of their influence on the object.
         As the main student repeats
your own lesson and also forces other students
repeat their lessons, and the will, starting to work in relation to its object, also forces the associated
mental states to perform their own tasks.
Volition is the most important mental factor in the generation of kamma, since it is volition that determines
ethical quality of action.</string>

    <string name="text_for_volenie_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTICS: state of volition.</string>
    <string name="text_for_volenie_function">FUNCTION: accumulate (kamma).</string>
    <string name="text_for_volenie_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: coordination.</string>
    <string name="text_for_volenie_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: associated conditions.</string>

    <string name="button_odnonapravlennost">5 \nUnidirectionality \n(ekaggatā)</string>

    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost">ONE-DIRECTIONALITY (ekaggatā): This is unification
mind on the object. Although this factor reaches its expressiveness only in the jhanas, where it functions as a factor
jhānas, the Abhidhamma teaches that the germ of this ability
to mental unification is present in all types of consciousness, even the most rudimentary.
In them it functions as the factor which fixes the mind on the object. </string>

    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: non-wandering or non-distraction.</string>
    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_function">FUNCTION: collect, or combine, associated states.</string>
    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: like peace.</string>
    <string name="text_for_odnonapravlennost_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: happiness</string>

    <string name="button_jivitindriya">6 \nMental life-controlling ability \n(jivitindriya)</string>

    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya">JIVITINRIYA: There are two types of control
life-faculties: mental, which animates associated mental states, and physical, which
animates material phenomena. But as cetasika
This means only the mental life-controlling ability.</string>

    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTICS: maintaining associated mental states.</string>
    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_function">FUNCTION: to cause associated mental states to occur.</string>
    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: establishing the presence of associated mental states.</string>
    <string name="text_for_jivitindriya_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: mental states that need to be maintained.</string>

    <string name="buttonAbhidhammaChetasikaEtichVerFakt">13 \n Ethically Verifiable Mental Factors \n(Annasamānachetasika)</string>

    <string name="button_vnimanie">7 \nAttention \n(manasikara)</string>

    <string name="text_for_vnimanie">ATTENTION (manasikāra): this is mental
the factor responsible for directing the mind towards an object, whereby the object becomes presented to the consciousness.
     Attention - how
the ship`s rudder, which guides it to its destination,
or like a charioteer who sends well-trained
horses (i.e. associated states) towards their destination (object). Mental factor
manasikāra must be distinguished from vitakka: at that time
how manasikāra directs the accompanying mental
factors to an object, Vittaka applies them to the object. Manasikāra is an obligatory cognitive factor,
         present in all states of consciousness; vitakka - special
alised factor that is not mandatory for
process of cognition.</string>

    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTICS: leading (sārana) of associated mental states towards an object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_function">FUNCTION: bind associated states to an object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: manifests itself as a confrontation with the object.</string>
    <string name="text_for_vnimanie_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: object.</string>
    <string name="buttonChetasikaKontaktKombinaciya">Association with consciousness</string>
    <string name="textButtonChittas">89 or 121 \n types of consciousness \n (chitta)</string>

    <string name="text_for_chittas">
        The Pali word "chitta" comes from the verb
root chiti - “to know, to know.” \n Commentators define citta in three ways: as an agent, as an instrument
and as an activity. As an agent, citta is that which cognizes the object (āramman am cinteti ti cittam). \n As an instrument, citta is that by which the accompanying mental factors cognize the object (etena chintenti ti
chittam). \n As the activity of citta itself is nothing other than
as a process of cognition of an object (chintanamattam chittam). \n
The third definition, given in terms of activity, is considered the most appropriate of them; that is, citta is fundamentally the activity, or process, of cognition, or knowledge, of an object. It is not an agent or a tool,
having actual existence in itself, separate from activity or cognition. Definitions in terms of agent and instrument are proposed to refute the misconception of those who believe that the permanent personality, or ego, is the agent and instrument of knowledge. Buddhist thinkers through
These definitions indicate that it is not the personality that carries out the act of cognition, but citta, or consciousness. This citta
is nothing more than an act of cognition, and this act is necessarily temporary, marked by emergence and disappearance. \n
While citta has the sole characteristic of knowing the object, a characteristic which remains the same in all its various manifestations, the Abhidhamma distinguishes different types of citta. These
the types, also called cittas, number eighty-nine, or, if classified more closely, one hundred and twenty-one. What we usually think about
as consciousness, is in fact a series of cittas - instantaneous acts of consciousness,
        occurring in such rapid succession that we are unable to notice the individual moments of their occurrence,
        belonging to different types. The Abhidhamma not only distinguishes these types of consciousness,
        but, more importantly, it also shows them in a certain ordered system, a single and closely intertwined whole.
</string>

    <string name="text_for_chitta_harakteristika">CHARACTERISTIC: knowledge of the object
(vijānana).</string>
    <string name="text_for_chitta_function">FUNCTION: to be a “forerunner” (pubbangama)
mental factors, in the sense that citta predominates
above them and always accompanied by them.</string>
    <string name="text_for_chitta_proyavlenie">MANIFESTATION: the way in which it appears to the experience of the meditator is
         it is a continuous connectedness of processes (sandhana).</string>
    <string name="text_for_chitta_prichina">IMMEDIATE CAUSE: mental-material (nāmarupa),
         because consciousness cannot arise
one, in the complete absence of mental factors and material phenomena.</string>

    <string name="text_for_chittasiki">
        CHETASIKAS are mental phenomena that occur in direct connection with chitta,
         or consciousness, and will perform more specific tasks in the general act of cognition, thereby helping the chitta.
         Mental factors cannot arise without citta,
         just as citta cannot be completely separated from mental factors.
         But, despite the fact that functionally these two types of realities are independent,
         Chitta is considered as the main one because mental factors help in the knowledge of the object
         depending on citta, which is the main cognitive element. \n
The relationship between the Citta and the Cetasikas is comparable to the relationship between a king and his retinue.
         Although they say: “The king is coming,” the king does not come alone, he always comes accompanied by his assistants.
         Likewise, whenever citta arises, it never arises alone,
         and always accompanied by his retinue - a cetasik.
</string>

</resources>