<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="hintText">Click on the verse to see a detailed description.</string>
    <string name="button3Dhammapada">3 \n He abused me, he beat me, he defeated me, he robbed me, in those who harbour such thoughts hatred will never cease.</string>
    <string name="button4Dhammapada">4 \n He abused me, he beat me, he defeated me, he robbed me, in those who do not harbour such thoughts hatred will cease.</string>
    <string name="button5Dhammapada">5 \n Hatred is never appeased by hatred in this world. Only the absence of hatred (non-hatred) calms hatred. This is an eternal law.</string>
    <string name="textViev3Dhammapada">
        \n TISSATHERA VATTHU \n \n
        <b> Akkocchi maṃ avadhi maṃ, \n \n</b>
        <i> He abused me, he beat me, \n \n</i>
        <b> ajini maṃ ahāsi me; \n \n</b>
        <i> he defeated me, he robbed me,\n \n</i>
        <b> Ye ca taṃ upanayhanti, \n \n</b>
        <i> those who harbour such thoughts \n \n</i>
        <b> veraṃ tesaṃ na sammati. \n \n</b>
        <i> hatred will never cease. \n \n \n</i>
            <b>The Parable of thera Tissa</b>\n\n
During his stay at the Jetavana Monastery in Savatti, the Buddha recited these verses (3 and 4) in connection with the story of thera Tissa. \n \n
Tissa, the son of Buddha`s maternal aunt, lived with Buddha at one time. He became a monk only in his old age, but he pretended to be a senior monk and was very pleased when visiting monks asked his permission to do him a favor. On the other hand, he did not fulfill the duties assigned to junior monks. In addition, he often quarreled with the younger monks. If someone reproached him for such behavior, he complained to the Buddha, crying, dissatisfied and upset. Others began to behave in a similar way in the presence of the Buddha. The Buddha instructed them not to harbor hostile thoughts, since hatred can be defeated only if one does not harbor hatred. \n
Then the Buddha recited these verses. \n \n \n \n \n \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="textViev4Dhammapada">
        \n TISSATHERA VATTHU \n \n
        <b> Akkocchi maṃ avadhi maṃ, \n \n</b>
        <i> He abused me, he beat me, \n \n</i>
        <b> ajini maṃ ahāsi me; \n \n</b>
        <i> he defeated me, he robbed me, \n \n</i>
        <b> Ye ca taṃ nupanayhanti, \n \n</b>
        <i> those who harbour such thoughts \n \n</i>
        <b> veraṃ tesūpasammati. \n \n</b>
        <i> hatred will cease. \n \n \n </i>
            <b>The Parable of thera Tissa</b>\n\n
During his stay at the Jetavana Monastery in Savatti, the Buddha recited these verses (3 and 4) in connection with the story of thera Tissa. \n \n
Tissa, the son of Buddha`s maternal aunt, lived with Buddha at one time. He became a monk only in his old age, but he pretended to be a senior monk and was very pleased when visiting monks asked his permission to do him a favor. On the other hand, he did not fulfill the duties assigned to junior monks. In addition, he often quarreled with the younger monks. If someone reproached him for such behavior, he complained to the Buddha, crying, dissatisfied and upset. Others began to behave in a similar way in the presence of the Buddha. The Buddha instructed them not to harbor hostile thoughts, since hatred can be defeated only if one does not harbor hatred. \n
Then the Buddha recited these verses. \n \n \n \n \n \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="textViev5Dhammapada">
        \n KALYAKKHINI VATTHU \n \n
        <b>Na hi verena verāni, \n</b>
        <i>Не ненавистью, ненависть \n Not by hatred, hatred \n \n</i>
        <b>sammantīdha kudācanaṃ; \n</b>
        <i>успокаивается здесь когда-либо \n calms down here ever \n \n</i>
        <b>Averena ca sammanti, \n</b>
        <i>Отсутствием ненависти успокаивается \n By absence of hatred calm down \n \n</i>
        <b>esa dhammo sanantano. \n</b>
        <i>Эта дхамма извечна \n This dhamma is eternal \n \n</i>
        \n \n The Parable of Kalayakkhini \n \n
During his stay at the Jetavana Monastery in Savatti, the Buddha recited this verse in connection with the story of a barren woman and her rival. There was once a landlord whose wife was infertile, and later he took another wife. The feud began when the eldest wife provoked the miscarriage of another wife, who died during childbirth.  \n
In the following lives they became: a chicken and a cat, a cow and a female leopard, and, finally, the daughter of a noble husband from Savatti and a cannibal named Kali. The ogress (Kalayakkhili) set off in pursuit of the woman with the child when the latter found out that the Buddha was reading a religious sermon at the Jetavana monastery nearby. The woman turned to him for help and put her son at his feet for protection. The ogre was stopped at the entrance by the guardian spirit of the monastery and forbade her to enter. She was called later, and the Buddha reprimanded both her and the woman.   \n
The Buddha told them about the enmity that began between them when they were wives of an ordinary husband, and continued when they became a chicken and a cat, and then a cow and a female leopard. This made them realize that hatred can only generate even greater hatred, which can only stop through friendship, understanding and goodwill.  \n  \n  \n  \n
 \n
    </string>
    <string name="button6Dhammapada">6 \n Still others don`t understand
that we must perish in this world,
those who understand this
their quarrels subside.</string>
    <string name="textViewAbout6Dhammapada">\n KOSAMBAKA VATTHU \n \n <b>Pare ca na vijānanti, \n</b> <i>другие не осознают \n others don`t realize \n \n</i> <b>mayam ettha yamāmase; \n</b> <i>мы здесь умрем \n we\'ll die here \n \n</i> <b>Ye ca tattha vijānanti, \n</b> <i>Те кто осознают \n Those who are aware \n \n</i> <b>tato sammanti medhagā. \n</b> <i>от этого успокаиваются ссоры \n This calms down quarrels \n \n</i> \n \n Притча о монахах из Косамби \n \n Во время пребывания в монастыре Джетавана в Саватти, Будда произнес этот стих в связи с историей о монахах из Косамби. Монахи из Косамби разделились. Одни последовали за учителем Винайи, а другие за учителем Дхаммы. Они часто спорили между собой. Даже Будда не мог положить конец этим спорам. Поэтому он ушел от них и провел васса (период дождей) в одиночестве в роще Раккхита, что возле леса Палилейа. Там Будду ждал слон Палилейа. Мирские ученики из Косамби, узнав причину ухода Будды, отказались приносить подание оставшимся [в монастыре] монахам. Это заставило их признать ошибку, и между ними воцарился мир. Но мирские ученики все равно не относились к ним так же уважительно, как раньше, пока они не покаялись в своих ошибках перед Буддой. Но Будда был далеко, и была как раз середина периода дождей, поэтому монахи Косамби провели период дождей в нужде и лишениях. По окончании периода дождей почтенный Ананда и пятьсот монахов пошли к Будде и передали ему послание от Аннатхапиндики и других мирских учеников, которые умоляли его вернуться. Когда пришло время, Будда вернулся в монастырь Джетавана в Саватти. Монахи последовали за ним и упали к его ногам, каясь в своих ошибках. Будда укорил их за непослушание. Он наказал им помнить, что однажды они все должны умереть, и поэтому они должны прекратить ссоры и перестать вести себя так, как будто им не суждено умереть. Затем Будда произнес следующий стих. \n \n The parable of the monks from Kosambi \n \n While staying at the Jetavana Monastery at Savatti, the Buddha recited this verse in connection with the story of the monks from Kosambi. The monks from Kosambi were divided. Some followed the Vinaya teacher and others followed the Dhamma teacher. They often argued among themselves. Even the Buddha could not put an end to these disputes. So he left them and spent the vassa (rainy season) alone in the grove of Rakkhita near the forest of Palileya. There the elephant Palileya was waiting for the Buddha. Lay disciples from Kosambi, having learned the reason for the departure of the Buddha, refused to bring tribute to the remaining [in the monastery] monks. This forced them to admit their mistake, and peace reigned between them. But the lay disciples still did not treat them with the same respect as before, until they repented of their mistakes before the Buddha. But the Buddha was far away, and it was just in the middle of the rainy season, so the monks of Kosambi spent the rainy season in need and deprivation. At the end of the rainy season, Venerable Ananda and five hundred monks went to the Buddha and gave him a message from Annathapindika and other worldly disciples, who begged him to return. When the time came, the Buddha returned to the Jetavana Monastery at Savatti. The monks followed him and fell at his feet, repenting of their mistakes. Buddha reproached them for their disobedience. He instructed them to remember that one day they must all die, and therefore they must stop quarreling and stop acting as if they were not destined to die. Then the Buddha spoke the following verse. \n \n \n \n \n</string>

</resources>