<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="textLive6">\n \n
In the picture, the Bodhisattva holds a swan in his hands, protecting it from his cousin Devadatta, who pierced the swan with an arrow and demands the return of the prey. \n \n
I couldn`t find the source of this plot; is this story canonical? I don`t know either (if anyone knows, please share). \n \n
The story is often told like this:
One day Siddhartha was walking through the forest with his cousin Devadatta, who was carrying a bow and arrows, suddenly Devadatta saw a flying swan and shot at it, the arrow wounded the swan and it fell down somewhere nearby. Both boys ran to look for the bird. Siddhartha found the swan first and, to his surprise, found that it was still alive. He carefully pulled the arrow out of the wing, then got some juice from the leaves and put them on the wound to stop the bleeding. When Devadatta came, he began to claim the swan, Prince Siddhartha refused to give it to him. Devadatta became very angry. ``Give me my bird! I shot him,`` Devadatta said.
``No, I`m not going to give it to you,`` said the prince. ``If you had killed him, he would have been yours. But since he is only wounded and is still alive, he belongs to me.``
Devadatta did not agree with this. Then Siddhartha suggested, ``let`s go to the sage and ask him who really owns the swan.`` Devadatta agreed.
The sage, having heard both versions of the boys` story, said: ``Life must certainly belong to the one who is trying to save it; life cannot belong to the one who is only trying to destroy it. The wounded swan rightfully belongs to Siddhartha.``
\n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="textLive7">\n \n
In the picture, the Bodhisattva demonstrates his archery skills. \n \n

At the time when Siddhartha came of age, his father was haunted by a prophecy that if the prince preferred worldly life, he would become a world-ruling king, but if, after leaving home, he preferred the life of a hermit, he would become Buddha. Preferring the first option, Shuddhodana surrounded his son with numerous luxurious lifestyles, building three palaces for him, each designed for a specific season of the year, where the prince enjoyed himself in the company of his friends. And on the advice of the elders, the father decided to marry his son: “having experienced the sweetness gained through women, he will not leave home. Thanks to this, our family, [originating from] the Lords of the world, will not be interrupted and will remain revered and not blamed by the rulers of all neighboring kingdoms.” Then King Shuddhodana said: “If so, it is necessary, according to your desire, to find a maiden worthy of a prince.”
Then he ordered to announce to all the Shakya princes: “Dear princes, my son has come of age and now all the princes must provide their daughters, who are suitable in age, to my palace.” \n
   When the princes received a message from King Shuddhodana, they refused to comply with his request, answering: “Siddhattha lives only for pleasures, does not learn anything. What will he do if a war suddenly happens?” \n
The Raja sent for the future Buddha and said to him: “Your relatives, my dear, say that you study nothing, spending all your time in pleasure. What do you think about this?” \n
“Your Majesty, there is no art that I need to learn. Order an announcement throughout the city to the beat of drums that I am going to show my skills. For seven days I will demonstrate my skills to my relatives.”
The Raja did just that. The Bodhisatta gathered skilled archers who could split even a hair in two, and they shot with lightning speed; In the presence of many spectators, the prince showed his relatives skills in 12 arts, and none of those archers could surpass him." \n \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="textLive8">
        The marriage of Siddhartha and Yashodhara is depicted. \n \n
        Yashodhara was the daughter of King Suppabuddha and Pamita, the sister of Siddhartha`s father, King Shuddhodana.
        Her father was from the Koliya family, her mother came from the Shakya family.
        Shakya and Kolya came from the clan of the solar deynasty.
        The absence of a similar and equal other family in the region indicated that members of these two royal families married only among themselves. \n \n
After Siddhartha showed skill in archery, all the reproaches and doubts about him from the royal relatives were replaced by admiration and praise, they said:
        “Never before in the history of the Shakyas were there such witnesses to feats of skill as we were at the present time.”
"And they willingly sent a multitude of their daughters for the royal betrothal."
When choosing from a large number of princesses, Siddhartha`s gaze fell on Yashodhara. \n \n
     </string>
    <string name="textLive9">
         Depicted: “four meetings” that prompted Siddhartha to renounce worldly life. \n \n

In the Pali Canon there may be no mention of specific historical circumstances indicating the events occurring in the tradition of the "four meetings" contained in the commentaries and later texts. In the canon you can find the sutta: Mahapadana Sutta: Great Discourse on the Line of Buddhas DN14, which contains the story of Buddha Vipasi, where the description of the “four meetings” is like two peas in a pod similar to the traditional description of the meetings of Siddhartha. \n \n
There is also a sutta in the Canon: Sukhumala Sutta: Subtlety
AN 3.39 in which the Buddha describes his luxurious life in the three palaces, among which he had these thoughts: \n \n
"(1) In the midst of such luxury and refinement of life, a thought came to me: "The untaught common man, being himself subject to old age and unable to escape old age, feels rejected, humiliated, disgusted when he sees one who is old, [but in this case] "He does not notice his own situation. After all, I, too, am subject to old age and am not able to avoid old age. Since this is so, if I felt rejection, humiliation, disgust at the sight of someone who is old, then it would be inappropriate for me. "And when I thought about it, my youthful intoxication was completely abandoned.\n \n
(2) [The thought came to me]: “The untrained ordinary person, being himself susceptible to illness and unable to avoid illness, feels rejected, humiliated, disgusted when he sees someone who is sick, [but in this case] he does not notice his own situation . After all, I, too, am susceptible to illness and am unable to avoid illness. Since this is so, if I felt rejection, humiliation, disgust at the sight of someone who was sick, then it would be inappropriate for me.” And when I thought about this, my intoxication with health was completely abandoned. \n \n
(3) [A thought came to me]: “The untrained ordinary person, being himself subject to death and unable to escape death, feels rejected, humiliated, disgusted when he sees someone who has died, [but in this case] he does not notice his own situation . After all, I, too, am subject to death and am unable to avoid death. Since this is so, if I felt rejection, humiliation, disgust at the sight of someone who died, then it would be inappropriate for me.” And when I thought about this, my intoxication with life was completely thrown away…" \n \n

It is impossible to say for sure whether the “four meetings” are a legend, an external manifestation of an experience that arose as a result of an internal search, or whether everything really happened exactly as the story that has come down to us tells. One thing is certain: the story of the four encounters condenses some of the fundamental teachings of the Buddha very clearly. \n \n
This story is often told like this: \n \n
  When Siddhartha was twenty-nine years old, after enjoying the comfort and luxury of palace life, accompanied by many princesses led by the chief queen Yashodhara, he one day wanted to visit the royal garden. So, he sent for the charioteer and ordered: “Charioteer, prepare the chariot! I will go to the Royal Garden." “Okay,” the charioteer answered and prepared the royal chariot. And the bodhisattva went to the royal garden. "\n\n
When the Bodhisattva had covered some distance on the way to the royal garden, the devas agreed among themselves; “The time is approaching when Prince Siddhartha will become Buddha. Let us show him sights that will make him renounce the world and become a hermit.” So they did, turning one of their sons into a emaciated old man with rotting teeth and gray hair, his gnarled body supported by a crutch. But only the future Buddha and his charioteer could see this old man.
Then the Bodhisatta asked the charioteer: “What kind of person is this whose hair is not like other people?” Then, hearing the servant`s answer, he said: “It`s a disgrace to this life, since the aging of the one born is obvious!” Shocked to his very heart, he ordered the chariot to be turned back and returned to his palace. \n \n

"Why did my son come back so quickly?" - asked the Raja.
“He saw an old man,” was the answer.
“And when he sees the old man, he will leave the world,” the Raja exclaimed, “you want my death!” Quickly prepare performances to show to my son. As long as he enjoys worldly pleasures, he will not leave the world." Then, increasing the number of guards, he placed them in all directions of the world at intervals of half a yojana. \n \n
And again, one fine day, the future Buddha was heading to a pleasure park and saw a seriously ill man, into whom one of the deities had turned; Having asked the same question as before, he received an answer and, shocked, returned to the palace. Raja again found out what was going on and gave similar instructions: he increased the guard. \n \n
And one more time the future Buddha was on his way to a pleasure park and saw a dead man shown by the deities, he asked a question, received an answer and returned to his palace stunned. The Raja again found out what was going on and again increased the number of guards, placing them around the palace at a distance of a yojana. \n \n
Finally, the future Buddha, heading to the pleasure park,
        saw a man who had left the world. He was neatly and decently dressed.
        The Bodhisatta asked the charioteer: “Friend, what kind of person is this?”
        At that time there was no Buddha in the world and the charioteer did not know what a
        hermit was and what his symptoms were, nevertheless, inspired by the deities, he said:
        “This is a hermit” and described the benefits of leaving the world. On this day, the thought of
        leaving the world arose in the future Buddha. \n \n \n \n \n
     </string>

    <string name="description8">8. Marriage of Siddhartha and Yashodhara.</string>
    <string name="description9">9. Four meetings.</string>
</resources>