<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="saveSwan">\n \n
In the picture, the Bodhisattva holds a swan in his hands, protecting it from his cousin Devadatta, who pierced the swan with an arrow and demands the return of the prey. \n \n
I couldn`t find the source of this plot; is this story canonical? I don`t know either (if anyone knows, please share). \n \n
The story is often told like this:
One day Siddhartha was walking through the forest with his cousin Devadatta, who was carrying a bow and arrows, suddenly Devadatta saw a flying swan and shot at it, the arrow wounded the swan and it fell down somewhere nearby. Both boys ran to look for the bird. Siddhartha found the swan first and, to his surprise, found that it was still alive. He carefully pulled the arrow out of the wing, then got some juice from the leaves and put them on the wound to stop the bleeding. When Devadatta came, he began to claim the swan, Prince Siddhartha refused to give it to him. Devadatta became very angry. ``Give me my bird! I shot him,`` Devadatta said.
``No, I`m not going to give it to you,`` said the prince. ``If you had killed him, he would have been yours. But since he is only wounded and is still alive, he belongs to me.``
Devadatta did not agree with this. Then Siddhartha suggested, ``let`s go to the sage and ask him who really owns the swan.`` Devadatta agreed.
The sage, having heard both versions of the boys` story, said: ``Life must certainly belong to the one who is trying to save it; life cannot belong to the one who is only trying to destroy it. The wounded swan rightfully belongs to Siddhartha.``
\n \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="showAbilities">\n \n
In the picture, the Bodhisattva demonstrates his archery skills. \n \n

At the time when Siddhartha came of age, his father was haunted by a prophecy that if the prince preferred worldly life, he would become a world-ruling king, but if, after leaving home, he preferred the life of a hermit, he would become Buddha. Preferring the first option, Shuddhodana surrounded his son with numerous luxurious lifestyles, building three palaces for him, each designed for a specific season of the year, where the prince enjoyed himself in the company of his friends. And on the advice of the elders, the father decided to marry his son: “having experienced the sweetness gained through women, he will not leave home. Thanks to this, our family, [originating from] the Lords of the world, will not be interrupted and will remain revered and not blamed by the rulers of all neighboring kingdoms.” Then King Shuddhodana said: “If so, it is necessary, according to your desire, to find a maiden worthy of a prince.”
Then he ordered to announce to all the Shakya princes: “Dear princes, my son has come of age and now all the princes must provide their daughters, who are suitable in age, to my palace.” \n
   When the princes received a message from King Shuddhodana, they refused to comply with his request, answering: “Siddhattha lives only for pleasures, does not learn anything. What will he do if a war suddenly happens?” \n
The Raja sent for the future Buddha and said to him: “Your relatives, my dear, say that you study nothing, spending all your time in pleasure. What do you think about this?” \n
“Your Majesty, there is no art that I need to learn. Order an announcement throughout the city to the beat of drums that I am going to show my skills. For seven days I will demonstrate my skills to my relatives.”
The Raja did just that. The Bodhisatta gathered skilled archers who could split even a hair in two, and they shot with lightning speed; In the presence of many spectators, the prince showed his relatives skills in 12 arts, and none of those archers could surpass him." \n \n \n \n</string>
</resources>