<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">
    <string name="buttonNissayaText">petition (Nissaya) \n Being under guardianship</string>
    <string name="nisayaText">
        \n <b>Ācariyo me bhante hohi \n</b>
           <i>Venerable one, be my teacher \n \n</i>
           <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n \n
           <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n \n \n </string>

    <string name="buttonPurMoralText">Fourfold purification of morality</string>
    <string name="purMoralText"><b>Four-part purification of morality</b> \n \n
The texts define morality (sīla) not simply as the observance of vows, but also all activities that form the basis for achieving higher states (samadhi and vipassana): \n \n
Morality is essence (sīla) in the sense of composition (sīlana). What is this layout? This is either coordination (samādhāna), meaning consistency of action with the body, etc. due to morality, or it is holding (upadhāraṇa), meaning the state of foundation (ādhāra) in view of the fact that it serves as the foundation for wholesome states. \n \n
A four-part cleansing of morality must be carried out: \n \n

     1) The morality of purification by accepted training vows (by status: samanera or bhikkhu). This also includes visiting appropriate places and engaging in appropriate leisure activities. The best “leisure” is to stay in the 4 pillars of awareness. \n \n

     2) The morality of training control abilities. Do not grow in perceived images along all 6 doors of perception, which cause thirst, anger and delusion. \n \n
     3) The morality of earning a living. Do not earn a living in a way unsuitable for a hermit: making hints, pretending to be a person of modest desires in order to get even more later, and so on. Ideal: only what is served. \n \n

     4) The morality of using monastic necessities. See next chapter below. \n \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="buttonUseMonksThings">Reflection when using monastic needs, proper consideration of them</string>
    <string name="useMonksThings"><b>Reflection when using monastic needs, proper consideration of them</b> \n \n
With wise deliberation, he uses robes only for protection from cold, for protection from high temperatures, for protection from contact with gadflies, flies, wind, heat and crawling
creatures, and only to hide intimate parts of the body. Wisely considering, he eats food from alms not for entertainment, not for intoxication, not for splendor, not for beauty, but only for the durability and duration of this body, to stop discomfort, to maintain life in purity: “So I will stop the old sensations and I will not allow new ones to appear; I will be healthy and not blameworthy, I will live in comfort." \n \n
Thinking wisely, he uses the dwelling only for the purpose of protection from cold, high temperatures, gadflies, flies, wind, heat and crawling creatures, only for the purpose of sheltering from the dangers of the climate and the joy of seclusion. \n \n
With wise deliberation, he uses medicines only for protection against painful feelings that arise and for complete resistance to painful influences. \n \n

Consideration has two types: during the receipt of needs and during their use. The use is also blameless for the one who, while taking on robes, etc. *as a gift+ considers them either as *mere+ elements or as disgusting,5 and then sets them aside
side for future use; similarly in the case of someone who does this during the direct use of them. \n \n
There are four uses of monastic necessities (robes, food, shelter and medicine): like stolen, like debt, like inheritance and like master. The use of necessities by those who are immoral, even if he sits in the midst of the Community, is called


The use of them without reflection by those who are moral is “use like duty.” So, reflection on clothes should be done every time they are used, just like food - piece by piece. Anyone who cannot do this *should conduct reflection+ before eating, after eating, in the first watch
night, in the middle watch of the night and in the last watch of the night. If it is already dawn, and the monk has not yet undertaken the practice of reflecting on clothes and food, then he finds himself in the position of one who uses necessity like duty. Similarly, reflection should be made in relation to housing - every time it is used. One must also consciously accept and
use medications; there will be an offense only if one uses them without awareness after consciously accepting them, but there will be no offense in knowingly using them after accepting them without awareness. \n \n

The use of necessities by the seven types in training (sekkha; from stream-entered to non-returner) is called “use like an inheritance,” since they are the sons of the Buddha, and they use the necessities as heirs of their father to whom they previously belonged. But how so? Whose needs are used: the Blessed One or the worldly followers? Although they are provided by lay followers, in
in reality they belong to the Blessed One, for he allowed them. This is why
necessities that essentially belong to the Blessed One are used. In confirmation of this is the Dhammadayada Sutta (M. 3). \n \n
The use of necessities by those whose vices have been destroyed is called “use like a master,” for such individuals have freed themselves from the slavery of craving *having thereby become
masters+. \n \n

Regarding these uses: use like a master and use like an inheritance are permissible. What cannot be said about use like debt, much less about use like stolen. But reflective use
moral is free from debt, because it is opposite to use, like debt, or is also included in use, like inheritance. For he who has
morality is also called being in training due to adherence to it. \n \n

Also: as long as using like a master is the best, then when a monk fulfills the morality of considering necessities, he should strive for this best and
use necessities only after reflecting on them. In addition it says:\n\n

“Truly a wise disciple \nWho listens to that Dhamma, \n
What was given to the Exalted Ones, \n Uses food, shelters \n
And even water for washing clothes \n Only after consideration” (Sn. 391). \n




“Like a drop of water \nOn a lotus leaf—\n
The monk is not tainted by all this:\n

No food, no shelter, \nNot even water
For simple washing of clothes” (Sn. 392). \n \n

“This help,\n
What was provided in time by others, \n He will appreciate it by measure, \n
Strong awareness:\n
In chewing, in swallowing, \n And in tasting \n - All this is only for him \n
How to apply ointment to a wound” (?). \n \n

“Like the flesh of a child in the desert, \n Or like the grease on a wheel axle, \n
He must eat food without illusions - \nOnly to continue living” (?) \n \n

In the light of morality regarding necessities, the story follows Let us tell the story of the novice Sangharakkhita Nephew. For he used necessities only after considering them, according to which it is said: \n \n
Seeing me eat cold rice,\nMy mentor said:\n
"Novice, if you are not curbed\n
So be careful - don`t get burned." \n \n

Having heard these words,\n
On the spot, I felt a direct impulse, \n And, taking hold of it at once, \n
I achieved the Arahant fruit there. \n \n

Now my thoughts are pure \n
The moon is like full on the fifteenth day (see M.iii,277), \nAll my vices are erased,\n
There will be no more becoming. \n \n
Therefore, any other\n
Who wishes the suffering to end. \n
Let all your needs be used only wisely - after consideration. \n \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="buttonDirectionMindText">What should one who has left worldly life constantly direct his mind to?</string>
    <string name="directionMindText" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis"><b>What should one who has left worldly life constantly direct his mind to?</b> \n \n
AN 10.48: *The Blessed One said+: There are ten things that one who has gone into a homeless life should often meditate on. What ten? \n \n
     • (1) “I no longer belong to Varna”: one who has gone into a homeless life should often reflect on this. \n \n

     • (2) “My life depends on others”: ... \n \n

     • (3) “My behavior should be different *compared to that of a housewife+”: … \n \n

     • (4) “Can I blame myself regarding my morality?”: ... \n \n
     • (5) “Can my companions in the holy life, after careful examination, reproach me with regard to my morality?”: ... \n \n
     • (6) “I will be separated from everything that is dear and pleasant to me”: ... \n \n

     • (7) “I am the owner of my own kamma, the heir of my own kamma, born of my own kamma, related to my own kamma, my kamma will be my judge. Whatever I do is good or
bad – I will inherit the *result+ of this”: ... \n \n

     • (8) “What do I become as the days and nights fly by?”: ... \n \n

     • (9) “Do I *rejoice* in being in an empty home?”: … \n \n
     • (10) “Have I achieved superhuman achievements, truly noble discernment in knowledge and vision - such that when my companions in holy life ask me *about this+ in
the last days of my life – wouldn`t I feel embarrassed?”: this is something someone who has gone into homelessness should often think about. \n \n
These are ten things that one who has gone into homelessness should often reflect on.” \n \n

AN 10.55: And how, friends, does a monk have the ability to *see+ the directions of his own mind? Like a young man or girl - young, young, who likes beauty - who studies the reflection of her face in a bright, clean mirror or
bowl of clean water. If she sees dirt or a stain, she will try to remove it. If she sees neither dirt nor stain, she will be glad of it, her wish will be fulfilled and she
will think: “How wonderful it is that I am clean!” In the same way, when a monk studies himself, it is very useful for the monk in terms of *increasing his+ good qualities. *And he should ask himself+: \n \n

     • (1) “Do I often crave *something+? Do I have this quality or not? \n \n

     • (2) Am I often unkind? …\n\n

     • (3) Am I often lazy and sleepy? …\n\n

     • (4) Am I often calm? …\n\n

     • (5) Am I often devoid of doubt? …\n\n

     • (6) Do I often remain without anger? …\n\n

     • (7) Is my mind often unpolluted? ...

     • (8) Do I often find the inner joy of Dhamma? …\n\n
     • (9) Do I often find inner peace of mind? …\n\n

     • (10) Do I often gain the highest wisdom of insight into phenomena? Do I have this quality or not? \n \n
If, through such self-observation, a monk does not see the presence of these good qualities in himself, then he should make an additional desire, effort, diligence, inspiration,
tirelessness, awareness and vigilance in order to acquire these good qualities. Just as someone whose clothes or *hair+ on his head would catch fire would put in extra desire, effort, diligence, inspiration, tirelessness, awareness and vigilance in order to extinguish the *flame+ on his clothes or head - that`s for sure also this monk must make an additional desire, effort, diligence,
inspiration, tirelessness, awareness and vigilance for the acquisition of these good qualities. \n \n
But if, through such self-observation, a monk sees in himself the presence of some of *these+ good qualities, but not the rest, then he should establish himself in these good qualities that he sees in himself, and make additional desire, effort, diligence,
inspiration, tirelessness, awareness and vigilance for the sake of acquiring those good qualities that he does not see in himself. Just like someone whose clothes would catch fire... - then in the same way this monk should establish himself in these good qualities that he sees in himself, and make an additional desire... for the sake of acquiring those good qualities that he does not see in himself. \n \n

But if, through such self-observation, a monk sees that all these good qualities are present in him, then he should establish himself in these very good qualities and
make further efforts to achieve the destruction of the defilements of *mind+.” \n \n

AN 10.59: *The Blessed One said+: “Therefore, monks, this is how you should train yourselves:
“Our minds will be strengthened in accordance with the *spirit+ of our departure into a homeless life, and the negative qualities that have arisen will not take possession of our minds. (1) Our minds will be strengthened by the perception of impermanence. (2) Our minds will be strengthened by perception
impersonality. (3) Our minds will be strengthened by the perception of unattractiveness. (4) Our minds will be strengthened by the perception of danger. (5) We will know good and bad, and our minds will be strengthened by the perception of it. (6) We will know the manifestation and
destruction of the world, and our minds will be strengthened by the perception of it. (7) We will know the origin and disappearance of the world, and our minds will be strengthened by the perception of it. (8)
Our minds will be strengthened by the perception of abandonment. (9) Our minds will be strengthened
the perception of dispassion. (10) Our minds will be strengthened by the perception of cessation.” This is how you should train yourself. \n \n
When the mind of a monk has been strengthened in accordance with the *spirit+ of his departure into a homeless life, and the negative qualities that have arisen do not take possession of his mind; when his mind has been strengthened by the perception of impermanence... ...cessation, then in his case one of two fruits can be expected: either final knowledge in this very life, or, if there is a remnant of *grasping+, a state of non-return.” \n \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="buttonTypesGoodsText">Types of benefits for those who have left worldly life</string>
    <string name="typesGoodsText" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis"><b>Types of benefits for those who have left worldly life</b> \n \n
AN 10.71: “Bhikkhus, practice moral conduct and observe Patimokkha.
Remain restrained by Patimokkha, possessing good behavior and *appropriate* means, seeing danger in the smallest offenses. Having assigned yourself the rules of training, train in them. \n \n

     (1) If a monk desires: “May I be liked and *may* be pleasant to my fellow monks, *may+ be respected and honored by them” - then let him perform moral behavior, *let+ be devoted to the inner peace of mind, does not neglect the jhanas, has insight and retires to empty dwellings. \n \n

     (2) If a monk desires: “May I receive robes, food, housing, medicine and provision for sick *monks+” - then let him perform moral behavior... retire to empty dwellings. \n \n

     (3) If a monk wishes: “May the services of those *people+ whose robes, food, medicines and provisions for sick *monks+ I use bring them great fruit and benefit” - then let him perform moral behavior... retire in empty houses. \n \n

     (4) If a monk desires: “When my deceased relatives and family members remember me with confidence in their minds after death, then let it bring them great fruit and benefit” - then let him perform moral behavior... retire into empty dwellings. \n \n

     (5) If a monk wishes: “Let me be content with any kind of clothing, food, housing, medicine and provision for sick *monks+” - then let him perform moral behavior... retire to empty dwellings. \n \n

     (6) If the monk wishes: “Let me patiently endure cold and heat; hunger and thirst; encountering flies, mosquitoes, wind, scorching sun and snakes; as well as with rude and offensive speech. Let me be able to withstand the painful bodily feelings that arise: painful, sharp, piercing, tearing, unpleasant, sucking out the vital force” - then let him perform moral behavior... retire to empty dwellings. \n \n

     (7) If a monk desires: “Let me be the one who conquers displeasure and pleasure, and
let discontent and pleasure not conquer me. May I be able to overcome discontent and pleasure as soon as they arise,” then let him fulfill the moral
behavior... retires to empty dwellings. \n \n
     (8) If the monk wishes: “Let me be the one who conquers horror and fear, and let horror and fear not conquer me. Let me be able to overcome horror and fear as soon as they arise,” then let him perform moral behavior... retire to empty dwellings. \n \n
     (9) If a monk desires: “May I achieve, at will, without difficulties or problems, the four jhanas, which constitute the highest mind and are pleasant abidings in this very life,” then let him perform moral behavior... retire to empty dwellings . \n \n

     (10) If a monk wishes: “May I, through the destruction of mental defilements, right *here and now+ in this very life, be able to enter and abide in the unblemished liberation of the mind, liberation by wisdom, directly knowing and manifesting it for myself on my own” - then then let him perform moral behavior, *let+ be devoted to the inner tranquility of the mind, not neglect the jhanas, have insight and retire to empty dwellings.
When it was thus said: “Monks, maintain moral behavior and observe Patimokkha. Remain restrained by Patimokkha, have good behavior and
*appropriate+ means, seeing danger in the smallest offenses. Having imposed on yourself the rules of training, train in them” - that`s what was said in relation to this.” \n \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="textGeneralInfo">
        <i>NOTE: THIS TEXT IS A COMPILATE TRANSLATION OF THE FOLLOWING BOOKS: "BUDDHIST MONASTIC CODE", "PA-AUK SAMANERA COURSE", VISUDHIMAGGA AND THE TEXT OF THE VINAYA HIMSELF, AS WELL AS A COMPILATION OF THEMATIC SUTTAS. \n \n
   FOR COMRADES FROM CHITTAVIVEKA AND AMBAKOTE - PRESENT AND FUTURE. </i>\n\n
Dhammanisita bhante. \n \n \n \n

         You can win a certain battle \n
         a thousand times a thousand warriors, \n
         but the one who conquers only one thing - himself \n
         truly the greatest Conqueror of all. \n
         (Dhammapada 103)\n\n

         <b>Why and why was the monastic discipline - Vinaya - established?</b> \n \n
AN 2.280: *The Blessed One said+: “Monks, for these two reasons the Tathagata has prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n
     • (1) for the well-being of the Sangha and \n
     • (2) for the sake of the peace of the Sangha. \n\n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of restraining capricious individuals, and \n
     • so that well-behaved monks can enjoy peace of mind. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the stains of *mental defilements+ inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the stains of *mental defilements+ inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the hostilities inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the hostilities inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the flaws inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the flaws inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the dangers inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the dangers inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of restraining the negative qualities inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the negative qualities inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • out of compassion for the laity, and \n
     • stopping groups of those who have evil desires. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • so that those who lack trust can gain confidence, and \n
     • for the sake of increasing the *trust+ of those who *already+ have trust. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of the duration of the good Dhamma, and \n
     • for the sake of promoting discipline. \n \n

For these two reasons, the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples.” \n \n \n

        <b>Why leave worldly life?</b> \n \n
In the Ratthapalla Sutta, the king answers this question like this: \n

         ◦ Due to losses due to aging. \n
         ◦ Due to losses due to illness. \n
         ◦ Due to loss of wealth. \n
         ◦ Due to the loss of relatives. \n \n
Venerable Ratthapala`s answer was as follows:\n

         ◦ Existence in any world is impermanent, swept away. \n
         ◦ Existence in any world has no refuge, no defender. \n
         ◦ Existence in any world has nothing “of its own”; everything will have to be left behind. \n
         ◦ Existence in any world is inferior, insatiable, in slavery to thirst. \n \n

<b>Samanera age</b> \n \n
Once upon a time, a disease called “Ahivata” swept across India. Many died. One
Only the father and son were left alive in the family, and both were tonsured as bhikkhus and samaneras, respectively. When this bhikkhu went begging, his samanera son followed him. People began to think that the monk did not keep his vow of abstinence from sexual activity, and that a certain nun gave birth to a child for him. To avoid misunderstandings, the Buddha established
The minimum age for tonsure as a samanera is 15 years. If the candidate for samanera is under 15 years old, then in order to receive tonsure he must be able to “drive away crows.” The history of this
The rule is this: during the same illness of "Ahivata", two children *under 15 years old+ of a laywoman outlived their mother, and whenever bhikkhus came, these children ran up to them.
Venerable Ananda, wanting to help them, told the situation to the Buddha; he asked: “When they eat, the crows can take their food. Are they able to drive them away?” Ananda replied: “Yes, they are capable,” and thus the second rule for tonsure as a samanera appeared. \n \n \n \n
   <b>Being under guardianship (Nissaya)</b> \n \n
A samanera should always live dependent on a mentor [a senior and experienced bhikkhu]. There are two types of guardianship: from a mentor (upajjhāya) *giving tonsure+, and from a teacher (ācariya) *teacher of recitations for tonsure, teacher of Dhamma and Pali language, teacher as performer
temporary mentor, etc.+. The relationship between them is identical in many details, so
the general word “mentor” is used. Both are expected to perform for life
corresponding obligations [vatta - “protocol”+ in relation to each other *see. below+, the texts define their relationship as “like father and son.” One bhikkhu is allowed to have
students of more than one samanera, but only if he is competent enough to
so that his samaneras do not behave inappropriately with each other (in the history of the introduction of this rule, two samaneras under the leadership of Venerable Upananda raped each other, and later one of
they were raped by a bhikkhuni [nun]). Bhikkhus are also prohibited from luring each other
following them. By "following them" Commentary 1 describes samanera or bhikkhus disciples. \n \n
A samanera can change his mentor only in two cases: \n \n

         ◦ The mentor leaves forever, dies, cuts off his hair, etc. \n
         ◦ He doesn`t like his mentor (he`s immoral, etc.)\n
Even if one bhikkhu mentor is immoral, another bhikkhu is expressly prohibited
lure those who follow him, but a statement can be made so that they realize the undesirability of their stay with such a mentor. Quoted by Commentary
example shows that such a hint need not be subtle: “Your life in
depending on an immoral person is like coming to bathe, but smearing yourself with excrement." If those to whom such a statement is addressed realize its truth and ask the bhikkhu making such a statement to be their mentor, then there will be no offense for the second one if he accepts them. \n \n

If, for some reason, the student and the mentor live in different monasteries, but their formal status in relation to each other is not severed, then the first must temporarily take guardianship from a certain teacher *in the monastery where he is located+ until reunification with mentor.
In view of the fact that the Mahavagga (I.72.1) gives dukkat a *formal designation for improper action; for bhikkhus only] for one who comes under the tutelage of an unconscious bhikkhu, then the newly initiated one is allowed to observe the behavior of his potential teacher for four or five days before entering under his tutelage. \n \n

Guardianship under a mentor ends if he loses his hair, dies, leaves forever, etc. In this case, you need to take a new mentor. A mentor may also reject a student if he sees that under his teaching he is making no progress in the Dhamma and Vinaya, or that he shows no respect and only experiences negative emotions towards
to your mentor, etc. If a mentor abandons a student, then his duty is to apologize, and his duty
mentor - forgive. If the student goes back to his old ways, he may be rejected completely. \n \n

How to enter the tutelage of a mentor? Throwing his outer robe over his left shoulder, leaving his right shoulder bare, he bows to the potential mentor, and then, kneeling with palms together over the heart, repeats the following passage three times: \n \n

Upajjhāyo me bhante hohi - "Venerable One, be my mentor." \n \n

This often happens right during the tonsure ceremony. Coming under the tutelage of a teacher follows the same procedure, but the phrase changes: \n \n
    Ācariyo me bhante hohi; āyasmato nissāya vacchāmi - "Venerable One, be my teacher; I will live under your tutelage" \n \n \n
<b>Four Great Standards (cattāro mahāpadesā)</b> \n \n
Separately, there are standards given by the Buddha in order to evaluate certain situations that were not covered by the canonical Vinaya and its prohibitions and resolutions, and on the basis of this to draw a conclusion about whether this or that is appropriate for someone who has passed away from worldly life or not. On
On the same basis one can also judge the actual applicability of a particular fragment from the Commentary on the Vinaya. \n \n
Mv.VI.40.1: “Whatever I forbid, saying: “It is not permitted,” if it corresponds to what is not permitted, if it contradicts (literally, “infringes upon”) what is permitted, then it is not
allowed for you. Whatever I prohibit by saying, “It is not permitted,” if it is in accordance with what is permitted, if it is contrary to what is not permitted, then it is permitted for you. Whatever I permit by saying, “This is permitted,” if it corresponds to what is not permitted,
if it is contrary to what is permitted, then it is not permitted for you. And whatever I permit by saying, "This is permitted," if it is in accordance with what is permitted, if it is contrary to what is not permitted, then it is permitted for you." \n \n \n \n
<b>Basic Vows</b> \n \n
Samaneras take 10 vows: \n \n

     1. Abstinence from killing living beings. \n \n

Next, the factors of the complete path of murder will be given, only the coincidence of all is the kamma of murder and, accordingly, a violation of the training rule: \n \n
         i. Object: a living thing, including fetuses (in the case of humans, etc.), eggs in the case of bedbugs, etc. - starting from the first conscious tact upon appearance in the womb, etc. \n \n
         ii. Intent: To consciously and intentionally wish for the death of some being. \n \n
         iii. Perception: the creature is perceived as a creature. \n \n
         iv. Effort: For the sake of the death of this or that creature, any means were taken (including contract killing, etc.). \n \n
         v. Result: the creature dies. \n \n \n \n

     2. Refraining from taking what is not given. \n \n

Next, the factors of the complete path of theft will be given, only the coincidence of all is the kamma of theft and, accordingly, a violation of the training rules: \n \n
         i. Object: something belonging to a person or group of people. \n \n
         ii. Perception: is the perception that something belongs to some person or group of people. \n \n
         iii. Intent: There is an intent to steal. \n \n
         iv. Effort: theft occurs (the value factor of the object plays a role only for bhikkhus; for samanas, even stealing blades of grass is a violation). \n \n \n \n

     3. Abstinence from sexual intercourse \n \n

Through the mouth, genitals, anus. This includes sexual intercourse with animals and corpses, as well as with oneself (in case of excessive flexibility). For the full path of misconduct must
there is an aspect of consent (quite mental) to sexual intercourse and awareness of what is happening. \n \n \n \n

     4. Abstinence from lying \n \n

Factors:\n\n

         i. Intention: the goal is to distort some truth. \n \n
         ii. Effort: By any means, deliberately distorted information is conveyed to another person. \n \n
Jokes are considered lies. There will be no misconduct only in two cases: the samanera speaks very quickly and hastily, or by one he means another. \n \n \n \n

     5. Abstinence from alcohol and fermented drinks leading to carelessness \n \n

According to the 4 Great Standards, this also includes drugs. If a bhikkhu accepts
intoxicating substances without knowing that they are such, then he still commits an offense. For a samanera, it will be an offense only if he uses them consciously. \n \n \n \n
     6. Abstain from eating during prohibited times (after noon until dawn the next day). \n \n

In the afternoon, five tonics are allowed in case of feeling hungry, tired and other ailments: honey, sugar/molasses (molasses), ghee, solid butter and liquid butter. Juices from any fruit are allowed, except for “juice from grains”; The commentary defines this as prohibiting the juice from the fruit
palmyra, coconut, jackfruit, pumpkin, bottle gourd, white pumpkin, nutmeg and breadfruit. Licorice juice is prohibited. Juices from any vegetables are allowed, except
cooked. If you have taken a laxative, then after 12 you can drink strained
broths made from rice, meat and mung bean. In case of poor health, a substance is allowed (how to prepare it is written in the Commentary when analyzing 3 parajiki), which is similar to miso paste (loṇasovīraka/loṇasocīraka; now this is not prepared anywhere; is miso the equivalent -
the question is controversial with a bias towards a negative answer), if you do not feel unwell, then you need to stir it in water and drink it like that (Mv.VI.16.3). \n \n

Recipe for the above substance from the Commentary:
Loṇasovīrakavatthusmiṃ– loṇasovīrakaṃ nāma sabbarasābhisaṅkhataṃ ekaṃ bhesajjaṃ. Taṃ kira karontā harītakāmalakavibhītakakasāve sabbadhaññāni sabbaaparaṇṇāni sattannampi dhaññānaṃ odanaṃ kadaliphalādīni sabbaphalāni vettaketakakhajūrikaḷīrādayo sabbakaḷīre macchamaṃsakhaṇḍāni anekāni ca madhuphāṇitasindhavaloṇanikaṭukādīni bhesajjāni pakkhipitvā kumbhimukhaṃ limpitvā ekaṃ vā dve vā tīṇi vā saṃvacchar āni ṭhapenti, taṃ paripaccitvā jamburasavaṇṇaṃ hoti. Vātakāsakuṭṭhapaṇḍubhagandarādīnaṃ siniddhabhojanaṃ bhuttānañca uttarapānaṃ bhattajīraṇakabhesajjaṃ tādisaṃ natthi. Taṃ panetaṃ bhikkhūnaṃ pacchābhattampi vaṭṭati, gilānānaṃ pākatikameva, agilānānaṃ pana udakasambhinnaṃ pānaparibhogenāti. \n \n \n \n

     7. Refrain from watching dancing, listening to singing and music \n \n
This includes looking at it all and participating directly. If a samanera accidentally stumbles upon such sights while going for alms, etc., then it will not
a misdemeanor until he consciously chooses to look. \n \n \n \n

     8. Abstinence from wearing garlands, perfume, cosmetics and body jewelry \n \n

When washing, you can use odorous elements in case of skin itching, small ulcers, open abscesses and bad body odor (according to the Commentary “like a horse”). \n \n \n \n
     9. Abstaining from high and luxurious seats and beds \n \n

A high bed is on average defined as the size of an elbow (about 45 cm, but there is an interpretation in form 16.7 cm). You can sit on seats higher than this size only if they are
you can`t lie down. Seats and benches with luxurious or unusual decorations or upholstery are prohibited, as are those made from luxurious materials. However, if it was received
an invitation to the house from the householders, and they have prepared high and luxurious seats, then you can sit on them (but not lie down), and in any case you cannot sit on the platform, throne or anything upholstered in cotton. \n \n \n \n
     10. Abstinence from accepting gold and silver (money) \n \n

A samanera cannot accept money and jewelry, and he also cannot specifically ask others to accept it for him (as a command). If someone puts money or jewelry next to him, then he is obliged to inform about his refusal to do so. However, there is no need to report
his refusal if he is sincerely unattached to these things. It is allowed to have a lay person who will manage the money (kappiya). Formally, donors of money are only allowed to say who your kappia is, or indicate that there is a box for money in the monastery
donations. \n \n \n \n
<b>10 Liṅganāsana (destruction of samanera status)</b> \n \n
If a samanera commits the 10 offenses described below, then his status as a samanera ceases. He falls away from the Three Jewels and loses his right to use the kuti and other property of the Sangha, remaining a samanera only outwardly. If he does not see the offense and does not want to make an effort to correct himself, then he should be expelled, which is the responsibility of the mentor.
Performing Lingasana is, in general, a reversible process: you need to re-take the Triple Refuge (and, optionally, anew the 10 vows) from your mentor. Can`t recover in
status only if the tenth lingasana has been completed. The top ten offenses that destroy the status of a samanera are as follows: \n \n
     1) Killing living creatures - even destroying bedbug eggs. \n \n
     2) Taking what is not given - even a small blade of grass. \n \n
     3) Sexual contact. \n \n
     4) Lie - even as a joke. \n \n
     5) Conscious drinking of alcohol and other types of intoxicants. \n \n
     6) Statement of blasphemy about Buddha (in the spirit: “he was not Enlightened, did not comprehend Liberation,” etc.). \n \n
     7) Speaking blasphemy about the Dhamma (“does not lead to Liberation”, etc.). \n \n
     8) Statement of blasphemy about the Sangha ("took the wrong path," etc.). \n \n
     9) Having a false view (about “self” [atta], about the non-existence of kamma and
rebirth, the non-existence of other worlds, etc. See Brahmajala Sutta, DN1. As soon as it turns out that the samanera has a false view, the bhikkhu must tell him three times to abandon this view; after the third time, if the samanera still persists, then he
status is destroyed). \n \n
     10) Sexual intercourse with a bhikkhuni (nun). \n \n

As was said above, the tenth lingasana (sexual intercourse with a bhikkhuni) is irreversible: whoever has completed it until the end of his life no longer has the right to become a samanera again, nor does he have the right to be tonsured as a bhikkhuni. The first five lingasanas coincide with the first five 10 samanera vows.
The commentary also adds that a samanera who knowingly drinks alcohol in violation of the fifth vow may be restored to his former status as a samanera, but can never be ordained as a bhikkhu in this life; not all communities share this point of view,
because it is not supported by canon. \n \n \n \n
<b>10 Daṇḍakamma (punishments and grounds for punishment)</b> \n \n
In case of violation of the last five of the 10 vows (starting from “abstinence from drinking alcohol”, etc.), the mentor can impose punishment (daṇḍa) on the samanera. Punishment is also imposed for the following actions: \n \n
     • He strives for the lack of something for the bhikkhus \n \n
     • He strives for the bhikkhu`s lack of housing \n \n
     • He seeks harm and danger for bhikkhus \n \n
     • He insults bhikkhus \n \n
     • He strives to disrupt unity among bhikkhus \n \n
In total there are 10 grounds for punishment. Punishment is the responsibility of the mentor. Another bhikkhu can impose punishment on a samanera only with the permission of his mentor.
The commentary adds that if the mentor was informed three times of his misdeeds
samanera, but did not do anything, then it is permissible to impose punishment bypassing the mentor. The sub-commentary adds that the Sangha should be notified first. \n \n
The main punishment for samaneras is a ban on their presence in any place.
It is impossible to prohibit the entire territory of the monastery, but only certain places where one or another samanera usually lives and spends time. Punishments in the form of food intake restrictions are prohibited. The commentary says that punishments in the form of carrying water, sand, etc. are also acceptable.
Punishments should be carried out with the idea that the samanera will correct itself and will no longer commit this or that offense. Cruel punishment, including corporal punishment, is prohibited. \n \n
In addition to the ten vows, it is also common practice for the Samaras to observe the 75 rules of the Sekhiya section and the protocols (vatta) of the Khandhak. \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textProtocols">

    </string>

    <string name="buttonTextAbout1">PROTOCOLS and general information</string>
    <string name="buttonTextAbout2">Who is allowed to take monastic vows, and who is not allowed.</string>
    <string name="textButtonGenInfo">general information</string>
    <string name="textButtonProtocolsInfo">protocols</string>
</resources>