<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="buttonAboutSanghadisesaText">about the rules of sanghadisesa</string>
    <string name="textAboutSanghadisesa"> \n Sanghadisesa \n \n This term means [violation] "involving the participation of the Community in the primary (adi) and subsequent (sesa) procedures". \n It follows from the fact that in case of violation of any of the rules of this class, it is the Community that initially imposes punishment on the monk (including a redemptive period and a probation period), imposes it again if the monk has not fulfilled the established requirements, and when the monk has fulfilled all the requirements, removes the punishment from him.   \n  This section contains 13 rules, in the case of the first nine, the monk is credited with a violation immediately after the offense is committed, in the last four only after the offender has been reprimanded three times in the form of a Community procedure.  \n  \n  \n  \n</string>
    <string name="buttonTextAboutParajika">about the rules of parajiki</string>
    <string name="textAboutParajika">\n Parajika (defeat) \n \n The book Parivara says that this term comes from a verb meaning to lose or to be defeated. A monk who commits the four prohibited acts described in this chapter is considered to have succumbed to his mental defilements (upakkilesa) to an extent that overpowers his original goal of becoming a monk. The Vibhanga gives a number of metaphors to illustrate the irreversible nature of defeat: like a man with his head cut off like a withered leaf torn from the stem… like a flat stone broken in two, which cannot be united… like a palm tree with its top cut off, unable to continue growth. A monk who commits any of these prohibited acts is irreversibly excommunicated from the life of the monastic community and is no longer considered a monk.</string>
    <string name="textSanghadisesa1">1 \n Intentional emission of semen, except while dreaming, entails initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText1">\n 1.(Sukkavissaṭṭhisikkhāpada) \n Правило о намеренном извержении семени \n <i>The rule of intentional ejaculation of the seed</i> \n \n <b>sañcetanikā sukkavissaṭṭhi \n \n aññatra</b>  <b>supinantā \n \n saṃghādiseso.</b> \n \n Намеренное извержение семени (за исключением семяизвержений во время сновидения) влечёт за собой первоначальное и последующие собрания Общины.  \n \n <i>Intentional ejaculation of semen (with the exception of ejaculations during a dream) entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</i>
    \n \n Это правило возникло в результате одного события связанного с достопочтенным Сеййясака \n \n
Сеййясака был недоволен святой жизнью и по совету достопочтенного удаина перстал воздерживаться от намеренного извержения семени. \n \n
\n \n This rule arose as a result of an event connected with the Venerable Seiyasaka \n \n
Seiyasaka was dissatisfied with the holy life and, on the advice of the venerable Udain, stopped to abstain from intention ejaculation. \n \n
<b>Исключения</b> \n \n
Во время сна, если сперма выделяется во время сна, никакой вины в этом нет. \n \n
Во время дефекации, если какое-то количество сперматозоидов все-таки выходит, намерение для этого отсутствует, никакой вины не совершается. \n \n
Во время ухода или чистки половых органов (из-за воспаления, травмы, укуса насекомого и т.д.) путем нанесения лекарства (крема, мази и т.д.), если выделяется немного сперматозоидов, а желание к этому отсутствует, вины в этом нет. \n \n
Если во время того, как монах ложится в постель, желая эякулировать, он зажимает свой половой орган между бедер или сильно сжимает его в кулаке, и во время сна выделяется сперма, он совершает сангхадишешу. \n \n
Если сперма высвобождается естественным образом без намерения монаха сделать это и что в этот момент этот последний действительно испытывает удовольствие, он не совершает никакой ошибки. Однако, если во время семяизвержения он воспользовался возможностью выпустить сперму рукой, он совершает сангхадишешу. \n \n
Если монах, настойчиво глядя на тело женщины со жгучим желанием, эякулирует, он не совершает сангхадишешу. \n \n
Примечание: Это правило частично соответствует третьему из десяти правил. \n \n \n


<b>Exceptions</b> \n \n
While sleeping, if the sperm is released during a dream, no fault is being committed. \n \n
While defecating, if some sperm does come out, the intention for it being absent, no fault is being committed. \n \n
While nursing or cleaning one`s sex (due to an inflammation, an injury, an insect bite, etc.) by putting medicine (cream, ointment, etc.), if some sperm is released, the desire for it being absent, no fault is being committed. \n \n
If at time of getting into bed, wishing to ejaculate, the bhikkhu wedges his sex between his thighs or holds it strongly in his fist and whilst sleeping the sperm is released, he commits the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
If the sperm is naturally released without the bhikkhu`s intention to do so and that at this moment this latter does experience pleasure, he does not commit any fault. However, if during ejaculation, he seized the opportunity to release the sperm with his hand, he commits the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
If while insistently looking at the body of a woman, with a burning desire, a bhikkhu ejaculates, he does not commit a saṃghādisesa. \n \n
Note: This rule partly corresponds with the third of the ten precepts. \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textSanghadisesa2">2 \n If any monk under the influence of lust, with a distorted mind,
makes bodily contact with a woman, takes her by the hand, by a lock of hair,
or caresses other parts of her body, this entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText2">\n 2. (Kāyasaṁsagga) \n
Похотливый телесный контакт  \n
<i>Lustful body contact</i> \n \n
<b>Yo pana bhikkhu otiṇṇo vipariṇatena cittena \n \n mātugāmena saddhiṁ kāyasaṁsaggaṁ samāpajjeyya \n \n hatthaggāhaṁ vā veṇiggāhaṁ vā aññatarassa vā aññatarassa vā \n \n aṅgassa parāmasanaṁ, \n \n saṅghādiseso”. \n \n</b>
        Если какой-либо монах под влиянием похоти, с искажённым умом, совершит телесный контакт с женщиной, возьмёт её за руку, за локон волос, или будет ласкать другие части её тела, это влечёт за собой первоначальное и последующие собрания Общины. \n \n
<i>If any monk under the influence of lust, with a distorted mind, makes bodily contact with a woman, takes her by the hand, by a lock of hair, or caresses other parts of her body, this entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community. \n \n</i>
    \n \n Это правило возникло в результате одного события связанного с достопочтенным Удаином \n \n
Удаин с похотью дотрагивался до жены брахмана. Это произошло, когда брахман со своей женой осматривали кути Удаина. \n \n

\n \n This rule arose as a result of one event related to the Venerable Udain \n \n
Udain touched the brahman`s wife with lust. This happened when a brahmin and his wife were examining Udain`s kuti. \n \n

Прикасаясь к ткани или к драгоценностям, которые носит женщина, монах совершает нарушение, но не сангхадисесу (при условии, что к женщине не прикасаются вместе с этой частью ткани или драгоценным камнем). \n \n

Точно так же, прикасаясь к женщине, которая является его родственницей, например, к матери или сестре, даже с умом, свободным от похоти, он совершает нарушение, но не сангхадисесу. \n \n

В случайном прикосновении к женщине нет нарушения. Однако, если женщина прикасается к монаху, это не должно восприниматься пассивно, потому что, если он получает от этого удовольствие, даже на короткое время, он немедленно совершает самгхадисесу. \n \n

Прикасаясь к женщине каким-либо предметом, монах совершает тхулачайя. \n \n

<b>Примечание:</b> Это правило частично соответствует третьему из десяти правил. \n \n

By touching a cloth or a jewel worn by a woman, a bhikkhu commits a fault but not the saṃghādisesa (provided the woman is not touched along with that part of cloth or jewel). \n \n
In the same way, by touching a woman who is a relative, his mother or sister for instance, even with a mind rid of lust, he commits a fault but not the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
By accidentally touching a woman, there is no fault. However, if a woman touches a bhikkhu, this latter must not undergo it passively, because if he takes pleasure in it, even for a short while, he immediately commits the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
By touching a woman with some kind of utensil, a bhikkhu commits a thullaccaya. \n \n
Note: This rule partly corresponds with the third of the ten precepts. \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="textButtonSanghadisesa3">
        3 \n
        If any monk, overcome by desire, with a distorted mind, addresses a woman with obscene words, just as a young man addresses a girl with a hint of sexual intercourse, this entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.
    </string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText3">
        \n 3. (Duṭṭhullavācāsikkhāpada) \n
Правило о непристойной речи  \n
<i>The rule of obscene speech</i> \n \n
<b>Yo pana bhikkhu otiṇṇo vipariṇatena cittena \n \n mātugāmaṁ duṭṭhullāhi vācāhi obhāseyya \n \n yathā taṁ yuvā yuvatiṁ methunupasaṁhitāhi, \n \n saṅghādiseso. \n \n</b>
       Если какой-либо монах, будучи охвачен желанием, с искажённым умом, обращается с непристойными словами к женщине, подобно тому как молодой человек обращается к девушке с намёком на сексуальный контакт, это влечёт за собой первоначальное и последующие собрания Общины. \n \n
<i>If any monk, overcome by desire, with a distorted mind, addresses a woman with obscene words, just as a young man addresses a girl with a hint of sexual intercourse, this entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.. \n \n</i>
   \n \n Это правило возникло в результате одного события связанного с достопочтенным Удаином \n \n
Удаин с непристойными словами обращался к женщинам которые пришли осмотреть кути. \n \n
\n \n This rule arose as a result of one event related to the Venerable Udain \n \n
Udayin addressed the women who came to inspect his kuti with obscene words. \n \n
В Канкха Витарани перечисляется пять факторов, которые должны присутствовать при полном нарушении данного правила: \n
<i>The K/Commentary lists five factors for a full breach of this rule.</i> \n \n
1) Объект: женщина, т.е. любой человек женского пола, достаточно опытный, чтобы понимать - что прилично, а что неприлично говорить, что пристойно, а что - непристойно. \n
<i>1) Object: a woman, i.e., any female human being experienced enough to know what is properly said and improperly said, what is lewd and not lewd.</i> \n \n
2) Понимание: монах понимает, что перед ним именно такая женщина. \n
<i>2) Perception: The bhikkhu perceives her to be such a woman.</i> \n \n
3) Намерение: его толкает страстное желание. \n
<i>3) Intention: He is impelled by lust.</i> \n \n
Как в предыдущем правиле мы можем принять определение страстного желания, даваемое в комментарии, как минимальное количество желания, для выполнения фактора: Он хочет получить удовольствие от высказывания чего-то непристойного или неподобающего. \n
<i>As in the preceding rule, we can take the Commentary`s definition of lust here as the minimum amount of lust to fulfill this factor: He wants to enjoy saying something lewd or improper.</i> \n \n
4) Усилие: он делает замечания, восхваляя, порицая, прося, умоляя, спрашивая, вопрошая, поучая, советуя или оскорбляя с упоминанием её половых органов, или совершения ей полового акта. \n
<i>4) Effort: He makes remarks praising, criticizing, begging, imploring, asking, quizzing, advising, instructing, or insulting with reference to her genitals or anus, or to her performing sexual intercourse.</i> \n \n
5) Результат: женщина немедленно понимает сказанное. \n
<i>5) Result: The woman immediately understands.</i> \n \n \n
В Вибханге объясняется, что под данное правило не подпадают слова, произносимые в порыве гнева.
Следовательно, любые оскорбления, которые монах произносит в отношении женщины не от желания, а в результате гнева, то, даже если в них упоминаются её половые органы и прочее, они подпадают под Паччитию 2, а не под это правило. \n
<i>The Vibhaṅga makes clear that this rule does not cover statements made in anger. Thus any insults a bhikkhu may direct at a woman out of anger rather than out of desire — even if they refer to her genitals, etc. — would come under Pc 2, rather than here.</i> \n \n
Поступки, не являющиеся нарушениями.
В Вибханге говорится, что для монаха нет нарушения, если он говорит ради цели (духовного) благополучия (attha - также может означать "смысл Дхаммы"), имя Дхамму в качестве цели или имея цель обучения.
Поэтому, например, если монах рассказывает что-то женщинам, не имея похотливого намерения, он может произнести текст этого правила, объяснить его смысл или пуститься в подробности при рассмотрении темы непривлекательности тела как темы медитации, и ему не будет засчитано нарушение.
В комментарии на этот счёт приводится пример монаха, который обращается к сексуально неполноценной женщине, говоря ей быть старательной в практике, чтобы не переродится с такими недостатками снова.
Однако, если монах углубится в любую из этих тем из желания удовольствия от того, чтобы сказать слушателям что-то непристойное, он не освобождается от наказания.
В новом подкомментарии это иллюстрируется на примере: монах учит монахиню тексту Вибханги на данную тему, отклоняясь от нормального тона повествования и хихикает, произнося примеры непристойных выражений.
Говорится, что такого рода поведение является здесь полным нарушением.
Монаху, который не намереваясь говорить ничего непристойного, произносит нейтральные слова, которые его слушатели принимают за непристойные, нарушение не засчитывается.

<i> \n \n
Non-offenses.
The Vibhaṅga states that there is no offense for a bhikkhu who speaks aiming at (spiritual) welfare (attha — this can also mean the "meaning of the Dhamma"), aiming at Dhamma, or aiming at teaching.
Thus, for example, if one is talking in front of women and has no lustful intent, one may recite or explain this training rule or go into detail on the topic of the loathsomeness of the body as a topic of meditation, all without incurring a penalty.
The Commentary here adds an example of a bhikkhu addressing a sexually deformed woman, telling her to be heedful in her practice so as not to be born that way again.
If, however, one were to broach any of these topics out of a desire to enjoy saying something lewd to one`s listeners, one would not be immune from an offense.
The New K/Sub-commentary illustrates this point with an example: A bhikkhu, teaching the Vibhaṅga of this rule to a bhikkhunī, departs from a normal tone of voice and keeps sniggering while reciting the examples of lewd speech.
This sort of behavior, it says, incurs the full offense here.
A bhikkhu who without intending to be lewd makes innocent remarks that his listener takes to be lewd commits no offense.
</i>
\n \n \n
</string>

    <string name="textButtonSanghadisesa4">
        4 \n
        If any monk, under the influence of a lustful mind with a distorted mind,
        praises lust in the presence of a woman, saying: this is the highest gift,
        how to perform sexual intercourse with me.  This entails an initial and subsequent community meeting.
    </string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText4">
        \n 4. (Attakāma pāricariya sikkhāpadaṁ) \n
        <i>Requesting sexual services from a woman.</i> \n \n
        <b> yo pana bhikkhu otiṇṇo vipariṇatena cittena  \n \n
            mātugāmassa santike attakāmapāricariyāya vaṇṇaṁ bhāseyya: \n \n
            “etadaggaṁ bhagini pāricariyānaṁ yā mādisaṁ \n \n
            sīlavantaṁ kalyāṇadhammaṁ brahmacāriṁ etena dhammena \n \n
            paricareyyā” \n \n
            ti,methunūpasaṁhitena, \n \n
            saṅghādiseso. \n \n
        </b>
        <i> If any monk, under the influence of a lustful mind with a distorted mind,
            praises lust in the presence of a woman, saying: this is the highest gift,
            how to perform sexual intercourse with me.
            This entails an initial and subsequent community meeting. \n \n </i>

        <i>The rule arose as a result of one event.
            Venerable Udain asked a woman to provide him with sexual favors. \n \n </i>

        <i>“At that time there was one attractive woman, a widow.
 So, Ven.  Udayin got dressed early in the morning, took his clothes and a bowl, and went to her home.
 Upon arrival, he sat down in the assigned seat.
 Then the woman approached him and, bowing to him, sat aside.
 While she was sitting there, Ven.  Udayin instructed, convinced and encouraged her by talking about the Dhamma.
 After Udayin`s conversation about the Dhamma, she said to him: “Tell me, venerable sir,
            what could I give you that you need: fabric for clothing?  Alms Housing?  Medicines?
 “It`s not difficult for us to get these things, sister...
 Give only what is difficult for us to get.
 “What, honorable sir?
 “Sexual intercourse.
 “Is this necessary, honorable sir?
 "Yes Sister.
 “Then let`s go, honorable sir.
 Entering the inner room, she took off her clothes and lay down on the bed.
 Then Ven.  Udayin approached the woman and said: “Who will touch this vile, stinking thing?”
 And he left, spitting.
 “So the woman criticized, complained and spread it... “How can this monk Udayin, when he
            himself was begging me for sexual intercourse, say: “Who will touch this vile,
            stinking thing?  and leave, spitting?
 What`s wrong with me?  What stinks about me?  In what ways am I inferior to whom? » \n \n</i>

            <b>Object:</b>
A woman experienced enough to know what is properly or improperly said, what is lewd and not lewd. \n \n

            <b>Perception \n</b>>
The bhikkhu perceives her to be a woman. \n \n

            <b>Intention: \n</b>
He is impelled by lust. According to the Commentary,
            this means he is lustful for his listener to minister to his desire for sexual intercourse.
            However, the Vibhaṅga defines overcome with lust here in the same broad terms it uses under Sg 2  3.
            This suggests that the factor of intention here can be fulfilled simply by the desire
            to enjoy making such remarks in a woman`s presence—say, getting a charge out of testing her reaction,
            which appears to have been Ven. Udāyin`s impulse in the origin story—regardless of how one feels
            about actually having sex with her. \n \n

            <b>Effort: \n</b>
The bhikkhu speaks to the woman in praise of her ministering to his sensual needs,
            referring to sexual intercourse as a meritorious gift.
            The Commentary maintains that his remarks must directly mention sexual intercourse for
            this factor to be fulfilled, but the examples in the rule itself and in the Vibhaṅga contradict
            its assertion. Some of the examples in the Vibhaṅga state simply, This is foremost.
            This is best. This is the utmost. This is highest. This is excellent. These statements are
            followed by the explanation that they have to allude to or be connected with sexual intercourse.
            It does not say that the allusion has to be explicit. \n \n

Also, the Vinīta-vatthu contains a number of cases in which bhikkhus simply tell women to give the highest gift,
            sexual intercourse—and one in which a bhikkhu simply tells a woman that sexual intercourse
            is the highest gift—without explicitly saying to whom it should be given. The bhikkhus all earn
            saṅghādisesas for their efforts, which shows that the reference to oneself need not be explicit,
            either. \n \n

Both the Commentary and the Commentary state that a physical gesture—this would include writing a
            letter—can fulfill the factor of effort here as well.

\n \n \n

</string>

    <string name="textButtonSanghadisesa5">
        5 \n
        If a bhikkhu is engaged in matchmaking
        Women with men, men with women.
        For marriage, for intimate relationships
        Even temporarily.
        This entails an initial and subsequent community meeting.
    </string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText5">
    \n 4. (Sañcarittasikkhāpadaṃ) \n
        Правило о посредничестве (сватовстве) .   \n
        <i>Mediation rule. \n rule about matchmaking.</i> \n \n

        <b>yo pana bhikkhu sañcarittaṃ samāpajjeyya \n</b>
            Если бхикху сватовством занимается \n
        <i>If a bhikkhu is engaged in matchmaking \n \n</i>

        <b>ittiyā vā purisamatiṃ purisassa vā ittimatiṃ \n</b>
           Женщины с мужчиной, мужчины с женщиной.  \n
        <i>Women with men, men with women. \n \n</i>

        <b>jāyattane vā jārattane vā, \n</b>
           Для женитьбы, для интимный отношений.  \n
        <i>For marriage, for intimate relationships \n \n</i>

        <b>antamaso taṅkheṇikāyapi,  \n</b>
           Даже временно.  \n
        <i>Even temporarily. \n \n</i>

        <b>saṃghādiseso. \n</b>
           Это влечет за собой начальное и последующее собрание сангхи \n
        <i>This entails an initial and subsequent community meeting.  \n \n</i>

         Возникновение этого правила, связано с двумя событиями связанными с достопочтенным Удайном.
        В первом событии, Удаин занимается сводничеством мужчины и женщины. Во втором событии,
        Удаин является посыльный к проститутке. \n \n

        <i> The arose of this rule is associated with two events connected with the venerable Udain.
            In the first event, Udain is doing matchmaking between a man and a woman.
            In the second event, Udain is a messenger to a prostitute. \n \n</i>

        <b>Violation under this rule. \n \n</b>

         Because both the Vibhanga and the Commentary define the action of transmission as “telling”:
         makes a gesture or writes a letter - is he committing a violation here?
         Simply carrying a letter without knowing its contents will not
         take into account the effort factor according to this rule. \n \n

         <b>Object: \n \n</b>

         There is no violation for a monk who tries to bring about reconciliation between an estranged couple,
         but not in a divorce, but it would be a complete violation if you try to achieve reconciliation between the couple,
         who is divorced. "Perception" is not a factor here either.
         which prompts the Commentary to note that even an arhat could commit an offense under this rule,
         if he tried to achieve reconciliation between his parents, whom he believed
         were separated when they actually divorced.

         Elsewhere, in a discussion of the five rules, the Commentary includes couples who live as husband and wife,
         without undergoing a formal ceremony in accordance with the definition of marriage, and the same definition,
         apparently applies here too.

         Vibhanga appoints tullacaya as mediator for the pandaka; according to the Commentary,
         the same punishment applies for acting as an intermediary for female yakkha or peta. \n \n

         <b>No offense: \n \n</b>
         Vibhanga argues that, apart from the usual exceptions, it is not a violation,
         if a monk conveys a message from a man to a woman or vice versa concerning “the matter of the community,
         a shrine or a sick person." The commentary illustrates the first two cases with cases
         when a monk conveys a message concerning construction work for a community or shrine;
         and the third case, when a monk, acting on behalf of a sick monk,
         sent by a layman to a laywoman for medicine. \n \n

         The Sub-Commentary adds that any such order,
         i.e. not involving any romantic relationship, is also exempt from punishment,
         unless it is a form of submission to the laity. \n \n
        <b>First sub-story</b> \n \n
At one time when the Buddha was staying at Sāvatthī in Anāthapiṇḍika`s Monastery, Venerable Udāyī was associating with and visiting a number of families in Sāvatthī.
When Udāyī saw a young man without a wife or a young woman without a husband, he would praise the young woman to the parents of a young man, “The young woman of such-and such a family is beautiful, intelligent, skilled, and diligent. She`s suitable for your son.” They would reply, “They don`t know who we are, Venerable. If you could persuade them to give the girl, we would take her for our son.”
And he praised the young man to the parents of a young woman, “The young man of such-and-such a family is handsome, intelligent, skilled, and diligent. He`s suitable for your daughter.” They would reply, “They don`t know who we are, Venerable, and we would be ashamed to speak to them for the sake of the girl. But if you could persuade them to ask us, we would give our girl to the young man.” In this way he arranged for the taking of a bride, for the giving of a bride, and for marriage.
At that time there was a former courtesan who had a beautiful daughter. On one occasion some lay followers of the Ājīvaka religion came from another village and said to that courtesan, “Madam, please give your girl to our boy.”
“I don`t know who you are, Sirs, and I won`t give my only daughter to be taken to another village.”
People asked those Ājīvaka lay followers why they had come. They replied, “We came to ask that courtesan to give her daughter to our son, but she refused.”
“But why did you ask the courtesan? You should speak to Venerable Udāyī. He`ll persuade her.”
They then went to Udāyī and said, “Venerable, we`ve asked that courtesan here to give her daughter to our son, but she refused. Would you please persuade her to give her daughter?”
Udāyī agreed. Soon afterwards he went to that courtesan and said, “Why didn`t you give them your daughter?”
“I don`t know who they are, Sir, and I won`t give my only daughter to be taken to another village.”
“Please give her to them. I know them.”
“If you know them, I`ll give her away.”
She then gave her daughter to those Ājīvaka followers, and they took her away. For a month they treated her like a daughter-in-law, but then like a slave.
The girl sent a message to her mother, saying, “Mom, I`m unhappy and miserable. For a month they treated me like a daughter-in-law, but then like a slave. Come, mom, and take me home.”
Soon afterwards the courtesan went to those Ājīvakas and said, “Please don`t treat my girl like a slave; treat her properly!”
They replied, “We deal with the monastic, not with you. Go away! We don`t want anything to do with you.” Literally, “We don`t know you.”Being dismissed, she returned to Sāvatthī.
A second time the girl sent the same message to her mother. That courtesan then went to Udāyī and said, “Venerable, my girl is unhappy and miserable. They treated her like a daughter-in-law for a month, but then like a slave. Please tell them to treat her properly.”
Udāyī went to the Ājīvakas and said, “Please don`t treat this girl like a slave; treat her properly.”
They replied, “We deal with the courtesan, not with you. A monastic shouldn`t get involved. You should behave like a proper monastic. So go away! We don`t want anything to do with you.” Being dismissed, he returned to Sāvatthī.
A third time that girl sent the same message to her mother, and a second time the courtesan went to Udāyī and told him the same thing.
He replied, “When I first went, they just dismissed me. Go yourself; I`m not going.”
Then that courtesan complained and criticized him, “May Venerable Udāyī be miserable and unhappy, just as my girl is miserable and unhappy because of her nasty mother-in-law, father-in-law, and husband.”
The girl, too, complained and criticized him in the same way,
as did other women who were unhappy with their mothers-in-law, fathers-in-law, and husbands.
But those women who were happy with their in-laws wished him well, saying, “May Venerable Udāyī be happy and well, just as we are happy and well because of our good mothers-in-law, fathers-in-law, and husbands.”
The monks heard that some women were criticizing him whereas others were wishing him well. And the monks of few desires complained and criticized him, “How could Venerable Udāyī act as a matchmaker?”
They told the Buddha. The Buddha had the Sangha gathered and questioned Udāyī: “Is it true, Udāyī, that you do this?”
“It`s true, Sir.” \n \n
<b>Second sub-story</b> \n \n
Soon afterwards a number of scoundrels who were enjoying themselves in a park sent a messenger to a sex worker, saying, “Please come, let`s enjoy ourselves in the park.”
She replied, “Sirs, I don`t know who you are. I`m wealthy. I don`t want to go outside the city.”
The messenger returned the message. A certain man then said to those men, “Why did you ask the sex worker? You should speak to Venerable Udāyī. He`ll persuade her.”
But a certain Buddhist lay follower said, “No way. That`s not allowable for the Sakyan monastics. He won`t do it.” And they made a bet on whether he would.
Those scoundrels then went to Udāyī and said, “Venerable, while we were enjoying ourselves in the park, we sent a message to such-and-such a sex worker, asking her to come, but she refused. Would you please persuade her?”
Udāyī agreed. He then went to that sex worker and said, “Why don`t you go to those men?”
She told him why.
“Please go. I know them.”
“If you know them, Sir, I`ll go.” And those men took her to the park.
Then that lay follower complained and criticized him, “How could Venerable Udāyī act as a matchmaker for a brief affair?”
The monks heard it, and the monks of few desires complained and criticized him, “How could Venerable Udāyī act as a matchmaker for a brief affair?”
They rebuked Udāyī in many ways and then told the Buddha. Soon afterwards he had the Sangha gathered and questioned Udāyī: “Is it true, Udāyī, that you did this?”
“It`s true, Sir.”
        \n \n
    </string>
</resources>