<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="buttonAboutSanghadisesaText">about the rules of sanghadisesa</string>
    <string name="textAboutSanghadisesa"> \n Sanghadisesa \n \n This term means [violation] "involving the participation of the Community in the primary (adi) and subsequent (sesa) procedures". \n It follows from the fact that in case of violation of any of the rules of this class, it is the Community that initially imposes punishment on the monk (including a redemptive period and a probation period), imposes it again if the monk has not fulfilled the established requirements, and when the monk has fulfilled all the requirements, removes the punishment from him.   \n  This section contains 13 rules, in the case of the first nine, the monk is credited with a violation immediately after the offense is committed, in the last four only after the offender has been reprimanded three times in the form of a Community procedure.  \n  \n  \n  \n</string>
    <string name="buttonTextAboutParajika">about the rules of parajiki</string>
    <string name="textAboutParajika">\n Parajika (defeat) \n \n The book Parivara says that this term comes from a verb meaning to lose or to be defeated. A monk who commits the four prohibited acts described in this chapter is considered to have succumbed to his mental defilements (upakkilesa) to an extent that overpowers his original goal of becoming a monk. The Vibhanga gives a number of metaphors to illustrate the irreversible nature of defeat: like a man with his head cut off like a withered leaf torn from the stem… like a flat stone broken in two, which cannot be united… like a palm tree with its top cut off, unable to continue growth. A monk who commits any of these prohibited acts is irreversibly excommunicated from the life of the monastic community and is no longer considered a monk.</string>
    <string name="textSanghadisesa1">1 \n Intentional emission of semen, except while dreaming, entails initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText1">\n 1.(Sukkavissaṭṭhisikkhāpada) \n Правило о намеренном извержении семени \n <i>The rule of intentional ejaculation of the seed</i> \n \n <b>sañcetanikā sukkavissaṭṭhi \n \n aññatra</b>  <b>supinantā \n \n saṃghādiseso.</b> \n \n Намеренное извержение семени (за исключением семяизвержений во время сновидения) влечёт за собой первоначальное и последующие собрания Общины.  \n \n <i>Intentional ejaculation of semen (with the exception of ejaculations during a dream) entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</i>
    \n \n Это правило возникло в результате одного события связанного с достопочтенным Сеййясака \n \n
Сеййясака был недоволен святой жизнью и по совету достопочтенного удаина перстал воздерживаться от намеренного извержения семени. \n \n
\n \n This rule arose as a result of an event connected with the Venerable Seiyasaka \n \n
Seiyasaka was dissatisfied with the holy life and, on the advice of the venerable Udain, stopped to abstain from intention ejaculation. \n \n
<b>Исключения</b> \n \n
Во время сна, если сперма выделяется во время сна, никакой вины в этом нет. \n \n
Во время дефекации, если какое-то количество сперматозоидов все-таки выходит, намерение для этого отсутствует, никакой вины не совершается. \n \n
Во время ухода или чистки половых органов (из-за воспаления, травмы, укуса насекомого и т.д.) путем нанесения лекарства (крема, мази и т.д.), если выделяется немного сперматозоидов, а желание к этому отсутствует, вины в этом нет. \n \n
Если во время того, как монах ложится в постель, желая эякулировать, он зажимает свой половой орган между бедер или сильно сжимает его в кулаке, и во время сна выделяется сперма, он совершает сангхадишешу. \n \n
Если сперма высвобождается естественным образом без намерения монаха сделать это и что в этот момент этот последний действительно испытывает удовольствие, он не совершает никакой ошибки. Однако, если во время семяизвержения он воспользовался возможностью выпустить сперму рукой, он совершает сангхадишешу. \n \n
Если монах, настойчиво глядя на тело женщины со жгучим желанием, эякулирует, он не совершает сангхадишешу. \n \n
Примечание: Это правило частично соответствует третьему из десяти правил. \n \n \n


<b>Exceptions</b> \n \n
While sleeping, if the sperm is released during a dream, no fault is being committed. \n \n
While defecating, if some sperm does come out, the intention for it being absent, no fault is being committed. \n \n
While nursing or cleaning one`s sex (due to an inflammation, an injury, an insect bite, etc.) by putting medicine (cream, ointment, etc.), if some sperm is released, the desire for it being absent, no fault is being committed. \n \n
If at time of getting into bed, wishing to ejaculate, the bhikkhu wedges his sex between his thighs or holds it strongly in his fist and whilst sleeping the sperm is released, he commits the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
If the sperm is naturally released without the bhikkhu`s intention to do so and that at this moment this latter does experience pleasure, he does not commit any fault. However, if during ejaculation, he seized the opportunity to release the sperm with his hand, he commits the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
If while insistently looking at the body of a woman, with a burning desire, a bhikkhu ejaculates, he does not commit a saṃghādisesa. \n \n
Note: This rule partly corresponds with the third of the ten precepts. \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textSanghadisesa2">2 \n If any monk under the influence of lust, with a distorted mind,
makes bodily contact with a woman, takes her by the hand, by a lock of hair,
or caresses other parts of her body, this entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText2">\n 2. (Kāyasaṁsagga) \n
Похотливый телесный контакт  \n
<i>Lustful body contact</i> \n \n
<b>Yo pana bhikkhu otiṇṇo vipariṇatena cittena mātugāmena \n \n saddhiṁ kāyasaṁsaggaṁ samāpajjeyya \n \n hatthaggāhaṁ vā veṇiggāhaṁ vā aññatarassa vā aññatarassa vā aṅgassa parāmasanaṁ, \n \n saṅghādiseso”ti. \n \n</b>
        Если какой-либо монах под влиянием похоти, с искажённым умом, совершит телесный контакт с женщиной, возьмёт её за руку, за локон волос, или будет ласкать другие части её тела, это влечёт за собой первоначальное и последующие собрания Общины. \n \n
<i>If any monk under the influence of lust, with a distorted mind, makes bodily contact with a woman, takes her by the hand, by a lock of hair, or caresses other parts of her body, this entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community. \n \n</i>
    \n \n Это правило возникло в результате одного события связанного с достопочтенным Удаином \n \n
Удаин с похотью дотрагивался до жены брахмана. Это произошло, когда брахман со своей женой осматривали кути Удаина. \n \n

\n \n This rule arose as a result of one event related to the Venerable Udain \n \n
Udain touched the brahman`s wife with lust. This happened when a brahmin and his wife were examining Udain`s kuti. \n \n

Прикасаясь к ткани или к драгоценностям, которые носит женщина, монах совершает нарушение, но не сангхадисесу (при условии, что к женщине не прикасаются вместе с этой частью ткани или драгоценным камнем). \n \n

Точно так же, прикасаясь к женщине, которая является его родственницей, например, к матери или сестре, даже с умом, свободным от похоти, он совершает нарушение, но не сангхадисесу. \n \n

В случайном прикосновении к женщине нет нарушения. Однако, если женщина прикасается к монаху, это не должно восприниматься пассивно, потому что, если он получает от этого удовольствие, даже на короткое время, он немедленно совершает самгхадисесу. \n \n

Прикасаясь к женщине каким-либо предметом, монах совершает тхулачайя. \n \n

<b>Примечание:</b> Это правило частично соответствует третьему из десяти правил. \n \n

By touching a cloth or a jewel worn by a woman, a bhikkhu commits a fault but not the saṃghādisesa (provided the woman is not touched along with that part of cloth or jewel). \n \n
In the same way, by touching a woman who is a relative, his mother or sister for instance, even with a mind rid of lust, he commits a fault but not the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
By accidentally touching a woman, there is no fault. However, if a woman touches a bhikkhu, this latter must not undergo it passively, because if he takes pleasure in it, even for a short while, he immediately commits the saṃghādisesa. \n \n
By touching a woman with some kind of utensil, a bhikkhu commits a thullaccaya. \n \n
Note: This rule partly corresponds with the third of the ten precepts. \n \n \n</string>
</resources>