<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="buttonAboutSanghadisesaText">about the rules of sanghadisesa</string>
    <string name="textAboutSanghadisesa"> \n Sanghadisesa \n \n This term means [violation] "involving the participation of the Community in the primary (adi) and subsequent (sesa) procedures". \n It follows from the fact that in case of violation of any of the rules of this class, it is the Community that initially imposes punishment on the monk (including a redemptive period and a probation period), imposes it again if the monk has not fulfilled the established requirements, and when the monk has fulfilled all the requirements, removes the punishment from him.   \n  This section contains 13 rules, in the case of the first nine, the monk is credited with a violation immediately after the offense is committed, in the last four only after the offender has been reprimanded three times in the form of a Community procedure.  \n  \n  \n  \n</string>
    <string name="buttonTextAboutParajika">about the rules of parajiki</string>
    <string name="textAboutParajika">\n Parajika (defeat) \n \n The book Parivara says that this term comes from a verb meaning to lose or to be defeated. A monk who commits the four prohibited acts described in this chapter is considered to have succumbed to his mental defilements (upakkilesa) to an extent that overpowers his original goal of becoming a monk. The Vibhanga gives a number of metaphors to illustrate the irreversible nature of defeat: like a man with his head cut off like a withered leaf torn from the stem… like a flat stone broken in two, which cannot be united… like a palm tree with its top cut off, unable to continue growth. A monk who commits any of these prohibited acts is irreversibly excommunicated from the life of the monastic community and is no longer considered a monk.</string>
    <string name="textSanghadisesa1">1 \n Intentional emission of semen, except while dreaming, entails initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</string>
    <string name="sanghadisesaText1">\n 1.(Sukkavissaṭṭhisikkhāpada) \n Правило о намеренном извержении семени \n <i>The rule of intentional ejaculation of the seed</i> \n \n <b>sañcetanikā sukkavissaṭṭhi aññatra</b> \n \n <b>supinantā saṃghādiseso.</b> \n \n Намеренное извержение семени (за исключением семяизвержений во время сновидения) влечёт за собой первоначальное и последующие собрания Общины.  \n \n <i>Intentional ejaculation of semen (with the exception of ejaculations during a dream) entails the initial and subsequent meetings of the Community.</i></string>
</resources>