<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="buttonNissayaText">petition (Nissaya) \n Being under guardianship</string>
    <string name="nisayaText">
        \n <b>Ācariyo me bhante hohi \n</b>
           <i>Venerable one, be my teacher \n \n</i>
           <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n \n
           <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n \n \n </string>

    <string name="textGeneralInfo">
        <i>NOTE: THIS TEXT IS A COMPILATE TRANSLATION OF THE FOLLOWING BOOKS: "BUDDHIST MONASTIC CODE", "PA-AUK SAMANERA COURSE", VISUDHIMAGGA AND THE TEXT OF THE VINAYA HIMSELF, AS WELL AS A COMPILATION OF THEMATIC SUTTAS. \n \n
   FOR COMRADES FROM CHITTAVIVEKA AND AMBAKOTE - PRESENT AND FUTURE. </i>\n\n
Dhammanisita bhante. \n \n \n \n

         You can win a certain battle \n
         a thousand times a thousand warriors, \n
         but the one who conquers only one thing - himself \n
         truly the greatest Conqueror of all. \n
         (Dhammapada 103)\n\n

         <b>Why and why was the monastic discipline - Vinaya - established?</b> \n \n
AN 2.280: *The Blessed One said+: “Monks, for these two reasons the Tathagata has prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n
     • (1) for the well-being of the Sangha and \n
     • (2) for the sake of the peace of the Sangha. \n\n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of restraining capricious individuals, and \n
     • so that well-behaved monks can enjoy peace of mind. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the stains of *mental defilements+ inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the stains of *mental defilements+ inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the hostilities inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the hostilities inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the flaws inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the flaws inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of containing the dangers inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the dangers inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of restraining the negative qualities inherent in this life, and \n
     • for the sake of dispelling the negative qualities inherent in the future life. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • out of compassion for the laity, and \n
     • stopping groups of those who have evil desires. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • so that those who lack trust can gain confidence, and \n
     • for the sake of increasing the *trust+ of those who *already+ have trust. \n \n

*And also+ for these two reasons the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples. Which two? \n

     • for the sake of the duration of the good Dhamma, and \n
     • for the sake of promoting discipline. \n \n

For these two reasons, the Tathagata prescribed rules of training for his disciples.” \n \n \n

        <b>Why leave worldly life?</b> \n \n
In the Ratthapalla Sutta, the king answers this question like this: \n

         ◦ Due to losses due to aging. \n
         ◦ Due to losses due to illness. \n
         ◦ Due to loss of wealth. \n
         ◦ Due to the loss of relatives. \n \n
Venerable Ratthapala`s answer was as follows:\n

         ◦ Existence in any world is impermanent, swept away. \n
         ◦ Existence in any world has no refuge, no defender. \n
         ◦ Existence in any world has nothing “of its own”; everything will have to be left behind. \n
         ◦ Existence in any world is inferior, insatiable, in slavery to thirst. \n \n

<b>Samanera age</b> \n \n
Once upon a time, a disease called “Ahivata” swept across India. Many died. One
Only the father and son were left alive in the family, and both were tonsured as bhikkhus and samaneras, respectively. When this bhikkhu went begging, his samanera son followed him. People began to think that the monk did not keep his vow of abstinence from sexual activity, and that a certain nun gave birth to a child for him. To avoid misunderstandings, the Buddha established
The minimum age for tonsure as a samanera is 15 years. If the candidate for samanera is under 15 years old, then in order to receive tonsure he must be able to “drive away crows.” The history of this
The rule is this: during the same illness of "Ahivata", two children *under 15 years old+ of a laywoman outlived their mother, and whenever bhikkhus came, these children ran up to them.
Venerable Ananda, wanting to help them, told the situation to the Buddha; he asked: “When they eat, the crows can take their food. Are they able to drive them away?” Ananda replied: “Yes, they are capable,” and thus the second rule for tonsure as a samanera appeared. \n \n \n \n
   <b>Being under guardianship (Nissaya)</b> \n \n
A samanera should always live dependent on a mentor [a senior and experienced bhikkhu]. There are two types of guardianship: from a mentor (upajjhāya) *giving tonsure+, and from a teacher (ācariya) *teacher of recitations for tonsure, teacher of Dhamma and Pali language, teacher as performer
temporary mentor, etc.+. The relationship between them is identical in many details, so
the general word “mentor” is used. Both are expected to perform for life
corresponding obligations [vatta - “protocol”+ in relation to each other *see. below+, the texts define their relationship as “like father and son.” One bhikkhu is allowed to have
students of more than one samanera, but only if he is competent enough to
so that his samaneras do not behave inappropriately with each other (in the history of the introduction of this rule, two samaneras under the leadership of Venerable Upananda raped each other, and later one of
they were raped by a bhikkhuni [nun]). Bhikkhus are also prohibited from luring each other
following them. By "following them" Commentary 1 describes samanera or bhikkhus disciples. \n \n
A samanera can change his mentor only in two cases: \n \n

         ◦ The mentor leaves forever, dies, cuts off his hair, etc. \n
         ◦ He doesn`t like his mentor (he`s immoral, etc.)\n
Even if one bhikkhu mentor is immoral, another bhikkhu is expressly prohibited
lure those who follow him, but a statement can be made so that they realize the undesirability of their stay with such a mentor. Quoted by Commentary
example shows that such a hint need not be subtle: “Your life in
depending on an immoral person is like coming to bathe, but smearing yourself with excrement." If those to whom such a statement is addressed realize its truth and ask the bhikkhu making such a statement to be their mentor, then there will be no offense for the second one if he accepts them. \n \n

If, for some reason, the student and the mentor live in different monasteries, but their formal status in relation to each other is not severed, then the first must temporarily take guardianship from a certain teacher *in the monastery where he is located+ until reunification with mentor.
In view of the fact that the Mahavagga (I.72.1) gives dukkat a *formal designation for improper action; for bhikkhus only] for one who comes under the tutelage of an unconscious bhikkhu, then the newly initiated one is allowed to observe the behavior of his potential teacher for four or five days before entering under his tutelage. \n \n

Guardianship under a mentor ends if he loses his hair, dies, leaves forever, etc. In this case, you need to take a new mentor. A mentor may also reject a student if he sees that under his teaching he is making no progress in the Dhamma and Vinaya, or that he shows no respect and only experiences negative emotions towards
to your mentor, etc. If a mentor abandons a student, then his duty is to apologize, and his duty
mentor - forgive. If the student goes back to his old ways, he may be rejected completely. \n \n

How to enter the tutelage of a mentor? Throwing his outer robe over his left shoulder, leaving his right shoulder bare, he bows to the potential mentor, and then, kneeling with palms together over the heart, repeats the following passage three times: \n \n

Upajjhāyo me bhante hohi - "Venerable One, be my mentor." \n \n

This often happens right during the tonsure ceremony. Coming under the tutelage of a teacher follows the same procedure, but the phrase changes: \n \n
    Ācariyo me bhante hohi; āyasmato nissāya vacchāmi - "Venerable One, be my teacher; I will live under your tutelage" \n \n \n
<b>Four Great Standards (cattāro mahāpadesā)</b> \n \n
Separately, there are standards given by the Buddha in order to evaluate certain situations that were not covered by the canonical Vinaya and its prohibitions and resolutions, and on the basis of this to draw a conclusion about whether this or that is appropriate for someone who has passed away from worldly life or not. On
On the same basis one can also judge the actual applicability of a particular fragment from the Commentary on the Vinaya. \n \n
Mv.VI.40.1: “Whatever I forbid, saying: “It is not permitted,” if it corresponds to what is not permitted, if it contradicts (literally, “infringes upon”) what is permitted, then it is not
allowed for you. Whatever I prohibit by saying, “It is not permitted,” if it is in accordance with what is permitted, if it is contrary to what is not permitted, then it is permitted for you. Whatever I permit by saying, “This is permitted,” if it corresponds to what is not permitted,
if it is contrary to what is permitted, then it is not permitted for you. And whatever I permit by saying, "This is permitted," if it is in accordance with what is permitted, if it is contrary to what is not permitted, then it is permitted for you." \n \n \n \n
<b>Basic Vows</b> \n \n
Samaneras take 10 vows: \n \n

     1. Abstinence from killing living beings. \n \n

Next, the factors of the complete path of murder will be given, only the coincidence of all is the kamma of murder and, accordingly, a violation of the training rule: \n \n
         i. Object: a living thing, including fetuses (in the case of humans, etc.), eggs in the case of bedbugs, etc. - starting from the first conscious tact upon appearance in the womb, etc. \n \n
         ii. Intent: To consciously and intentionally wish for the death of some being. \n \n
         iii. Perception: the creature is perceived as a creature. \n \n
         iv. Effort: For the sake of the death of this or that creature, any means were taken (including contract killing, etc.). \n \n
         v. Result: the creature dies. \n \n \n \n

     2. Refraining from taking what is not given. \n \n

Next, the factors of the complete path of theft will be given, only the coincidence of all is the kamma of theft and, accordingly, a violation of the training rules: \n \n
         i. Object: something belonging to a person or group of people. \n \n
         ii. Perception: is the perception that something belongs to some person or group of people. \n \n
         iii. Intent: There is an intent to steal. \n \n
         iv. Effort: theft occurs (the value factor of the object plays a role only for bhikkhus; for samanas, even stealing blades of grass is a violation). \n \n \n \n

     3. Abstinence from sexual intercourse \n \n

Through the mouth, genitals, anus. This includes sexual intercourse with animals and corpses, as well as with oneself (in case of excessive flexibility). For the full path of misconduct must
there is an aspect of consent (quite mental) to sexual intercourse and awareness of what is happening. \n \n \n \n

     4. Abstinence from lying \n \n

Factors:\n\n

         i. Intention: the goal is to distort some truth. \n \n
         ii. Effort: By any means, deliberately distorted information is conveyed to another person. \n \n
Jokes are considered lies. There will be no misconduct only in two cases: the samanera speaks very quickly and hastily, or by one he means another. \n \n \n \n

     5. Abstinence from alcohol and fermented drinks leading to carelessness \n \n

According to the 4 Great Standards, this also includes drugs. If a bhikkhu accepts
intoxicating substances without knowing that they are such, then he still commits an offense. For a samanera, it will be an offense only if he uses them consciously. \n \n \n \n
     6. Abstain from eating during prohibited times (after noon until dawn the next day). \n \n

In the afternoon, five tonics are allowed in case of feeling hungry, tired and other ailments: honey, sugar/molasses (molasses), ghee, solid butter and liquid butter. Juices from any fruit are allowed, except for “juice from grains”; The commentary defines this as prohibiting the juice from the fruit
palmyra, coconut, jackfruit, pumpkin, bottle gourd, white pumpkin, nutmeg and breadfruit. Licorice juice is prohibited. Juices from any vegetables are allowed, except
cooked. If you have taken a laxative, then after 12 you can drink strained
broths made from rice, meat and mung bean. In case of poor health, a substance is allowed (how to prepare it is written in the Commentary when analyzing 3 parajiki), which is similar to miso paste (loṇasovīraka/loṇasocīraka; now this is not prepared anywhere; is miso the equivalent -
the question is controversial with a bias towards a negative answer), if you do not feel unwell, then you need to stir it in water and drink it like that (Mv.VI.16.3). \n \n

Recipe for the above substance from the Commentary:
Loṇasovīrakavatthusmiṃ– loṇasovīrakaṃ nāma sabbarasābhisaṅkhataṃ ekaṃ bhesajjaṃ. Taṃ kira karontā harītakāmalakavibhītakakasāve sabbadhaññāni sabbaaparaṇṇāni sattannampi dhaññānaṃ odanaṃ kadaliphalādīni sabbaphalāni vettaketakakhajūrikaḷīrādayo sabbakaḷīre macchamaṃsakhaṇḍāni anekāni ca madhuphāṇitasindhavaloṇanikaṭukādīni bhesajjāni pakkhipitvā kumbhimukhaṃ limpitvā ekaṃ vā dve vā tīṇi vā saṃvacchar āni ṭhapenti, taṃ paripaccitvā jamburasavaṇṇaṃ hoti. Vātakāsakuṭṭhapaṇḍubhagandarādīnaṃ siniddhabhojanaṃ bhuttānañca uttarapānaṃ bhattajīraṇakabhesajjaṃ tādisaṃ natthi. Taṃ panetaṃ bhikkhūnaṃ pacchābhattampi vaṭṭati, gilānānaṃ pākatikameva, agilānānaṃ pana udakasambhinnaṃ pānaparibhogenāti. \n \n \n \n

     7. Refrain from watching dancing, listening to singing and music \n \n
This includes looking at it all and participating directly. If a samanera accidentally stumbles upon such sights while going for alms, etc., then it will not
a misdemeanor until he consciously chooses to look. \n \n \n \n

     8. Abstinence from wearing garlands, perfume, cosmetics and body jewelry \n \n

When washing, you can use odorous elements in case of skin itching, small ulcers, open abscesses and bad body odor (according to the Commentary “like a horse”). \n \n \n \n
     9. Abstaining from high and luxurious seats and beds \n \n

A high bed is on average defined as the size of an elbow (about 45 cm, but there is an interpretation in form 16.7 cm). You can sit on seats higher than this size only if they are
you can`t lie down. Seats and benches with luxurious or unusual decorations or upholstery are prohibited, as are those made from luxurious materials. However, if it was received
an invitation to the house from the householders, and they have prepared high and luxurious seats, then you can sit on them (but not lie down), and in any case you cannot sit on the platform, throne or anything upholstered in cotton. \n \n \n \n
     10. Abstinence from accepting gold and silver (money) \n \n

A samanera cannot accept money and jewelry, and he also cannot specifically ask others to accept it for him (as a command). If someone puts money or jewelry next to him, then he is obliged to inform about his refusal to do so. However, there is no need to report
his refusal if he is sincerely unattached to these things. It is allowed to have a lay person who will manage the money (kappiya). Formally, donors of money are only allowed to say who your kappia is, or indicate that there is a box for money in the monastery
donations. \n \n \n \n
<b>10 Liṅganāsana (destruction of samanera status)</b> \n \n
If a samanera commits the 10 offenses described below, then his status as a samanera ceases. He falls away from the Three Jewels and loses his right to use the kuti and other property of the Sangha, remaining a samanera only outwardly. If he does not see the offense and does not want to make an effort to correct himself, then he should be expelled, which is the responsibility of the mentor.
Performing Lingasana is, in general, a reversible process: you need to re-take the Triple Refuge (and, optionally, anew the 10 vows) from your mentor. Can`t recover in
status only if the tenth lingasana has been completed. The top ten offenses that destroy the status of a samanera are as follows: \n \n
     1) Killing living creatures - even destroying bedbug eggs. \n \n
     2) Taking what is not given - even a small blade of grass. \n \n
     3) Sexual contact. \n \n
     4) Lie - even as a joke. \n \n
     5) Conscious drinking of alcohol and other types of intoxicants. \n \n
     6) Statement of blasphemy about Buddha (in the spirit: “he was not Enlightened, did not comprehend Liberation,” etc.). \n \n
     7) Speaking blasphemy about the Dhamma (“does not lead to Liberation”, etc.). \n \n
     8) Statement of blasphemy about the Sangha ("took the wrong path," etc.). \n \n
     9) Having a false view (about “self” [atta], about the non-existence of kamma and
rebirth, the non-existence of other worlds, etc. See Brahmajala Sutta, DN1. As soon as it turns out that the samanera has a false view, the bhikkhu must tell him three times to abandon this view; after the third time, if the samanera still persists, then he
status is destroyed). \n \n
     10) Sexual intercourse with a bhikkhuni (nun). \n \n

As was said above, the tenth lingasana (sexual intercourse with a bhikkhuni) is irreversible: whoever has completed it until the end of his life no longer has the right to become a samanera again, nor does he have the right to be tonsured as a bhikkhuni. The first five lingasanas coincide with the first five 10 samanera vows.
The commentary also adds that a samanera who knowingly drinks alcohol in violation of the fifth vow may be restored to his former status as a samanera, but can never be ordained as a bhikkhu in this life; not all communities share this point of view,
because it is not supported by canon. \n \n \n \n
<b>10 Daṇḍakamma (punishments and grounds for punishment)</b> \n \n
In case of violation of the last five of the 10 vows (starting from “abstinence from drinking alcohol”, etc.), the mentor can impose punishment (daṇḍa) on the samanera. Punishment is also imposed for the following actions: \n \n
     • He strives for the lack of something for the bhikkhus \n \n
     • He strives for the bhikkhu`s lack of housing \n \n
     • He seeks harm and danger for bhikkhus \n \n
     • He insults bhikkhus \n \n
     • He strives to disrupt unity among bhikkhus \n \n
In total there are 10 grounds for punishment. Punishment is the responsibility of the mentor. Another bhikkhu can impose punishment on a samanera only with the permission of his mentor.
The commentary adds that if the mentor was informed three times of his misdeeds
samanera, but did not do anything, then it is permissible to impose punishment bypassing the mentor. The sub-commentary adds that the Sangha should be notified first. \n \n
The main punishment for samaneras is a ban on their presence in any place.
It is impossible to prohibit the entire territory of the monastery, but only certain places where one or another samanera usually lives and spends time. Punishments in the form of food intake restrictions are prohibited. The commentary says that punishments in the form of carrying water, sand, etc. are also acceptable.
Punishments should be carried out with the idea that the samanera will correct itself and will no longer commit this or that offense. Cruel punishment, including corporal punishment, is prohibited. \n \n
In addition to the ten vows, it is also common practice for the Samaras to observe the 75 rules of the Sekhiya section and the protocols (vatta) of the Khandhak. \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textProtocols">

    </string>

    <string name="buttonTextAbout1">PROTOCOLS and general information</string>
    <string name="buttonTextAbout2">Who is allowed to take monastic vows, and who is not allowed.</string>
    <string name="textButtonGenInfo">general information</string>
    <string name="textButtonProtocolsInfo">protocols</string>
</resources>