<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">

    <string name="textButton1">1. Protocol in relation to the mentor</string>
    <string name="textButton2">2. Protocol in relation to the student</string>
    <string name="textButton3">3. Protocol for arriving bhikkhus</string>
    <string name="textButton4">4. Resident Bhikkhu Protocol</string>
    <string name="textButton5">5. Protocol of departing bhikkhus</string>
    <string name="textButton6">6. Anumodana Protocol</string>
    <string name="textButton7">7. Protocol when inviting someone to the house</string>
    <string name="textButton8">8. Protocol when going for alms</string>
    <string name="textButton9">9. Protocol while in the wilderness</string>
    <string name="textButton10">10. Protocol in the home</string>
    <string name="textButton11">11. Sauna protocol</string>
    <string name="textButton12">12. Toilet protocol</string>


    <string name="text1" tools:ignore="StringEscaping,TypographyEllipsis"><b>Protocol in relation to the mentor teacher (mentor)</b> \n \n
Rising early in the morning, taking off his sandals, putting his outer robe over his shoulder, the student should
Prepare the mentor with wood sticks for brushing teeth and water for rinsing the mouth washing the face. [Comment: you should bring three dental sticks: small, medium and large; as well as cold and hot water for rinsing the mouth and for bathing. What kind of mentor will this make?
use for three days, should be brought regularly from now on. If he uses it without special preference, then you should bring him what is available. (The commentary here means by "preparing" only the display of these things in the right place for this purpose, and not in
direct transfer of these to the mentor. Once this has been done, you should begin sweeping the restroom and surrounding area while the mentor brushes his teeth and washes his face. Then, while the mentor is still busy with his morning shower, he should proceed to the next step). \n \n

We need to prepare the seat. If there is drinking porridge, then after washing a shallow bowl, you need to offer it to the mentor. When the mentor drank the porridge, then, giving him water, taking a bowl,
holding it down (so as not to wet the clothes), you need to wash the bowl thoroughly, but do not scrape it Comm.: hitting it on the floor, and then put it in its place. When the mentor gets up, you need to remove his seat, and if the area is dirty, sweep it up. \n \n

If the mentor wishes to go to the village for alms, give him his undergarment, taking his spare one (which he is currently wearing). (This is one of several passages that show that at the time the canon was compiled it was already the practice to have spare vestments). Give him his belt, outer robe and outer cloak sangati; bhikkhus have 3 robes,
the last of which is the cloak, which you need to put on before going out into the populated area, folding them in a straight line. After rinsing his cup, give it to him while it is still wet. \n \n

If the mentor wants an assistant *when going for alms, then, putting on your robes (see sekkhiya), putting on the belt, washing and taking the cup, help the mentor. Don`t go too far
behind him, and don`t walk too close. Comment: one or two steps will be just right. Take the contents of the mentor`s cup. Comment: if the mentor`s cup is heavy or too hot for
in order to hold it, then take his cup and give yours (which, most likely, will be lighter and not so hot). (In the Sangha, where, during begging, cups are carried in covers -
carriers, the student can simply pick up the mentor`s cup). \n \n

Do not interrupt the mentor when he speaks. If he is one step away from committing a crime, then he should be stopped.
Comment: you should speak in an indirect manner, with hints, to bring him to his senses. Sub-comm.: contrary to the fact that protocols to a mentor may not be fulfilled due to illness, this particular point should always be fulfilled. \n \n

When returning before the mentor, you should prepare the seat. Set out the water to wash your feet,
a footrest and a stone for wiping your feet. Then go meet him; when you meet him, take his cup. Give him a spare undergarment, take away the one he is currently wearing. If the outer garment and outer cloak of the mentor are wet from perspiration, then they should be dried on
sun, but don`t keep them there for too long. Fold the garments Sub-com: separately so that they do not wrinkle. (This, as Vinaya-mukha notes, helps extend the life of the fabric.) Fold
    belt for robes. (From these phrases it is clear that in those days, bhikkhus walked in their abodes only in their lower robe, even when eating). \n \n
`If you managed to get alms and the mentor wants to eat, then prepare food for him and give him water to wash the bowl. Ask if he needs drinking water. [Comment: if there is enough time before lunch, you should wait next to the mentor until he eats, then offer him
drinking water, and only then eat it yourself. If there is not enough time, then you should simply put out drinking water and start eating.] \n \n
`When he has finished eating, then, after giving him water, take his cup, lower it lower, and then wash it carefully, but do not scrape it. Then, having dried the bowl, place it in the sun for a short time, but not for long. \n \n

`Put his cup and robes back in their place of storage. When cleaning, you should take the bowl in one hand, and with the other hand, check under the bed (if there is anything there that will harm the bowl), and then put the bowl itself there. But you should not place it on bare ground *Comm.: any place where it
will become dirty.] When putting away the clothes, you need to take them in one hand, and run the other along the pole or clothes line *Comment: to check if there are any notches that can catch and tear the fabric], after checking, you need to throw the clothes over the pole or rope so that the edges are away from you and the fold is towards you. *Comment: the fold of fabric should not be directed towards the wall, because if there is
serif, then you can tear the robe in the middle.] \n \n

`When the mentor stands up, remove his seat. Remove the foot wash water, foot rest and foot stone. If it`s dirty, sweep it up. \n \n
`If the mentor wants to swim, prepare a swimming place. If he wants to bathe in cold water, prepare cold water; if he wants to bathe in hot water, prepare hot water. \n \n

`If the mentor wants to visit the bathhouse, mix the bathing powder, moisten the bathing clay, take the bathhouse bench and follow the mentor. Having given him a bench, take away his clothes, and
put it aside [Comm: where there is no soot and smoke.] Give him the powder or clay. If you can, also go to the bathhouse. When entering, you should smear your face with clay and cover yourself in front and behind (in
"three circles" [see sekhiya 1] there is no need to wrap yourself up). \n \n

`Sit so as not to crowd the elders and not to infringe upon the younger ones. Help a mentor *Comm:
light the fire, provide him with hot water and clay]. When leaving the bathhouse, cover yourself in front and
behind, take the bench. Help the mentor also in the subsequent bathing. After taking a swim,
The student should come out of the water first, dry himself and put on his underwear. Then he should wipe the water from the mentor and give him his lower and upper garments. \n \n
`When taking the bath bench, the student should return first, prepare the seat, prepare water for washing feet, a footrest and a stone for wiping feet. (When the mentor has sat down,) ask him if he wants something to drink. \n \n

`If the mentor wishes to recite *Comm: memorize passages from the Dhamma or Vinaya], then
should be recited. If he wants to ask you *Comm: about the meaning of these passages], then you should answer the questions. \n \n
`If the mentor`s place of residence is dirty, then, if the student is capable, he needs to clean it. You need to take out his bowl, robes, sitting cloth, sheet, pillow and mattress. Need to
    carefully remove the bed without scraping [Comm.: on the floor], and without hitting it against the door. Take it out
a spittoon... a board for leaning on... Having noted where the floor covering is located, it also needs to be removed. \n \n
`If there are cobwebs in your home, then they need to be removed, starting from the ceiling. Window frames and surrounding areas, as well as corners (of rooms), should be wiped. If the walls are decorated with ocher and there appears
mold, then you need to wet a rag and wipe it off. If the floor is laid out, it needs to be washed. If the floor is bare earth, then you need to sweep it, first moistening it with water: “Let its dust rise and not
will dirty the room." Any rubbish must be taken out. \n \n

`After drying the floor covering in the sun, you need to clean it and knock it out of dust, and then lay it down as it was laid before. After drying and cleaning the bed supports, you need to bring them back and
put them where they were. After drying the bed... bench... mattress... pillow... seat fabric... spittoon... leaning board... carefully bring it in. \n \n
`If dusty winds blow from any direction, then you need to close the windows on that side. If
The weather is cold, then the windows need to be opened during the day and closed at night. If the weather is hot, then the windows should be closed during the day and opened at night. \n \n
`If the surrounding area is dirty, you need to sweep it. If the porch... meeting room... fireplace... toilet is dirty, then you need to clean, sweep. If water for washing (feet) or water for drinking is not set, then it needs to be set. If there is no water in the toilet for flushing, then it
needs to be exposed. \n \n

`If the mentor has any dissatisfaction with the life of purity, then it should be dispelled, or someone who will be able to do this should be found, or a conversation should be held about the Dhamma. If the mentor has any concerns (regarding his adherence to the training rules), then he
it must be dispelled, or someone who can do it must be found, or a conversation about the Dhamma must be had. If the mentor has a view (diṭṭhigata: a strong view regarding a matter about which one should not expand [see MN 72], or a completely false view [see eg MN 22].), then it must be dispelled, or one must be found who will be able to do this, or should a conversation about the Dhamma be held. \n \n

`If the mentor has committed a serious offense (saṅghādisesa) and deserves appropriate
disciplinary action (temporary suspension), then the student should make an effort: “How would the Community impose disciplinary action on my mentor?” \n \n

`If the Community wants to hold a meeting against the mentor (criticism, expulsion [from a certain monastery], suspension, etc.), then the student should make an effort: “How could the Community not make such a decision, or how can I soften its decision?” . If a certain decision is made against him, then the student should make an effort: “How can I make my mentor behave appropriately and correct himself, so that the Community withdraws its decision?” \n \n

`If the mentor`s robes need to be washed, then the disciple should wash it, or make an effort: “How can I make sure that my mentor`s robes are washed?” If a mentor needs to cut robes... If he needs to brew dye... If a mentor needs to dye robes... When dyeing a mentor`s robes, you need to do it consistently and carefully. \n \n
`Without the permission of the mentor, the disciple should not give his begging bowl to anyone [Comm: who is on bad terms with the mentor], and should not receive his bowl from such a person. Not
    one should give cloth for robes... Monastic necessities... One should not cut his hair... One should not look after him... One should not bring back alms to him... \n \n
`Without the permission of the mentor, the student should not go into the city, cemetery (for meditation), or leave the area. \n \n
`If the mentor is sick, then the student should take care of him while he is alive; he should remain with him until he is restored. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text2" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis"><b>Protocol in relation to the student</b> \n \n
—Cv.VIII.11.2-18
`The student should be helped with recitation, questioning, exhortation and instruction. If the mentor has a cup, but the student does not, then the first should provide the second with one, or make an effort: “How would my student receive the cup?” If the mentor has fabric for robes… a monastic necessity... \n \n

`If the student is sick, then the mentor should (fulfill his own obligations in relation to him: from morning procedures and right up to cleaning his home; but the mentor does not need to take off his sandals and put on clothes in a certain way, he does not need to help the student when walking for
alms, and there is no prohibition to interrupt). \n \n

`If a student has dissatisfaction with life in purity, then it should be dispelled, or someone who will be able to do this should be found, or a conversation should be held about the Dhamma. If
the student has anxiety (regarding his adherence to the rules of training), then she
it must be dispelled, or someone who can do it must be found, or a conversation about the Dhamma must be had. If a student has a view (diṭṭhigata: a strong view regarding a matter about which one should not expand *see MN 72+, or a completely false view *see e.g. MN 22+.), then it must be dispelled, or one must be found who will be able to do this, or should a conversation about the Dhamma be held. \n \n

`If the mentor has committed a serious offense (saṅghādisesa) ... [for bhikkhus only] \n \n

`If a student`s clothes need to be washed, the mentor should say to him: “This is how to wash,” or make an effort: “How can I get my student`s clothes to be washed?” If a student`s robes need to be cut... If a student`s robes need dye... If a student`s robes need to be dyed... \n \n

`If a student is sick, then the mentor should take care of him while he is alive; he should remain with him until he is restored. \n \n


[extra] Chullawagga XII.2.8
— Cv.VIII.12.2-11
Is it permissible to follow what has become customary? What is the permission regarding what has become customary? \n \n
`Thinking: “This is the custom of my mentor, this is the custom of my teacher,” it is permissible to act accordingly. But this is allowed in some cases, but not in others. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text3" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis"><b>Protocol of arriving bhikkhus</b> \n \n
 To the arriving bhikkhu [Comm.: having entered the environs of the monastery,] thinking: “Now I will go into
monastery", taking off his sandals, putting them on the ground and knocking out the dust, lowering his umbrella, opening
their head (from robes, etc.; (the protocol for being in the wilderness *see below+ shows that bhikkhus, walking in the heat through the wild wilderness, covered their heads with robes), throwing up their outer
robe on your back/shoulder (khandha), you should enter the monastery carefully and without haste. Walking in
he needs to mark the place where the bhikkhus who live in the monastery on a permanent basis gather. Having gone there, you should put down your cup and robe, and, having chosen a suitable seat, sit down (from this passage, as well as from the passage in the protocol regarding the mentor, it seems that in those days the monks walked around the monastery only in their lower robe, which today was would be rude). Should
ask where there is water for drinking and water for washing feet, and use it if necessary. My
feet, you need to pour water with one hand and wash your feet with the other; You should not wash your feet with the same hand that pours water. \n \n
 If you ask about a rag for wiping your sandals, you should wipe them. When wiping, you need to first wipe them with a dry cloth and then with a damp one (Vinaya-mukha adds that if the sandals are in
swampy mud, then the order is reversed). After washing the rag for wiping, squeezing it out, you need to put it back in place. \n \n
 If the local bhikkhu is older, then the arriving monk should bow to him. If you are younger, then you should accept a bow from him. You should ask about his place: “Which place was assigned to me?” You should ask whether it was previously used for housing or not. Should
ask in what radius the begging takes place [Comment: “Far or close?
How early should you leave?" Places "outside the radius" are the homes of people with false
views, as well as those who have little food]. One should ask which families are in training (i.e. those families whose faith is so strong that they begin to sacrifice to their detriment, and,
to avoid possible exploitation of their generosity, they are allocated separately; optionally they are included in the stream, etc.). You should ask where the place to cope is big
needs and minor needs, where is drinking water, where is water for washing, where are camping staffs. You should ask about the time of the Community meetings. \n \n
 If the fallen dwelling has not been previously used for its intended purpose, then, having opened the door, you need to stand outside for a while [Comment: in case there is a snake or some kind of non-
human]. If it is dirty, and if the furniture is stacked on top of each other, then, if he is able, he needs to tidy up and disassemble *Comment: if he is not able to clean the entire home, then he needs to clean only the section where he plans to live.] \n \n
 When cleaning, you need a cloth for sitting, a sheet, a pillow and a mattress. You need to carefully remove the bed without scraping *Comment: on the floor+, and without hitting it against the door. Take out the spittoon… the leaning board... Having noted where the floor covering is, it also needs to be taken out.

 If there are cobwebs in your home, then they need to be removed, starting from the ceiling. Window frames and surrounding areas, as well as corners (of rooms), should be wiped. If the walls are decorated with ocher and there appears
mold, then you need to wet a rag and wipe it off. If the floor is laid out, it needs to be washed. If the floor is bare earth, then you need to sweep it, first moistening it with water: “Let its dust rise and not
will dirty the room." Any rubbish must be taken out. \n \n
 After drying the floor covering in the sun, you need to clean it and knock it out of dust, and then lay it down as it was laid before. After drying and cleaning the bed supports, you need to bring them back and
put them where they were. After drying the bed... bench... mattress... pillow... seat fabric... spittoon... leaning board... carefully bring it in. \n \n
 Remove the cup and the garments to their place of storage. When cleaning, you should take the bowl in one hand, and with the other hand, check under the bed (if there is anything there that will harm the bowl), and then put the bowl itself there. But you should not place it on bare ground *Comm.: any place where it will become dirty.+ When removing clothes, you need to take them in one hand, and run the other along a pole or rope for clothes *Comm.: to check if there are notches there + which can catch and tear the fabric,+ after checking, you need to throw the garments over a pole or rope so that the edges are away from you and the fold is towards you. *Comment: the fold of the fabric should not be directed towards the wall, because if there is a notch there, the robe can be torn in the middle. \n \n

 If dusty winds blow from any direction, then you need to close the windows on that side. If
The weather is cold, then the windows need to be opened during the day and closed at night. If the weather is hot, then the windows should be closed during the day and opened at night. \n \n
 If the surrounding area is dirty, you need to sweep it. If the porch... meeting room... fireplace... toilet is dirty, then you need to clean, sweep. If water for washing (feet) or water for drinking is not set, then it needs to be set. If there is no water in the toilet for flushing, then it
needs to be exposed. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text4" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis"><b>Resident Bhikkhu Protocol</b> \n \n
—Cv.VIII.1.2-5
  A resident bhikkhu, seeing a senior bhikkhu arriving, should prepare a seat for him [Comment: if a resident is busy with construction work, dyeing robes, etc., then he should
stop to prepare the seat, etc. for the arrival. If he sweeps around the chetiya, then he needs to put the broom aside to prepare the seat, etc. To the one who arrives, if he is smart,
the resident should be told to finish sweeping first. If a resident is preparing medications for a patient and his illness is not serious, then the first one needs to be distracted by the protocol. If the illness is serious, then you need to finish the medications first. In both cases, the arriving monk, if he is smart, should tell the resident to finish with the medicine first.] Water for the feet, a footrest and a stone for wiping the feet should be set out. Going out to meet
senior arriving bhikkhu, you need to take the cup and robe from him, ask if you need
drinking water, is water needed for washing feet [Comment: if the arrival has used the first vessel of water, you need to ask if he needs more]. If you have the opportunity/desire, you should
wipe the arrival`s sandals. [Comment: the resident should start fanning the older arrival, first from the back of his legs, then from his body, then his head; if he says "enough" then
you need to start fanning more gently, and so on until the third “enough”, after which you need to stop.] \n \n
  If the arrival is older, he should bow and prepare his home, saying
whether it was recently used for its intended purpose or not [Comment: before his arrival in the home, one should have cleaned up.] It should be said where is the place for major and minor needs, where is the drinking water, where is the water for washing, where are the walking staffs, what is the walking radius behind
alms, where is the meeting place of the Community.
  If the arriving monk is younger than the resident, then the second one, while he is sitting, should be told where to put the cup and vestments, where to sit. You need to tell him where the place is for washing his feet, where the rag is for wiping his sandals. You should accept a bow from the younger one. We need to show him where he is
home We need to show him where the place is for small and big needs... where the Community meeting place is. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text5"><b>Protocol of departing bhikkhus</b> \n \n
—Cv.VIII.2.2-3
  A bhikkhu who is about to leave, having placed wooden and earthen things in their places, closing windows and doors, can leave after saying so. [Comm: if his hut is not a suitable place for storing the above items, then they should be moved to a bathhouse, under an overhanging rock, or to any other place where the rain will not reach them.] If in
There are no bhikkhus in the monastery; a samanera should announce his departure. If there is no samanera, then to the minister at the monastery. If there are no ministers, then a secular follower. Then, putting
a four-stone bed, putting a bed on a bed, a bench on a bench, putting the rest (seats, floor coverings, bedding) on top in a pile, removing wooden and clay things,
Having closed the windows and doors, he can go. [Comment: if his hut is not attacked by termites, then there is no need to talk about leaving or lay the bed on four stones, etc. (And yet it would be good to transfer this into the hands of a responsible person, if there is one, of course.)] \n \n
  If the house is leaking, then, if he is able, he should repair the roof, or give birth to
effort: “How can I patch the leak?” If it works, then good. If not, then put down the bed
on four stones in a place where there are no leaks, putting the bed on top of the bed, the bench on the bench, putting the rest in a pile on top, putting away wooden and clay things in a suitable place,
close the windows and doors, he can leave. \n \n

  If the entire home is leaking, then, if he is able, he should move things (bedding and
other short-lived things) to a certain village, or make an effort: “How can I move all this to the village?” If it works, then good. If not, then put the bed on four stones, the bed on the bed, the bench on the bench, putting the rest in a pile on top, removing the wooden and
clay things to a suitable place, covering them with grass or leaves, he can go, thinking: “I hope that at least some of them will remain intact.” \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text6" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis"><b>Anumodana Protocol</b> \n \n
— Cv.VIII,3.2-3
"I allow that anumodana (rejoicing in the merits of donors) be performed in the house where
invited" ... "I allow anumodana to be carried out by the eldest of the bhikkhus" [Comm.: if the owner of the house (where he was invited) asks another bhikkhu to give anumodana instead of the eldest, then it is possible: neither one nor the other will commit an offense, but the elder should notify before anumodana.+... "I allow four or five bhikkhus, who are elders (10+ years of monastic experience) or non-elders, to stand in the refectory behind (with the most senior bhikkhus who gives anumodana)."[Comm. : if he gives them permission to leave early, then they can go. They can also ask permission to leave.+... There is a story connected with this: a certain elder stood in the refectory behind, although he was very much in need of relief. Holding back, he fell into
fainting... "When there is a reason, I allow you to leave after the next monk in line is informed." \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text7"><b>Protocol when inviting someone to the house</b> \n \n
—Cv.v.VIII.4.1
  If the monastery announces the time of departure by invitation to a certain house, then, putting on the lower robe in three krgua, tying the belt, aligning the upper robe in line with the lower one, putting on
outer cloak (only bhikkhus have it), aligning the outer cloak in line with the outer robe, tying a thread in a loop (at the bottom of the cloak), washing the bowl, taking the bowl, you should carefully and without haste enter the village. You should not go ahead of your elders. \n \n

  You should not sit crowding your elders, and you should not drive the younger ones out of their places. In populated areas, you should not spread your outer raincoat and sit on it. When water is given to wash the bowl, you should accept the water by grasping the bowl with both hands. After lowering the bowl, it should be washed thoroughly
[Comment: so that the water does not make a sound], but do not scrape it (on the floor). If there is someone who collects the used water, then it should be carefully poured into the vessel without splashing. If this is not the case, then it should be carefully poured onto the ground. \n \n
  When rice is served, grab the bowl with both hands and take the rice. You need to leave room for the bean curry. If there is ghee, oil or seasonings [Comm.: or any other food, even just
rice], then the senior monk should say: “Divide everyone equally.” [Comment: If a certain dish is not enough for everyone, but only for two bhikkhus, then the elder should not say so.
One or two monks should take what is offered, even if the others do not receive anything] / The senior monk should not eat until everyone has had rice. SECKHII 31-55. \n \n
  The senior monk should not take water to rinse the bowl until everyone has eaten. When water is given to rinse the bowl, you should take the water while holding the bowl with both hands. After lowering the bowl, it should be washed thoroughly, without scraping on the floor. If there is someone who collects the used water, then it should be carefully poured into the vessel without splashing. If this is not the case, then it should be carefully poured onto the ground. SEKCHIA 56.\n\n

  When returning, new bhikkhus should go first, followed by the elders. [Comment: new bhikkhus should wait for the elders at the door and then line up according to seniority. Walking through the village, they must keep a distance between themselves so that other people can freely
pass.] SECKHIAH 1-26. \n \n

—Cv.VIII.4.3-6 \n \n

In addition to the protocol when invited to the house - the manners of Buddha *MN 94+: \n \n

When he is given water to bowl, he does not lift the bowl too high or hold it too low, or tilt it forward or backward. It takes not too little, but not too much water for the bowl. It cleans the bowl without creating splashing noise. He washes the bowl without rotating it. He does not put the bowl on the floor to wash his hands - but when he washes his hands, he washes
cup; and when he washes the cup, he washes his hands. He drains the water from the bowl neither too far *from himself+, nor too close, without splashing it. \n \n

When he is given rice, he does not lift the bowl too high or hold it too low, or tilt it forward or backward. He takes not too little, but not too much rice.
He adds the sauce in the right proportion. It doesn`t add more sauce to the lump than
it`s supposed to. He turns the lump over two or three times in his mouth and then swallows it -
not a single grain of rice passes through unchewed, not a single grain of rice remains in his mouth when he puts the next lump into his mouth. \n \n
When he eats food, he tastes but does not crave the taste. His food intake is eightfold: he eats not for the sake of entertainment, not for the sake of intoxication, not for the sake of
physical beauty and attractiveness, but simply for the sake of the durability and duration of this body, to eliminate discomfort, *thereby+ supporting *the conduct+ of a holy life. He thinks: “This way I will eliminate the old feelings of *hunger+ and will not create new feelings *from
overeating+. I will be healthy, I will not be blamed for this, I will be in relief.” \n \n

When he has eaten and taken water for the cup, he does not lift the cup too high or hold it too low, or tilt it forward or backward. It takes not too little, but not too much water for the bowl. It cleans the bowl without creating splashing noise. He is washing
bowl without rotating it. He does not put the cup on the floor to wash his hands - but when he washes his hands, he washes the cup; and when he washes the cup, he washes his hands. He drains the water from the bowl neither too far *from himself+, nor too close, without splashing it. \n \n

When he has eaten, he places the bowl on the floor, neither too far nor too close. He doesn`t care much about the cup, but he isn`t careless about it either. \n \n
When he has eaten, he sits silently for some time, but does not miss the time allotted for anumodana. When he has eaten and said anumodana, he does not criticize the food and does not expect other food. He instructs, compels, encourages and delights those who listen with discourse exclusively on the Dhamma. After that, he gets up from his seat and leaves. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text8"><b>Protocol when going for alms</b> \n \n
  A bhikkhu going for alms to a certain village, wearing a lower robe of three krgua, tying a belt, aligning the upper robe in line with the lower one, putting on an outer cloak (only the
bhikkhu), having aligned the outer cloak in line with the outer robe, tying a thread in a loop (at the bottom of the cloak), washing the bowl, taking the bowl, you should carefully and without haste enter the village.
SEKKHHII 1-25. \n \n

  When entering the yard, he should make the following observation: “I will go in like this and come out like this.” You should not enter in a hurry, you should not leave in a hurry. You shouldn`t stand too far, you shouldn`t stand too close. Shouldn`t stand too long, shouldn`t walk away too
early. While standing still, you should observe whether the residents of the yard want to offer something or not.
If the potential donor gets up from his seat, he puts the work aside. grabs a spoon and a plate, then
you should stand and wait for him. When alms are given, they must be received into the bowl by raising the outer
cloak with your left hand, extending the bowl with your right hand, and then grabbing it with both hands. If the giver is a woman, then she should not look at her face [Comment: this is also true for male givers.] Then you should observe whether they want to offer bean curry. If the giver takes a spoon and a plate, then you should stand and wait. When alms have been received, you should leave carefully and without haste, covering the bowl under your outer cloak. SECKHII 1-25. \n \n

  Whoever returns first from begging should prepare the seats,
set out water for washing feet, a footrest and a stone for wiping feet. After washing the container for leftover food, it should be put out. Drinking water and drinking water should be provided
rinsing the bowl. Whoever returns from begging last, if there are leftovers of food, then if he wants, he can eat them. If he doesn`t want to, then they should be thrown there,
where there are no crops, or into water where there are no living creatures (so as not to pollute it). He should remove the seats, and prepare water for washing his feet, a footstool and a stone for drying his feet.
Water should be provided for drinking and rinsing the bowl. The refectory should be swept. Whoever sees an empty container for drinking water, water for drinking water, or water for washing the toilet, should fill these containers. If he cannot do it alone, then he should call with a gesture
help someone, but there is no need to fall into idle talk for this reason. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text9"><b>Protocol while in the wilderness</b> \n \n
  A bhikkhu living in the wilderness, getting up early in the morning, putting the bowl in the bowl case, putting it on his shoulder, throwing the robe over his shoulder/back, putting on sandals, putting wooden and glazed things in their places, closing the windows and doors, can leave his home . Thinking: “Now I will enter the village,” taking off my sandals, lowering them to the ground, knocking them out of the dust, putting them in a bag and throwing it over my shoulder, putting on the lower robe in three krgua, tying the belt, aligning the outer robe in line with
the lower one, putting on the outer cloak (only bhikkhus have it), aligning the outer cloak in line with the outer robe, tying a thread in a loop (at the bottom of the cloak), washing the bowl, taking the bowl, should
enter the village carefully and without haste. SEKKHHII 1-25. (Based on the fact that the protocols say to dress in robes according to a standard pattern only when entering the village, it can be assumed that monks living in the wilderness could wear robes in any way they wanted, as long as they were not naked. Protocol when returning to the wilderness (see . below) says that, in the time of the Buddha, after going for alms, bhikkhus walked back with folded robes on their heads.) \n \n

  When entering the yard, he should make the following observation: “I will go in like this and come out like this.” You should not enter in a hurry, you should not leave in a hurry. You shouldn`t stand too far, you shouldn`t stand too close. Shouldn`t stand too long, shouldn`t walk away too
early. While standing still, you should observe whether the residents of the yard want to offer something or not.
If the potential donor gets up from his seat, he puts the work aside. grabs a spoon and a plate, then
you should stand and wait for him. When alms are given, they must be received into the bowl by raising the outer
cloak with your left hand, extending the bowl with your right hand, and then grabbing it with both hands. If the giver is a woman, then she should not look at her face *Comment: this is also true for male givers.+ Then you should observe whether they want to offer bean curry. If the giver takes a spoon and a plate, then you should stand and wait. When alms have been received, you should leave carefully and without haste, covering the bowl under your outer cloak. SECKHII 1-25. [Comment: if in
If there is no water in the wilderness, then you can eat in the village, wash what you need, and then return to your home. If there is water in the wilderness, then you only need it in your home.] \n \n
  After leaving the village, putting the bowl in the case and putting it on your shoulder, folding your clothes and throwing them over (over?) your head, putting on your sandals, you can continue on your way. \n \n

  A bhikkhu living in the wilderness should provide drinking water and water for washing the bowl, should maintain a fire and always have sticks for lighting it, should have
with the marching staff exposed, you should remember the zodiac signs in whole or in part
constellations (in order to be able to calculate the date of uposatha, one should be skilled in the main directions of the world (to find the way if lost (according to the original story, all this is done in order to
so that possible thieves do not mistake the bhikkhus for other thieves). \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text10"><b>Protocol in the home</b> \n \n
  Whatever dwelling a bhikkhu lives in, if he is able, he should keep it clean. (As in the protocol for arriving monks + insert:) dust must be knocked out into the wind, avoiding the gathering place of the monks, dwellings, places of drinking water, water for washing the bowl. \n \n

  If the younger one lives in a dwelling with an older bhikkhu, then, without the permission of the second one, the first one should not recite, give a talk about the Dhamma, open windows, close windows [Comm.: no
the need to ask permission before opening or closing doors; You can ask about this in advance. If two people get along well, then there is no need to constantly ask]. When meditating while walking, the younger one should turn where the older one is, and also do not need to touch him with the edge of his robe. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text11"><b>Sauna protocol</b> \n \n
—Cv.VIII.7.2-4
  No matter who enters the bathhouse, if there is a lot of soot there, then it should be removed. If the bathhouse is dirty, it
needs sweeping. You should mix the bathing powder, moisten the clay, and pour water into the water tray. When entering the bathhouse, you need to smear your face with clay, covering yourself in front and behind. There is no need to crowd out older bhikkhus or disadvantage younger ones. If he wants/is able, then he can help the elders
monks in the bath [Comment: maintain the fire, give them clay and hot water]. When leaving the sauna, you need to pick up the sauna bench, covering yourself in front and behind. . If he wants/is able, then he can help the senior monks with further bathing [Comment: e.g. rub body parts with it].
When swimming after a bath, you should not swim in front of an elder, or swim upstream from an elder. When leaving the water, you need to let those entering the water pass. \n \n
  Whoever leaves the bathhouse last should wash it, put out the fire and close the doors. \n \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="text12"><b>Toilet protocol</b> \n \n
—Cv.VIII.8.2
You always need to wash yourself. Priority does not apply to the toilet queue.
Before entering the toilet, you need to cough to check if anyone is there. There is no need to make loud noises when defecating. If it`s dirty, the toilet needs to be cleaned. If the area around the toilet is dirty, it needs to be swept. [Omitted all details relating to toilets and
procedures in the toilet (like wiping with chopsticks) of that time, which are not done now]. \n \n \n \n</string>
</resources>