<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">
    <string name="mainButtonLiveBuddha">THE LIFE OF BUDDHA</string>
    <string name="mainButtonTeachersLecture">DHAMMADESANA</string>
    <string name="mainButtonStofiDlyaDeclomacii">RECITATION</string>
    <string name="mainButtonShortSuttas">SUTTAS</string>
    <string name="mainButtonMonksRules">FOR LAYS AND MONKS</string>
    <string name="namerenie_sumedhi">1. Sumedha\`s Intention</string>
    <string name="son_mahamayi">2. Mahamaya\`s Dream</string>
    <string name="rogdenie_sidharthi">3. The Birth of Siddhartha</string>
    <string name="mudrec_asita">4. Sage Asita</string>
    <string name="pervoe_dostigenie_dgani">5. The first achievement of jhana</string>
    <string name="spasenie_lebedya">6. Saving the swan</string>
    <string name="demonstraciya_umenii">7. Demonstration of skills</string>

    <string name="pudja">\n<b>Vandana</b>\n</string>
    <string name="sutta">\n<b>Sutta</b>\n</string>
    <string name="buttonTextAnumodana">\n<b>Anumodanā</b>\n Blessings \n</string>
    <string name="buttonTextReflections">\n<b>recitations for reflection</b>\n </string>

    <string name="drugie_declomacii">\n<b>declamations for reflection</b>\n</string>
    <string name="button_karaniya_metta">Karania metta sutta</string>

    <string name="DeklomaciyaAlmsWish"><b>БЛАГОПОЖЕЛАНИЯ МИРЯНАМ ПРИ ВЗЯТИИ ДАНЫ</b> \n \n \n
        <u>ВАРИАНТ 1</u> \n
<b>Abhivādana-sīlissa—Niccaṁ vuḍḍhāpacāyino;</b> \n \n
<i>Постоянно выражая почтение нравственности и тем кого следует почитать</i> \n \n
<b>Cattāro dhammā vaḍḍhanti—Āyu vaṇṇo sukhaṁ balaṁ.</b> \n \n
<i>Пусть увеличиваются четыре дхаммы: долголетие, успех, благополучие, здоровье</i> \n \n
<b>Ayu raro ge sampatti,</b> \n \n
<i>Желаю вам долголетия и отсутствия болезней.</i> \n \n
<b>Sage sampatti me vacha,</b> \n \n
<i>Пусть у тебя будет перерождение на небесах.</i> \n \n
<b>Ato nibbana sampatti,</b> \n
<b>Imina te samijjhatu.</b> \n \n
<i>Пусть однажды ты достигнешь Ниббаны!</i> \n \n \n
        <b>Комментарий:</b> \n \n
    Однажды жили вместе два подвижника и практиковали аскетизм.
        Позже один из них вернулся к мирской жизни и женился.
        Когда у него и его жены родился сын, они отвели мальчика к другому подвижнику.
        Он сказал: «Живите долго!» родителям, но ребенку ничего не сказал.
        Родители были удивлены и спросили его, почему он это сделал. Подвижник сказал,
        что своими силами видел, что мальчик умрет еще через семь дней.
        Он послал их увидеть Будду, который мог знать, как предотвратить его смерть.
    Когда они подошли к Будде, он снова сказал: «Живите долго!» только родителям и ничего сыну.
        Чтобы предотвратить свою смерть, он велел родителям построить у их дома беседку и
        посадить в нее ребенка на кушетку. Затем он послал нескольких монахов повторять тексты для защиты.
        Многие боги и другие небесные существа пришли в павильон и присутствовали на нем.
        На седьмой день прибыл сам Будда. Затем в павильон пришел злой демон и стал у входа.
        Он ждал возможности напасть на мальчика. Но поскольку вокруг было так много могущественных существ,
        он не мог приблизиться к нему. Пение продолжалось всю ночь, а утром демону пришлось уйти.
        Маленького ребенка удалось спасти. \n
        Затем он выразил свое почтение Будде, который сказал ему:  «Живи долго!
    Прошло много лет и мальчик вырос. Однажды он пришел к Будде и спросил его, как обрести долголетие. n \n
        Будда ответил этим стихом, сказав, что те, кто уважает людей с добродетельным характером и
        оказывает почтение тем, кто достоин почтения, обретут не только долголетие, но также красоту, счастье и силу. \n \n \n</string>

    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaKaraniyaMettaSutta"> \n <b>KARANIA METTA SUTTA</b>\n \n\n<b><u />Karaṇīyamatthakusalena, yanta santaṃ padaṃ abhisamecca;</b>\n \n\n<i>This is what one should do who is skilled in good things and wants to achieve a peaceful state:</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Sakko ujū ca suhujū [sūjū (sī.)] ca, sūvaco cassa mudu anatimānī.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let him be able, direct and honest, meek, gentle and not proud,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Santussako ca subharo ca, appakicco ca sallahukavutti;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>satisfied and unburdensome, with few responsibilities, content with little,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Santindriyo ca nipako ca, appagabbho kulesvananugiddho.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>with calm perception abilities, reasonable, humble, and not fawning over families.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Na ca khuddamācare kiñci, yena viññū pare upavadeyyuṃ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>And let him not do the slightest thing that the wise would condemn.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Sukhino va khemino hontu, sabbasattā [sabbe sattā (sī. syā.)] bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>[And let him think:] Joyful and safe, may all beings be joyful in heart.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Ye keci pāṇabhūtatthi, tasā vā thāvarā vanavasesā;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Whatever the creatures, fragile or strong, without exception,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Dīghā vā ye va mahantā [mahanta (?)], majjhimā rassakā aṇukathūlā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>long, large, medium, small, small, thick,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Diṭṭhā vā ye va adiṭṭhā [adiṭṭha (?)], ye va [ye ca (sī. syā. kaṃ. pī.)] dūre vasanti avidūre;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>visible and invisible, living near and far,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Bhūtā va sambhavesī va [bhūtā vā sambhavesī vā (syā. kaṃ. pī. ka.)], sabbasattā bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>those who have come into the world and strive for manifestation: may all beings be joyful in heart.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Na paro paraṃ nikubbetha, nātimaññetha katthaci na kañci [naṃ kañci (sī. pī.), naṃ kiñci (syā.), na kiñci (ka.)] ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let no one upset another or despise anyone anywhere,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Byārosanā paṭighasaññā, nāññamaññassa dukkhamiccheyya.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>and let no one wish another to suffer because of anger or an unpleasant impression.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mātā yathā niyaṃ puttamāyusā ekaputtamanurakkhe;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>As a mother, at the cost of her life, is ready to protect her child, her only child,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Evampi sabbabhūtesu, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>so without restrictions to all beings he should develop this thought.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mettañca sabbalokasmi, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>For the whole world, let it develop the boundless thought of friendliness:</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Uddhaṃ adho ca tiriyañca, asambādhaṃ averamasapattaṃ.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Up, down, and in between, without obstruction, malevolence, or foe.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Tiṭṭhaṃ caraṃ nisinno va, sayāno yāvatāssa vitamiddho [vigatamiddo (bahūsu)] ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Standing, walking, sitting or lying down while not drowsy</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Etaṃ satiṃ adhiṭṭheyya, brahmametaṃ vihāramidhamāhu.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let him strive for this remembrance. It is spoken of as being in the state of brahma [straight] here</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Diṭṭhiñca anupagamma, sīlavā dassanena sampanno;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Not confused with views, moral, he has insight,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Kāmesu vinaya gedhaṃ, na hi jātuggabbhaseyya punaretīti.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>With the elimination of greed for sensual pleasures, he will never again be in the womb.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mettasuttaṃ aṭṭhamaṃ niṭṭhitaṃ. \n \n \n \n \n \n</u></b></string>
    <string name="rukovodstvo_dlya_lay">\n <b>guide for laypeople</b> \n </string>
    <string name="rukovodstvo_dlya_samaner">\n <b>guide for samanera</b> \n</string>
    <string name="sekhiya_n">75 sekhiya \n rules for training</string>
    <string name="first_category">Category one \n26 sekhiya on proper behavior:</string>
    <string name="clothing_wrapped_around_body">1-2.\nI will wear the lower garment [upper garment] wrapped around the body \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="sit_in_wheel_clothing">3-4.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] well covered \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="sit_strong">5-6.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] well restrained\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="eyes_looking_doun">7-8.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] with my eyes down \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="dont_up_clothes">9-10.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my robes pulled\nup — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="laughing_noisily">11-12.\n In a populated area, I won\`t walk [sit] laughing out loud \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="speak_noisily">13-14.\n In a populated area, I will walk [sit], talking in a lowered voice\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_body">15-16.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] rocking my body \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_urms">17-18.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk [sit], swinging my arms \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_head">19-20.\n In a populated area, I will walk [sit], shaking my head\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="hands_on_sides">21-22.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my hands on my hips \n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="covered_head">23-24.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my head covered \n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="walc_on_heels">25.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk only on my toes or on my heels \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="hugging_knees">26.\nIn a populated area, I will not sit with my knees clasped \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="pabaja_text">pabbajja \n stanzas for ceremony becoming a samanera</string>
    <string name="secondCategory">Category two \n 30 sekkhiy with regards to food:</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_priznatelno">27.\nI will eat alms gratefully\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pishi_vnimanie_na_chashe">28.\nI will take food from alms, keeping my attention on the bowl \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_vnadlegaishey_proporcii">29.\nI will accept alms with bean curry in the proper proportion \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_vroven_skraem_chashi">30.\nI will take food from alms level with the edge of the bowl\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_est_priznatelno">31.\nI will eat food from alms gratefully\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_svnimaniem_nachashu">32.\nI will eat alms food with attention directed to the bowl \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_metodichno">33.\nI will eat alms food methodically \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_karri_vnadleg_proporcii">34.\nI will eat alms food with bean curry in the proper proportion \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_kuski_skuchi">35.\nI will not eat food from alms, taking pieces from the pile \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_pryatat_karry">36.\nI will not hide bean curry and various types of food under rice out of a desire to get more \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_est_ris_kotor_prosil_za_sebya">37.\nNot being sick, I won\`t eat rice or bean curry that I asked for myself \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="smotret_vchashu_drugogo">38.\nI will not look into the bowl of another in order to find a flaw\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_brat_bolsh_kuski_pishi">39.\nI won\`t take very large chunks of food \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="rovnie_kuski_pishi">40.\nI will form even pieces of food\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="otkrivat_rot">41.\nI will not open my mouth until a piece of food has been brought to it yet \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="zasovivat_ruku">42.\nWhen eating, I will not put a whole hand in my mouth \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="govorit_snabitim_rtom">43.\nI won\`t talk with my mouth full of food \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="podnyatie_komki">44.\nI will not eat from raised lumps of food \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="pokusivat_kuski">45. \n I will not eat by biting pieces of food \n — training for compliance</string>
    <string name="nabivat_shoki">46.\nI will not eat while stuffing my cheeks\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="stryahivat_edu_sruk">47.\nI won\`t eat by shaking food off my hand \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="rasbrasivat_ris">48.\nI will not eat by scattering rice \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="visovivat_yazik">49.\nI will not eat by sticking out my tongue \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="chmokat_gubami">50.\nI won\`t eat by smacking my lips \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="prihlebivayshii_zvuk">51.\nI won\`t eat while making a slurping sound \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="oblizivat_ruki">52.\nI won\`t eat by licking my hands \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="oblizivat_chashu">53.\nI will not eat by licking the bowl \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="oblizivat_gubi">54.\nI won\`t eat while licking my lips \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="brat_sosud_gryaznoi_rukoi">55.\nI will not take a vessel of water with a hand dirty from eating \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="vilivat_vodu_v_naselennoi_mestnosti">56.\nIn a populated area, I will not pour out water to wash the bowl in which the drawings\nare left — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="tretiya_kategoriya_sekhiya">Category three \n 16 sekkhiy with regard to instruction in the Dharma:</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_szontom">57.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds an umbrella in his hand \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_sposohom">58.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds a staff in his hand\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_snogom">59.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds a knife in his hand\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_sorugiem">60.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds a weapon in his hand \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_skogobuvi">61 – 62 \n I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, wears leather [non-leather] shoes \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_vtransporte">63.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is on a vehicle \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_legachego">64.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is in a supine position\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_obhvativkoleni">65.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, sits with his knees clasped \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_sgolovnimuborom">66.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, wears a headdress \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_ssharfom">67.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is with his head covered (with a robe or scarf, etc.)\n- training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_nasidenii">68.\nSitting on the ground, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is sitting on a seat\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_boleevisokomsidenii">69.\nSitting on a lower seat, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, sits on a higher seat\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_vsidyachemesliyastou">70.\nBeing in a standing position, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is in a sitting position\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_iduchegovperedi">71.\nWalking behind, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, walks in front \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_idushegopodoroge">72.\nWithout walking on the road (path), I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, walks on the road (path) \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="o_raznom">Category four \n 3 sekkhii about different things:</string>
    <string name="spravliat_nugdu_stoya">73.\nNot being ill, I will not relieve myself of small or large needs standing up \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="spravlyat_nugdu_naposevi">74.\nNot being ill, I will not spit and relieve small or large need for crops \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="spravliat_nugdu_vvodu">75.\nNot being ill, I will not spit and relieve myself of a small or large need in water \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="taxt_pabaja">1. Triple bow before the abbot. The candidate bows and says: \n \n\n    <b>Okasa aham bhante</b> \n \n\n    2. The abbot cuts off a bunch of hair. The candidate repeats in the forward and reverse order: \n \n\n    <b>Kesa, loma, nakha, danta, tacho</b> \n\n    <i>Facial and head hair, body hair, nails, teeth, skin</i> \n \n\n    3. After cutting the hair and ablution, the candidate, taking the cassock with both hands, should approach the abbot and squatting down, put his palms together at face level (holding the cassock on the bends of the elbows) declare the desire to get a haircut: \n \n\n    <b>OkAsa kArunnam katvA pabbajjam detha me bhante aham bhante pabbajjam yAcAmi. \n\n    Dutiyampi…\n\n    Tatiyampi…</b> \n \n\n    4. Having declared, the cassock should be given to the abbot and the gatha should be declared: \n \n\n    <b>sabbe dukhE nissaranA nibbAna saccikaranattai etan kaasavan gahetva pabbajate man bhante anukampam upadai \n\n    Dutiyampi... \n\n    Tatiyampi...</b> \n\n    <i>For liberation from all suffering and achievement of Nibanna, taking this chivara, cut my hair with compassion.</i> \n \n\n    5. After it is necessary to declare, (Attention! In the first gatha, kanditat gives chivara to the mentor, in the second he asks for it.): \n \n\n    <b>sabbe dukhE nissaranA nibbAna saccikaranattai etan kaasavan datva pabbajate man bhante anukampam upadai \n\n    Dutiyampi \n\n    Tatiyampi</b> \n\n    <i>To be freed from all suffering and achieve Nibanna, by giving me this chivara, cut my hair with compassion.</i> \n \n\n    6.\n    Next, the candidate recites: \n \n\n    <b>PatisankhAyoniso civaram patisEvami, yAvadEva sitasa patighAntAya unhasa patighAtaya damsa makasa vatatape sirinsapa sampasano patighataya yAvadEva hiri kOpina paticchAdanattham.</b> \n \n\n    7. Next, the candidate goes to put on a cassock. \n \n\n    8. The candidate makes a nine-part bow: 3 standing with his palms folded over his head with the words okāsa vandāmi bhante, then standing with his knees, his palms are also folded over his head, the words are repeated. After that, the candidate makes a full bow and utters the phrase in full. \n \n\n    <b>okāsa vandāmi bhante</b> \n\n    <i>Let me honor you, honorable</i> \n\n    <b>sabbaṃ accayaṃ khamatha me bhante</b> \n\n    <i>Forgive me all mistakes, my dear</i> \n\n    <b>mayā kataṃ puññaṃ sāminā anumoditabbaṃ</b> \n\n    <i>Let the teacher rejoice in the good (deeds) I have done (them)</i> \n\n    <b>sāminā kataṃ puññaṃ mayhaṃ dātabbaṃ</b> \n\n    <i>Let the good deeds done by the Teacher be shared with me</i> \n\n    <b>sādhu sādhu anumodāmi</b> \n\n    <i>Good, good I rejoice</i> \n\n    <b>Okāsa! Dvārattena kataṁ sabbaṁ accayaṁ khamatha me Bhante</b> \n\n    <i>Allow me! Any and all misdemeanors committed, forgive me, honorable</i> \n \n\n    9. After the candidate expresses a desire to receive refuge and 10 vows: \n \n\n    <b>Okāsa ahaṃ bhante, tisaraṇena saddhiṃ</b> \n\n    <i>Let me venerable with triple refuge together</i> \n\n    <b>pabbajjā dasasīlaṃ dhammaṃ yācāmi.</b> \n\n    <i>I am going to take the vows of 10 vows</i> \n\n    <b>Anuggahaṃ katvā sīlaṃ detha me bhante.</b> \n\n    <i>Support by providing training give me the honorable</i> \n\n    <b>anukampaṃ upādāya</b> \n\n    <i>Compassion originated</i> \n\n    <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n\n    <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n\n    10. The mentor must answer: \n \n\n    <b>Yamahaṃ vadāmi taṃ vadetha</b> \n\n    <i>what I say, then repeat</i> \n\n    The candidate responds: \n \n\n    <b>āma bhante!</b> \n\n    <i>Yes venerable</i> \n \n\n    The candidate declares lines of respect. \n \n\n    <b>Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambhuddhassa(x3)</b> \n \n\n    After that, the mentor declares the lines of refuge with the ending in M, the kadidat repeats loudly and clearly: \n \n\n    <b>Buddham, saraṇam, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dhammam, saraṇam, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Saṇgham, saraṇam, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n\n    <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n\n    After that, the mentor declares the lines of refuge with the ending in ṃ, the kadidat repeats loudly and clearly: \n \n\n    <b>Buddhaṃ, saraṇaṃ, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dhammaṃ, saraṇaṃ, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Saṇghaṃ, saraṇaṃ, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n\n    <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n\n    <i>Note. There is no semantic difference in the translation. The formula of refuge can be pronounced in any language if it is accepted by a layman. If a monk, then it should be pronounced only in the Pali language. Because this is an official action in the produced within the framework of the Wine Pitaka. Therefore, all sounds should be pronounced as close as possible to the original. The pronunciation of the Refuge is duplicated in case of incorrect pronunciation. The pronunciation at the end of the \"am\" is called Makaranta sarana gamane. And with the ending on \"an\" Niggahitānta sarana gamana.</i> \n \n\n    After, the Mentor pronounces the end of the refuge: <b>Sarana gamana sampunnam!</b> \n\n    The candidate replies: <b>Ama bhante!</b> \n \n\n    From that moment on, the candidate ceases to be a layman and becomes a monk. Next, follows the adoption of 10 vows.  The mentor declares a list of vows! \n \n\\\n    <b>1.pāṇātipātā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from killing living beings abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>2.adinnādānā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from taking undone abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>3.abrahmacariyā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>The non-hermit life of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>4.musāvādā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from false abstinence speech</i> \n\n    <b>5.surāmerayamajjapamādaṭṭhānā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from the use of intoxicating substances leading to carelessness of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>6.vikālabhojanā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from eating at the wrong time of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>7.nacca gīta vādita visūkadassanā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>abstinence from dancing, singing, music, attending entertainment events</i> \n\n    <b>8.mālā gandha vilepana dhāraṇa maṇḍana vibhūsanaṭṭhānā veramaṇī</b>  \n\n    <i>from wearing garlands, using perfumes and cosmetics to decorate the body of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>9.uccā sayana mahā sayanā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from high and large beds of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>10.jāta rūpa rajata paṭiggahaṇā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from taking gold and silver abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>Imāni pabbajjā dasa sikkhāpadāni samādiyāmi (3x)</b> \n\n    <i>I accept these ten rules of tonsure</i> \n \n\n    <b>Ama bhante</b></string>
    <string name="sekhiya_about"><i> \n\n            75 Sekhiya (rules for training) \n \n\n        The term in Pali literally means to train in. \n \n\n        There are 75 rules in this section of the Vinaya, which are divided into four categories: \n \n\n        1. etiquette of wearing robes and etiquette of behavior in a populated area; \n\n        2. etiquette in accepting and eating food from alms; \n etiquette when teaching someone the Dhamma; \n\n        3. etiquette in relieving need. \n \n The sum of these rules is the person of samaner and bhikkhu,\n        and hence the appearance of the Sangha as a whole. \n \n\n        There are stories of how Bhante Sariputta was inspired by the manners of bhante Assaji and decided to join the community, as well as how King Ashoka converted to Buddhism under the impression of the manners of the young samanera.</i></string>
    <string name="button_morning_vandana_with_laymans">\n <b>morning vandana with layman at Cittawiveque Monastery</b> \n</string>
    <string name="button_morning_vandana_with_laymans2"> \n <b>Vandanā with laypeople during dāna at Chitthaviveka Monastery \n \n offering to the Bhikkhu Saṅgha  \n (in Sinhala)</b> \n</string>


    <string name="deklomation_after_evening_meditation">\n <b>Recitation after evening meditation at Cittawiveque Monastery</b> \n</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaOfterEveningMeditationO"> \n
        <b>RECLAIMATION AFTER EVENING MEDITATION AT CHITTAVIVEKA MONASTERY</b> \n \n \n
<b><u>Imaya dhammanu dhamma patipattiya buddham pujemi.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this practice be an offering to the Buddha.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Imaya dhammanu dhamma patipattiya dhammam pujemi.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this practice be an offering to the Dhamma.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Imaya dhammanu dhamma patipattiya sangham pujemi.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this practice be an offering to the Sangha.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Addha imaya patipattiya jati jara maranamha parimuccissami.</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this practice lead to liberation from birth, aging and death.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Idam me punnam kamma asavekkhaya vaham hotu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May the assavas be destroyed by this meritorious kamma.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sabbe dukha pamojjatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>All pain and pleasure</i> \n \n \n
<b>KARANIA METTA SUTTA</b> \n \n
<b><u></u>Karaṇīyamatthakusalena, yanta santaṃ padaṃ abhisamecca;</b> \n \n
<i>This is what one should do who is skilled in good things and wants to achieve a peaceful state:</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sakko ujū ca suhujū [sūjū (sī.)] ca, sūvaco cassa mudu anatimānī.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let him be able, direct and honest, meek, gentle and not proud,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Santussako ca subharo ca, appakicco ca sallahukavutti;</u></b> \n \n
<i>satisfied and unburdened, with few responsibilities, content with little,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Santindriyo ca nipako ca, appagabbho kulesvananugiddho.</u></b> \n \n
<i>with calm perception abilities, reasonable, humble, and not fawning over families.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Na ca khuddamācare kiñci, yena viññū pare upavadeyyuṃ;</u></b> \n \n
<i>And let him not do the slightest thing that the wise would condemn.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sukhino va khemino hontu, sabbasattā [sabbe sattā (sī. syā.)] bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b> \n \n
<i>[And let him think:] Joyful and safe, may all beings be joyful in heart.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ye keci pāṇabhūtatthi, tasā vā thāvarā vanavasesā;</u></b> \n \n
<i>Whatever the creatures, fragile or strong, without exception,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Dīghā vā ye va mahantā [mahanta (?)], majjhimā rassakā aṇukathūlā.</u></b> \n \n
<i>long, large, medium, small, small, thick,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Diṭṭhā vā ye va adiṭṭhā [adiṭṭha (?)], ye va [ye ca (sī. syā. kaṃ. pī.)] dūre vasanti avidūre;</u></b> \n \n
<i>visible and invisible, living near and far,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Bhūtā va sambhavesī va [bhūtā vā sambhavesī vā (syā. kaṃ. pī. ka.)], sabbasattā bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b> \n \n
<i>those who have come into the world and aspire to appear: may all beings be joyful in heart.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Na paro paraṃ nikubbetha, nātimaññetha katthaci na kañci [naṃ kañci (sī. pī.), naṃ kiñci (syā.), na kiñci (ka.)] ;</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let no one upset another or despise anyone anywhere,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Byārosanā paṭighasaññā, nāññamaññassa dukkhamiccheyya.</u></b> \n \n
<i>and let no one wish another to suffer because of anger or an unpleasant impression.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Mātā yathā niyaṃ puttamāyusā ekaputtamanurakkhe;</u></b> \n \n
<i>As a mother, at the cost of her life, is ready to protect her child, her only child,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Evampi sabbabhūtesu, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ.</u></b> \n \n
<i>so without restrictions to all creatures he should develop this thought.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Mettañca sabbalokasmi, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ;</u></b> \n \n
<i>For the whole world, let it develop the boundless thought of friendliness:</i> \n \n
<b><u>Uddhaṃ adho ca tiriyañca, asambādhaṃ averamasapattaṃ.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Up, down, and in between, without obstruction, malevolence, or foe.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Tiṭṭhaṃ caraṃ nisinno va, sayāno yāvatāssa vitamiddho vigatamiddo (bahūsu) </u></b> \n \n
<i>Standing, walking, sitting or lying down while not drowsy</i> \n \n
<b><u>Etaṃ satiṃ adhiṭṭheyya, brahmametaṃ vihāramidhamāhu.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let him strive for this remembrance. It is spoken of as being in the state of brahma [straight] here</i> \n \n
<b><u>Diṭṭhiñca anupagamma, sīlavā dassanena sampanno;</u></b> \n \n
<i>Not confused with views, moral, he has insight,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Kāmesu vinaya gedhaṃ, na hi jātuggabbhaseyya punaretīti.</u></b> \n \n
<i>With the elimination of greed for sensual pleasures, he will never again be in the womb.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ētēna saccavajjêna sabbē dukkhā vinnasatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all your suffering disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ētēna saccavajjêna sabbē bhayā vinnasatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all your fears disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ētēna saccavajjêna sabbē rogā vinnasatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all your diseases disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>jayo munindassa subodhi mūle</u></b> \n \n
<i>"Buddhas victory under the great Bodhi tree</i> \n \n
<b><u>ahosi mārassa parajāyosi</u></b> \n \n
<i>Caused Maras defeat!</i> \n \n
<b><u>ugghosayuṃ devagaṇā pasannā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Various deities exclaimed in admiration.</i> \n \n
<b><u>etena saccena jayantu tuyhaṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this truth bring you victory.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>sabbe buddhā balappattā paccekānañca yaṃ balaṃ arahantānañca tejena rakkhaṃ bandhāmi sabbaso</u></b> \n \n
<i>By the power of all the Buddhas, by the power of all the self-awakened ones, by the power of the Arhats, may I be protected in every possible way.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā dēvā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let the gods and Nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ tam anumōditvā ciram rakkhantu lōka sāsanaṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>rejoice in our beneficence and long defend Buddhism in this world.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā dēvā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let the gods and Nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ tam anumōditvā ciram rakkhantu dēsanaṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>They will rejoice in our good deeds and defend the Teaching for a long time.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā dēvā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let the gods and Nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ tam anumōditvā ciram rakkhantu maṃ paraṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>rejoice in our good deeds and protect me and others for a long time.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Iminā puññakammēna - mā me bālasamāgamō</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this merit never follow fools.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sataṃ samāgamō hōtu - yāva nibbāna pattiyā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let me follow only the wise until I achieve Nibbana.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Idaṃ me puññaṃ - āsavakkhayā vahaṃ hōtu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this merit lead me to cessation of cravings.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sabba dukkhā pamuccatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all suffering disappear.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Idaṃ no (me) ñātīnaṃ hōtu - sukhitā hontu ñātayō [3x]</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this go to the benefit of our (my) relatives. May my relatives be happy.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Dēvo vassatu kālena</u></b> \n \n
<b><u>sassasampatti hētu ca</u></b> \n \n
<b><u>phito bhavātu lōko ca</u></b> \n \n
<b><u>Raja bhavatu dhammiko</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let it rain in its own time</i> \n \n
<i>let there be a rich harvest,</i> \n \n
<i>May the world prosper</i> \n \n
<i>Let the government be righteous.</i> \n \n \n \n \n \n \n

    </string>
    <string name="button_sutta_mangala">Maha mangala sutta</string>
    <string name="button_sutta_ratana">ratana stta</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaMangala">
        \n <b>MAHA MANGALA SUTTHA</b> \n \n
         <i>A sermon on what best contributes to well-being</i> \n \n
         <b>Ēvaṃ mē sutaṃ ēkaṃ samayaṃ bhagavā sāvatthiyaṃ viharati jētavanē anāthapiṇḍikassa ārāmē</b> \n \n
         <i>So I heard: once the Perfect One was not far from Savatthi, in the Jeta grove, in the monastery of Anathapindika.</i> \n \n
         <b>Athakhō aññatarā dēvatā abhikkantāya rattiyā</b> \n \n
         <i>When the night was almost over, one deity,</i> \n \n
         <b>Abhikkantavaṇṇā kēvalakappaṃ jētavanaṃ ōbhāsetvā yena bhagavā</b> \n \n
         <i>appeared in the grove of Jeta, and, illuminating it with its radiance, to the Perfect</i> \n \n
         <b>Tenupasaṃkami upasaṅkamitvā bhagavantaṃ abhivādetvā ēkamantaṃ aṭṭhāsi</b> \n \n
         <i>approached. Approaching, it respectfully greeted him and stood aside</i> \n \n
         <b>Ēkamantaṃ ṭhitā kho sā dēvatā bhagavantaṃ gāthāya ajjhabhāsī</b> \n \n
         <i>And, standing aside, the deity then turned to the Perfect in verses:</i> \n \n
         <b>Bahū dēvā manussā ca maṅgalāni acintayuṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>"Many gods and people thought about what contributes to well-being,</i> \n \n
         <b>Ākaṅkhamānā sotthānaṃ brūhi maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>wanting to succeed. So tell me: what best contributes to it?"</i> \n \n
         <b>Asēvanā ca bālānaṃ paṇḍitānañca sēvanā</b> \n \n
         <i>"Dont deal with fools, deal with wise ones,</i> \n \n
         <b>Pūjā ca pūjanīyānaṃ ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and to honor those worthy of veneration is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Patirūpadēsavāsōca pubbē ca katapuññatā</b> \n \n
         <i>To live in a suitable area, having accumulated merit in the past,</i> \n \n
         <b>Attasammāpaṇidhi ca ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>being guided by right intentions is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Bāhusaccañca sippañca vinayo ca susikkhito</b> \n \n
         <i>Deep knowledge, skills, good discipline,</i> \n \n
         <b>Subhāsitā ca yā vācā ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Pleasant speech is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Mātāpitū upaṭṭhānaṃ puttadārassa saṅghahō</b> \n \n
         <i>Helping mother and father, taking care of wife and children,</i> \n \n
         <b>Anākulā ca kammantā ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Conflict-free work is what contributes best to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Dānañca dhammacariyā ca ñātakānañca saṅgahō</b> \n \n
         <i>Generosity, righteous living, caring for relatives,</i> \n \n
         <b>Anavajjāni kammāni ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>impeccability in deeds is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Āratī viratī pāpā majjapānā ca saṃyamō</b> \n \n
         <i>Abstaining from the vicious, avoiding intoxicating substances,</i> \n \n
         <b>Appamādo ca dhammēsu ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>mindfulness of mental qualities is what best promotes well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Gāravō ca nivātō ca santuṭṭhi ca kataññutā</b> \n \n
         <i>Respect, humility, contentment and gratitude,</i> \n \n
         <b>Kālēna dhammassavanaṃ ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>listening to the Dhamma at the right time is what is most conducive to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Khantī ca sovacassatā samaṇānañca dassanaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Patience, complaisance, seeing ascetics,</i> \n \n
         <b>Kālēna dhammasākacchā ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Discussing the Dhamma at the right time is what is most conducive to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Tapo ca brahmacariyañca ariyasaccana dassanaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Self-restraint, chastity, realization of Noble Truths</i> \n \n
         <b>Nibbāna sacchikiriyā ca ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and the realization of Nibbana is what best promotes well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Phuṭṭhassa lōkadhammēhi cittaṃ yassa na kampati</b> \n \n
         <i>The mind that remains steady in contact with the mundane</i> \n \n
         <b>Asōkaṃ virajaṃ khēmaṃ ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>carefree, pure, calm - thats what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētādisāni katvāna sabbatthama′parā′jitā</b> \n \n
         <i>Those who do this are always invincible,</i> \n \n
         <b>Sabbattha sotthiṃ gacchanti taṃ tēsaṃ maṅgalamuttaman′ti</b> \n \n
         <i>always succeeding is what best contributes to their well-being."</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sotthi te hōtu sabbadā</b> \n \n
         <i>May all prosperity follow you through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna hōtu te jayamaṅgalaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>May you gain the benefit of victory through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabbarōgō vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all illnesses be healed through the power of this truth</i> \n \n \n \n \n \n
    </string>

    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaRatana">
        \n <b>RATANA SUTTA</b> \n \n
         <i>THE TREASURE SUTTA</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatānī</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial, -</i> \n \n
         <b>Sabbēva bhūtā sumana bhavantu</b> \n \n
         <i>may you all be happy</i> \n \n
         <b>Athopi sakkacca suṇantu bhāsitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and listen to the words.</i> \n \n
         <b>Tasmā hi bhūtā nisāmētha sabbē</b> \n \n
         <i>Listen, spirits!</i> \n \n
         <b>Mettaṃ karōtha mānusiyā pajāya</b> \n \n
         <i>be friendly to the human race,</i> \n \n
         <b>Divā ca ratto ca haranti ye baliṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>who brings his offerings day and night</i> \n \n
         <b>Tasmā hi ne rakkhata appamattā</b> \n \n
         <i>Zealously guard the people!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yaṃ kiñci vittaṃ idha vā huraṃ vā</b> \n \n
         <i>No treasure here or in the next world</i> \n \n
         <b>Saggēsu vā yaṃ ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>no jewels of heaven</i> \n \n
         <b>Na nō samaṃ atthi tathāgatēna</b> \n \n
         <i>will not equal the Ultimate.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi buddhē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure resides in the Buddha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Khayaṃ virāgaṃ amataṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>The destruction of passions, freedom from them, and then the highest immortality</i> \n \n
         <b>Yadajjhagā sakyamunī samāhitō</b> \n \n
         <i>which Sakyamuni attained in concentration</i> \n \n
         <b>Na tena dhammēna samatthi kiñci</b> \n \n
         <i>There is nothing equal to this state!</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi dhammē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure dwells in the Dhamma.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yambuddhaseṭṭhō parivaṇṇayī suciṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This path of purity, praised by the Supreme Buddha</i> \n \n
         <b>Samādhimānata rikaññamāhu</b> \n \n
         <i>invariably leads to concentration.</i> \n \n
         <b>Samādhinā tēna samō na vijjati</b> \n \n
         <i>Nothing compares to this concentration.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi dhammē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure dwells in the Dhamma.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ye puggalā aṭṭha sataṃ pasatthā</b> \n \n
         <i>Eight of them, glorified by the Righteous One,</i> \n \n
         <b>Cattari ētāni yugāni honti</b> \n \n
         <i>four pairs of them,</i> \n \n
         <b>Te dakkhiṇeyyā sugatassa sāvakā</b> \n \n
         <i>disciples of the Achieved Good, worthy of donation:</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēsu dinnāni mahapphalānī</b> \n \n
         <i>what is bestowed upon them will bear good fruit.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ye suppayuttā manasā daḷhēna</b> \n \n
         <i>Those who are steadfast and thorough</i> \n \n
         <b>Nikkāminō gōtamasāsanamhi</b> \n \n
         <i>Follow the teachings of Gotama, free from [mental defilements],</i> \n \n
         <b>Te pattipattā amataṃ vigayha</b> \n \n
         <i>achieved what they should have achieved by gaining the Immortal.</i> \n \n
         <b>Laddhā mudhā nibbutiṃ bhuñjamānā</b> \n \n
         <i>They are freely enjoying their attained Liberation.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yathindakhīlō pathaviṃsito siyā</b> \n \n
         <i>The pillars of Indra stand firmly in the ground,</i> \n \n
         <b>Catubhi vātēhi asampakampiyo</b> \n \n
         <i>not shaken by the four winds</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathūpamaṃ sappurisaṃ vadāmi</b> \n \n
         <i>Nothing can shake the righteous</i> \n \n
         <b>Yo ariyasaccāni avecca passati</b> \n \n
         <i>who has comprehended noble truths, who has clearly comprehended them.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ye ariyasaccāni vibhāvayanti</b> \n \n
         <i>Who has comprehended noble truths</i> \n \n
         <b>Gambhīrapaññēna sudēsitāni</b> \n \n
         <i>proclaimed in perfection by the Wise,</i> \n \n
         <b>Kiñcāpi te honti bhusaṃ pamattā</b> \n \n
         <i>no matter how careless he may be in the future,</i> \n \n
         <b>Na te bhavaṃ aṭṭhamamādiyanti</b> \n \n
         <i>will not experience the eighth rebirth.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Sahāvassa dassanasampadāya</b> \n \n
         <i>He who has gained insight</i> \n \n
         <b>Tayassu dhammā jahitā bhavanti</b> \n \n
         <i>got rid of three traits:</i> \n \n
         <b>Sakkāyadiṭṭhi vicikicchitañca</b> \n \n
         <i>belief in individuality, insecurity and </i> \n \n
         <b>Sīlabbataṃ vāpi yadatthi kiñci</b> \n \n
         <i>any attachment to rituals and ceremonies.</i> \n \n
         <b>Catūhapāyehi ca vippamuttō</b> \n \n
         <i>He is free from being reborn in the four bad realms,</i> \n \n
         <b>Chacābhiṭhānāni abhabbō kātuṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and unable to commit the six heaviest offenses. </i>\n\n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Kiñcāpi so kammaṃ karōti pāpakaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>What a bad thing to do</i> \n \n
         <b>Kāyena vācā udacetasā vā</b> \n \n
         <i>the person who entered the stream did not commit the body, speech or thoughts,</i> \n \n
         <b>Abhabbō so tassa paṭicchādāya</b> \n \n
         <i>he is unable to hide it</i> \n \n
         <b>Abhabbatā diṭṭhapadassa vuttā</b> \n \n
         <i>because it s impossible for someone who sees the path.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Vanappagumbē yathā phussitaggē</b> \n \n
         <i>Like the tops of trees</i> \n \n
         <b>Gimhānamāsē paṭhamasmiṃ gimhē</b> \n \n
         <i>everything is in bloom at the beginning of summer</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathūpamaṃ dhammavaraṃ adesayī</b> \n \n
         <i>so is His exalted Dhamma,</i> \n \n
         <b>Nibbānagāmiṃ paramaṃ hitāya</b> \n \n
         <i>leading to the tranquility of Nibbana, striving for the highest good.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi buddhē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure resides in the Buddha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Varō varaññū varadō varāharō</b> \n \n
         <i>Incomparable, he is the one who sees Nibbana, gives Nibbana, brings the Noble Eightfold Path,</i> \n \n
         <b>Anuttarō dhammavaraṃ adēsayi</b> \n \n
         <i>told us this supreme Truth.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi buddhē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure resides in the Buddha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Khīṇaṃ purāṇaṃ nava natthi sambhavaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Their past is exhausted, the new does not arise,</i> \n \n
         <b>Virattacittāāyatikē bhavasmiṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Their mind is not attached to future becoming.</i> \n \n
         <b>Te khīṇabījā avirūḷhicchandā</b> \n \n
         <i>Their seed has been destroyed and they have no more desire for a new life.</i> \n \n
         <b>Nibbanti dhīrā yathāyaṃ padīpō</b> \n \n
         <i>Such sages are extinguished like the flame of this lamp.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatāni</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial,</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathāgataṃ dēvamanussapūjitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>A Tathagata honored by gods and men</i> \n \n
         <b>Buddhaṃ namassāma suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Lets glorify the Buddha too. Let there be prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatāni</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial,</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathāgataṃ dēvamanussapūjitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>A Tathagata honored by gods and men.</i> \n \n
         <b>Dhammaṃ namassāma suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Lets glorify the Dhamma too. Let there be prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatāni</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial,</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathāgataṃ dēvamanussapūjitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>A Tathagata honored by gods and men.</i> \n \n
         <b>Saṅghaṃ namassāma suvatthi hōtuti</b> \n \n
         <i>Lets glorify the Sangha too. Let there be prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabba dukkhaṃ vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all your suffering disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabba bhayō vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all your fears disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabba rōgō vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all your diseases disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="rukovodstvo_dllya_bhikkhu">\n <b>guide for bhikkhu</b> \n</string>
    <string name="button_upasampada">upasampada \n Stanzas for the ceremony of becoming a Bhikkhu</string>
    <string name="button_patimokha">Rules of patimokkha</string>
    <string name="buttonAboutParajika">ABOUT THE RULES OF PATIMOKKHA</string>
    <string name="buttonaboutParajikaNakazanie">THE SYSTEM OF PUNISHMENTS PROVIDED FOR BY THE RULES OF PATIMOKKHA</string>
    <string name="buttonPatimokhaRazdelParajika">PARAJIKA</string>
    <string name="buttonParajika1">1\n If any monk participating in the training and lifestyle of monks, without refusing to study, without openly declaring his weakness, commits sexual intercourse with a woman or with a female animal, such a monk has been defeated and is no longer a member of the sangha.</string>
    <string name="textAboutPatimokha">\n The word "patimokkha" usually refers to a set of rules of conduct for Buddhist monks, established, according to Buddhist tradition, by the Buddha himself. These rules applied to almost all aspects of monastic life, according to these rules, all local Buddhist monastic communities functioned. The etymology of the word "patimokkha" (sancr. "pratimoksha") is not entirely clear. According to Mahavagga 2.3.4., this means the beginning, the head of all qualities. This term is used not only as the name of a set of rules of monastic behavior, but also the name of a sermon in which the Buddha outlined the basic principles common to the teachings of all Buddhas:"not doing all kinds of evil, doing all kinds of good, and purifying one`s own heart: this is the message of all the Buddhas" (Dhammapada, 183) \n \n

In the early years of the Buddha s activity, there was no need to formulate any disciplinary rules. All the monks who followed him – the community of nuns did not exist then – were people of high personal achievements, those who succeeded in destroying all or many mental defilements. They knew the Buddhas teachings well and behaved accordingly. The canon tells how venerable Sariputta, one of the main disciples of the Buddha, asked the Buddha early enough to establish a Patimokkha, or set of rules. This set of rules could ensure the long life of the Buddhas teachings, just as the thread that binds together flower ornaments ensures that the flowers are not scattered by the wind. The Buddha replied that the time for such a code had not yet come, since even the most backward members of the community at that time already had the first experience of approaching the goal. Only when mental defilements (asava) make themselves felt in the community, there will be a need for the rules of Patimokkha. \n \n

As time passed, the conditions that allowed mental pollution to enter the community began to appear. In the Bhaddali Sutta (M. 67), the Buddha lists five such conditions: \n

"Bhaddali: "Why is it, dear sir, there were few rules of conduct before, and the number of monks who were established in the knowledge of Awakening was large? And why now, when there are many rules of conduct, fewer monks are confirmed in the knowledge of Awakening?" (Bhaddali, who did not want to live by disciplinary rules, suggests that an increase in the number of rules is the reason that fewer monks achieve Awakening. The Buddha, however, offers another explanation.)

Buddha: "So it is, Bhaddali. When living beings began to degenerate and the true Dharma began to disappear, many disciplinary rules appeared, and the number of monks who had established themselves in the knowledge of Awakening became small. The teacher (i.e., the Buddha himself) did not establish rules of conduct until conditions arose that contributed to the rise of mental pollution in the community. But when such conditions arose, the Teacher established rules of conduct as a means of countering such conditions. .. These conditions did not arise until the community became large. But when the community became large, conditions were created that contributed to the rise of mental pollution in the community. …When the community began to possess large material resources, ... a high status in society, ... a large body of teaching (texts), ... when the community had existed for a long time, ... then conditions were created that contributed to the rise of mental pollution in the community."

Thus, the rules themselves were not the cause of the degeneration of the community, and the conditions conducive to the rise of mental pollution were not in themselves pollution. Rather, the complication of the life of the community provided an opportunity for the monks to act on the basis of their pollution, and the rules – although they could not prevent any of these conditions – had to be complicated accordingly.

When establishing the rules of conduct, the Buddha justified the need for this with ten reasons: for the perfection of the sangha, for peace in the sangha, for abstinence from shamelessness, for the convenience of bhikkhus of good behavior, for the suppression of defilements related to the past life, for the prevention of defilements related to the future life, for raising faith in non-believers, for the growth of believers, for affirmations of the true dharma and for the education of students .

These causes fall into three types. The first two are external: to ensure peace and correct behavior within the sangha proper and to educate and protect the faith among lay followers of Buddhism. The third type of reasons are internal: to help control and prevent mental contamination within each individual monk. This last division quickly becomes the main one for anyone who seriously tries to follow the rules, as they help to develop mindfulness and concentration when performing any actions – those qualities that are necessary when training consciousness (mind).

The Buddha did not establish the whole set of rules at the same time. On the contrary, he formulated the rules one by one, in response to individual specific events. In the canon, all the cases about which a particular rule was formulated have been preserved, and often knowledge of these "origin stories" can help in understanding the meaning of a particular rule. For example, the history of the origin of the rule prohibiting sexually directed affectionate behavior between monks and women shows that the Buddha did not consider women as something unclean. On the contrary, this rule comes from the case when a monk gently touched the wife of a brahmin who came to visit his home, and the Buddha wanted the women to feel safe when coming to the monastery, knowing that no one would molest them.

Over time, the number of rules grew, and several followers of the Buddha, led by the pious Upali, collected the main rules into a complete set - the Patimokkha Sutta – which contained 227 rules. The Patimokkha sutta, as we know it now, is included in the text called the Vibhanga Sutta. It presents each rule preceding its origin story. It is followed by an explanation of what changes took place in this rule (if any) before it was fixed in its final form. The rule is then analyzed by its constituent elements to show how the factors of effort, object of action, perception, intention and result mitigate or do not mitigate the punishment prescribed by this rule. The discussion ends with a list of circumstances in which this action is not considered a violation, despite the rule.

The minor rules, which numbered several hundred, were collected into chapters distributed on topics called Khandaks. The Khandakas themselves are also divided into two parts: Mahavagga, or the Big Chapter, and Chulavagga, or the Smaller Chapter. Historians estimate that Vibhanga and Khandaki acquired their final form no later than the 2nd century BC. A little later, a Parivara was added to them – a text reviewing and systematizing the previous parts, and thus the canonical Vinaya pitaka was completed.

 The system of punishments applied by the Buddha in his disciplinary rules was based on two principles. Firstly, the goal of Buddhist practice is primarily the development of the mind. Thus, the factors of intention and conscious perception of committed actions often determined whether a particular action was a violation of the rules. For example, the accidental killing of an animal, in terms of the action of the mind, is very different from intentional killing, and is not considered a violation of the rule prohibiting the killing of animals.

There are very few rules where the factors of intention and conscious perception do not play a role at all – such as the rule forbidding monks to drink alcohol – but they almost always deal with situations where an individual is expected to retain attentiveness and perceptual ability sufficiently to understand what he is going to do, and thus these rules also help train the mind.

In any case, the system of analyzing each violation in terms of effort, object, conscious perception, intention and result shows how firm adherence to the rules leads to the development of concentration and understanding. If a monk gets used to being aware of his actions in terms of these factors, he will develop mindfulness, an analytical approach to reality (the present) and perseverance. These are the first three factors of Enlightenment (awakening), forming the basis for the other three: joy, nobility, concentration and equanimity of the spirit.

The second principle used in certain punishments is based on the Buddha`s impressions of communication with Ananda, his main disciple. The Buddha became convinced that friendliness and sociability are extremely necessary in religious life. Anyone who approaches the Dharma seriously should be wise enough to understand that without the possibility of communication and learning from people who have already established themselves on the path, it is almost impossible to make progress on their own path. Thus, monks get used to appreciating their good reputation on the part of respected members of their group, and the whole system of punishments developed by the Buddha is built entirely on the impact on the status of the offender within the community.       \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="textAboutPunish" tools:ignore="TypographyEllipsis">Patimokkha classifies the rules of conduct into eight sections: \n \n

1) parajika – defeat (exclusion from the community); \n

2) sanghadisesa – requiring an initial (adi) and subsequent (sesa) community meeting; \n

3) aniyata – indefinite (i.e. the result depends on the decision of the community); \n

4) nissagia pachittia – requiring reckoning and recognition; \n

5) pachittia – requiring recognition; \n

6) patidesania – requiring recognition a certain form; \n

7) sekhiya – instructions; \n

8) adhikarana samatha – rules for the consideration of controversial issues arising in the community. \n \n

Not all sections of Patimokkha are associated with certain types of punishments. Aniyatas rules give direction for solving uncertain cases. The rules of Sekhia relate primarily to the etiquette of behavior and simply state that one should behave in a certain way. The rules of the Adhikaran samatha are rather not rules, but principles according to which issues arising in the community should be resolved. \n \n

The system of punishments prescribed by the rules consists of four main types, varying from final and unconditional expulsion from the sangha to a simple confession in the presence of another monk. \n \n

A monk who has committed one of the four most serious offenses included in the section of the parajika is automatically considered deprived of the monastic title, even if no one knows about this offense. Therefore, there is no need to conduct any ceremony related to the deprivation of monastic dignity. The very act of committing a misdemeanor is an act of exclusion from the monastic community. A monk is considered to be excluded from the sangha completely and irrevocably, in this life he cannot re-enter the community. The same rules requiring exclusion from the community also applied to nuns. (there were four other rules of this category for nuns). In addition, nuns who returned to secular life as wives of householders were excluded from the community. \n \n

If a monk violates one of the following important rules – the rules of the sanghadises, he is obliged to notify one of the monks and ask the community of at least four monks to impose a six-day period of punishment on him. During the punishment, the monk is deprived of his status and must comply with a number of restrictions, the main of which are the following: \n

"he can`t live under the same roof with fully ordained monks."; \n
– he cannot leave the monastery without being accompanied by fully dedicated monks; \n
– every day he must inform all the monks in the monastery what violation he has committed and what punishment has been imposed on him. If there are visiting monks in the monastery, he is also obliged to inform them. \n \n

After the term of punishment has ended, a monk can ask a community of at least twenty monks to rehabilitate him. After rehabilitation, he returns to his former status as a fully ordained monk of regular behavior. \n \n

If a monk has been hiding for some time that he has violated one of the rules of the sanghadises, he must observe an additional probation period of the same duration as he hid his offense. Only after that he can ask for a six-day punishment and subsequent rehabilitation. \n \n

Violations from the category of sanghadises are classified as severe – both because of their own seriousness, and because of the anxiety that the punishment and subsequent rehabilitation procedure brings to the community. \n \n

The following type of punishment is imposed for violating the rules of nisaggia pachittia, which can be translated as "requiring reckoning and recognition." Each of the rules in this section is related to an item that the monk acquired or used incorrectly. Before publicly admitting his mistake, a monk must give this item "as payback" to his fellow monk or a group of monks. After a public confession, he is released from the offense. In most cases, the payment is symbolic – after his confession, the monk receives the item back, and only in three cases he gives the item away forever. \n \n

A monk can make a confession of committing a violation in front of one or more monks or in front of the entire community. Only the violation of the rules regarding the receipt and use of money, as well as the receipt of an excessive bowl for collecting alms (NP No. 18, 19 and 22) requires mandatory recognition before the whole community. In the same three cases, incorrectly received or used items are not returned to the monk. In other cases, after receiving back his property, he must use it properly. \n \n

Violations of this and the following two types are classified as mild. The guilt for the commission of the last two violations (pacchitia and patidesania) is removed through a simple confession to one monk or the entire community. The difference between these two sections is only that in the last section the form of recognition is fixed in the text of the rules of Patimokkha itself. \n \n

In addition, there are also derivative punishments not specified in the rules of Patimokkha, but specified in the Vibhanga and in the comments. These derivative punishments deal with two kinds of cases: \n \n

– a monk tries to perform an action specified in the rules, but for some reason the action does not reach its final completion (for example, a monk tries to kill someone, but this person does not die); \n \n

– a monk performs an action not directly specified in the rules, but similar to that specified in the rules (for example, he strikes a layman – this case is not specified in the rules, but there is a clause when a monk strikes another monk). \n \n

Such derivative punishments include thullachiya (in more serious cases) and dukkata (in less serious cases). The derivative punishment for incorrect speech also includes dubbhasita. The guilt for committing such derivative violations is removed through a simple confession. \n \n

If these punishments do not correct the behavior of the violator, and he repeatedly violates the rules, the community can impose additional punishments on him. They may vary from the removal of certain privileges of seniority, expulsion from a separate community of monks or expulsion from the community as a whole. In all cases, the punishment is temporary, if the monk understands his mistakes and corrects his way of acting, the community returns him to his former status. The same temporary expulsion from the community occurs if the monk who committed the offense refuses to be punished. \n \n

It should be noted that there is a lot of evidence in the canon that the Buddhas attitude to observing the rules of behavior was not too formal. \n \n

"Once the Enlightened One was in Vesali, in a Great Grove. Then a certain monk came to the Enlightened One … and he said:

– Sir, more than 150 rules of conduct have already been collected in order to repeat them every two weeks. I cant perfect myself according to them.

– Can you improve according to three rules: the rule of increasing virtue, the rule of increasing awareness, the rule of increasing wisdom?

– Yes, I can...

– Then improve yourself according to these three rules. When you improve according to these rules, passion will leave you, hatred will leave you, delusions will leave you. When passion, hatred and delusions leave you, you will not do anything wrong, you will not commit any evil." \n \n \n </string>
    <string name="buttonRiulesPatimokhaParajika2">2 \n If any bhikkhu should take what has not been given from a village or
wilderness, which is reckoned as theft, [and] the taking of what has
not been given is of the kind [that] on account of it kings, having
caught the robber, would physically punish or imprison or banish
[him, saying]: “You are a robber! You are a fool! You are insane! You
are a thief!,” a bhikkhu taking what has not been given of such a kind,
such a monk has been defeated and is no longer a member of the sangha.</string>
    <string name="buttonRiulesPatimokhaParajika3">3 \n If any bhikkhu should deliberately deprive a human being of life, or
should seek an assassin for him, or should praise the attractiveness of
death, or should incite [him] to death [saying]: “Dear man, what [use]
is this bad, wretched life for you? Death is better than life for you!”
should he, [having] such-thought-and-mind, [having such-] thoughtand-
intention, praise in manifold ways the beauty of death or incite
[him] to death, such a monk has been defeated and is no longer a member of the sangha.</string>
    <string name="buttonRiulesPatimokhaParajika4">4 \n If any bhikkhu, [though] not directly knowing [it], should claim a
superhuman state pertaining to himself, [a state of] knowing and
seeing [that is] suitable for the noble [ones], [saying]: “Thus I know!
Thus I see!,” [and] then, on another occasion, [whether] being
interrogated or not being interrogated, having committed [the
offence], desiring purification, should say so: “Friends, [although] not
knowing [it,] I spoke thus [saying]: ‘I know,’ not seeing [it, I spoke,
saying:] ‘I see.’ I bluffed vainly [and] falsely,” except [when said] in
overestimation, such a monk has been defeated and is no longer a member of the sangha.</string>
    <string name="textViewHintParajika">Click on the rule to see the rule in the Pali language and the reasons for the rule.</string>
    <string name="button_sutta_girimananda">girimananda sutta</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaGirimananda">
        \n  <b>GIRIMANANDA SUTTA</b> \n \n
        <i>FOR GIRIMANANDA</i> \n \n
        <b>Ekaṃ samayaṃ bhagavā sāvatthiyaṃ viharati jetavane anāthapiṇḍikassa ārāme. Tena kho pana samayena āyasmā girimānando ābādhiko hoti dukkhito bāḷhagilāno. Atha kho āyasmā ānando yena bhagavā tenupasaṅkami; upasaṅkamitvā bhagavantaṃ abhivādetvā ekamantaṃ nisīdi. Ekamantaṃ nisinno kho āyasmā ānando bhagavantaṃ etadavoca:</b> \n \n
        <i>On one occasion the Blessed One was staying near Savatthi, in Jetas Grove, Anathapindikas monastery. And on that occasion Ven. Girimananda was diseased, in pain, severely ill. Then Ven. Ananda went to the Blessed One and, on arrival, having bowed down to him, sat to one side. As he was sitting there he said to the Blessed One:</i> \n \n
        <b>– Āyasmā, bhante, girimānando ābādhiko hoti dukkhito bāḷhagilāno. Sādhu, bhante, bhagavā yenāyasmā girimānando tenupasaṅkamatu anukampaṃ upādāyā ti.</b> \n \n
        <i>– Lord, Ven. Girimananda is diseased, in pain, severely ill. It would be good if the Blessed One would visit Ven. Girimananda, out of sympathy for him.</i> \n \n
        <b>Sace kho tvaṃ, ānanda, girimānandassa bhikkhuno dasa saññā bhāseyyāsi, ṭhānaṃ kho panetaṃ vijjati yaṃ girimānandassa bhikkhuno dasa saññā sutvā so ābādho ṭhānaso paṭippassambheyya. Katamā dasa? Aniccasaññā, anattasaññā, asubhasaññā, ādīnavasaññā, pahāna·saññā, virāgasaññā, nirodhasaññā, sabbaloke anabhiratasaññā, sabbasaṅkhāresu anicchāsaññā, ānāpānassati.</b> \n \n
        <i>Ananda, if you go to the monk Girimananda and tell him ten perceptions, its possible that when he hears the ten perceptions his disease may be allayed. Which ten? The perception of inconstancy, the perception of not-self, the perception of unattractiveness, the perception of drawbacks, the perception of abandoning, the perception of dispassion, the perception of cessation, the perception of distaste for every world, the perception of the undesirability of all fabrications, mindfulness of in  out breathing.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, aniccasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu araññagato vā rukkhamūlagato vā suññāgāragato vā iti paṭisañcikkhati: rūpaṃ aniccaṃ, vedanā aniccā, saññā aniccā, saṅkhārā aniccā, viññāṇaṃ aniccanti. Iti imesu pañcasu upādānakkhandhesu aniccānupassī viharati. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, aniccasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of inconstancy? There is the case where a monk — having gone to the wilderness, to the shade of a tree, or to an empty building — reflects thus: Form is inconstant, feeling is inconstant, perception is inconstant, fabrications are inconstant, consciousness is inconstant. Thus he remains focused on inconstancy with regard to the five clinging-aggregates. This, Ananda, is called the perception of inconstancy.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, anattasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu araññagato vā rukkhamūlagato vā suññāgāragato vā iti paṭisañcikkhati: cakkhu anattā, rūpā anattā, sotaṃ anattā, saddā anattā, ghānaṃ anattā, gandhā anattā, jivhā anattā, rasā anattā, kāyā anattā, phoṭṭhabbā anattā, mano anattā, dhammā anattāti. Iti imesu chasu ajjhattikabāhiresu āyatanesu anattānupassī viharati. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, anattasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of not-self? There is the case where a monk — having gone to the wilderness, to the shade of a tree, or to an empty building — reflects thus: The eye is not-self, forms are not-self; the ear is not-self, sounds are not-self; the nose is not-self, aromas are not-self; the tongue is not-self, flavors are not-self; the body is not-self, tactile sensations are not-self; the intellect is not-self, ideas are not-self. Thus he remains focused on not-selfness with regard to the six inner and outer sense media. This is called the perception of not-self.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, asubhasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu imameva kāyaṃ uddhaṃ pādatalā adho kesamatthakā tacapariyantaṃ pūraṃ nānāppakārassa asucino paccavekkhati: atthi imasmiṃ kāye kesā lomā nakhā dantā taco maṃsaṃ nhāru aṭṭhi aṭṭhimiñjaṃ vakkaṃ hadayaṃ yakanaṃ kilomakaṃ pihakaṃ papphāsaṃ antaṃ antaguṇaṃ udariyaṃ karīsaṃ pittaṃ semhaṃ pubbo lohitaṃ sedo medo assu vasā kheḷo siṅghāṇikā lasikā muttanti. Iti imasmiṃ kāye asubhānupassī viharati. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, asubhasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of unattractiveness? There is the case where a monk ponders this very body — from the soles of the feet on up, from the crown of the head on down, surrounded by skin, filled with all sorts of unclean things: There is in this body: hair of the head, hair of the body, nails, teeth, skin, muscle, tendons, bones, bone marrow, spleen, heart, liver, membranes, kidneys, lungs, large intestines, small intestines, gorge, feces, gall, phlegm, lymph, blood, sweat, fat, tears, oil, saliva, mucus, oil in the joints, urine. Thus he remains focused on unattractiveness with regard to this very body. This is called the perception of unattractiveness.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, ādīnavasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu araññagato vā rukkhamūlagato vā suññāgāragato vā iti paṭisañcikkhati: bahudukkho kho ayaṃ kāyo bahuādīnavo? Iti imasmiṃ kāye vividhā ābādhā uppajjanti, seyyathidaṃ: cakkhurogo sotarogo ghānarogo jivhārogo kāyarogo sīsarogo kaṇṇarogo mukharogo dantarogo oṭṭharogo kāso sāso pināso ḍāho jaro kucchirogo mucchā pakkhandikā sūlā visūcikā kuṭṭhaṃ gaṇḍo kilāso soso apamāro daddu kaṇḍu kacchu nakhasā vitacchikā lohitaṃ pittaṃ madhumeho aṃsā piḷakā bhagandalā pittasamuṭṭhānā ābādhā semhasamuṭṭhānā ābādhā vātasamuṭṭhānā ābādhā sannipātikā ābādhā utupariṇāmajā ābādhā visamaparihārajā ābādhā opakkamikā ābādhā kammavipākajā ābādhā sītaṃ uṇhaṃ jighacchā pipāsā uccāro passāvoti. Iti imasmiṃ kāye ādīnavānupassī viharati. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, ādīnavasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of drawbacks? There is the case where a monk — having gone to the wilderness, to the foot of a tree, or to an empty dwelling — reflects thus: This body has many pains, many drawbacks. In this body many kinds of disease arise, such as: seeing-diseases, hearing-diseases, nose-diseases, tongue-diseases, body-diseases, head-diseases, ear-diseases, mouth-diseases, teeth-diseases, cough, asthma, catarrh, fever, aging, stomach-ache, fainting, dysentery, grippe, cholera, leprosy, boils, ringworm, tuberculosis, epilepsy, skin-disease, itch, scab, psoriasis, scabies, jaundice, diabetes, hemorrhoids, fistulas, ulcers; diseases arising from bile, from phlegm, from the wind-property, from combinations of bodily humors, from changes in the weather, from uneven care of the body, from attacks, from the result of kamma; cold, heat, hunger, thirst, defecation, urination. Thus he remains focused on drawbacks with regard to this body. This is called the perception of drawbacks.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, pahānasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu uppannaṃ kāmavitakkaṃ nādhivāseti, pajahati, vinodeti, byantīkaroti, anabhāvaṃ gameti. Uppannaṃ byāpāda·vitakkaṃ nādhivāseti, pajahati, vinodeti, byantīkaroti, anabhāvaṃ gameti. Uppannaṃ vihiṃsāvitakkaṃ nādhivāseti, pajahati, vinodeti, byantīkaroti, anabhāvaṃ gameti. Uppannuppanne pāpake akusale dhamme nādhivāseti, pajahati, vinodeti, byantīkaroti, anabhāvaṃ gameti. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, pahānasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of abandoning? There is the case where a monk does not tolerate an arisen thought of sensuality. He abandons it, destroys it, dispels it, and wipes it out of existence. He does not tolerate an arisen thought of ill-will. He abandons it, destroys it, dispels it, and wipes it out of existence. He does not tolerate an arisen thought of harmfulness. He abandons it, destroys it, dispels it, and wipes it out of existence. He does not tolerate arisen evil, unskillful mental qualities. He abandons them, destroys them, dispels them, and wipes them out of existence. This is called the perception of abandoning.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, virāgasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu araññagato vā rukkhamūlagato vā suññāgāragato vā iti paṭisañcikkhati: etaṃ santaṃ etaṃ paṇītaṃ yadidaṃ sabbasaṅkhārasamatho sabbūpadhippaṭinissaggo taṇhākkhayo virāgo nibbānanti. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, virāgasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of dispassion? There is the case where a monk — having gone to the wilderness, to the shade of a tree, or to an empty building — reflects thus: This is peace, this is exquisite — the stilling of all fabrications, the relinquishment of all acquisitions, the ending of craving, dispassion, Unbinding. This is called the perception of dispassion.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, nirodhasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu araññagato vā rukkhamūlagato vā suññāgāragato vā iti paṭisañcikkhati: etaṃ santaṃ etaṃ paṇītaṃ yadidaṃ sabbasaṅkhārasamatho sabbūpadhippaṭinissaggo taṇhākkhayo nirodho nibbānanti. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, nirodhasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of cessation? There is the case where a monk — having gone to the wilderness, to the shade of a tree, or to an empty building — reflects thus: This is peace, this is exquisite — the stilling of all fabrications, the relinquishment of all acquisitions, the ending of craving, cessation, Unbinding. This is called the perception of cessation.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, sabbaloke anabhiratasaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu ye loke upādānā cetaso adhiṭṭhānābhinivesānusayā, te pajahanto viharati anupādiyanto. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, sabbaloke anabhiratasaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of distaste for every world? There is the case where a monk abandoning any attachments, clingings, fixations of awareness, biases, or obsessions with regard to any world, refrains from them and does not get involved. This is called the perception of distaste for every world.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, sabbasaṅkhāresu anicchāsaññā? Idhānanda, bhikkhu sabbasaṅkhāresu aṭṭīyati harāyati jigucchati. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, sabbasaṅkhāresu anicchāsaññā.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is the perception of the undesirability of all fabrications? There is the case where a monk feels horrified, humiliated, and disgusted with all fabrications. This is called the perception of the undesirability of all fabrications.</i> \n \n
        <b>Katamā cānanda, ānāpānassati? Idānanda, bhikkhu araññagato vā rukkhamūlagato vā suññāgāragato vā nisīdati pallaṅkaṃ ābhujitvā ujuṃ kāyaṃ paṇidhāya parimukhaṃ satiṃ upaṭṭhapetvā. So satova assasati satova passasati.</b> \n \n
        <i>And what is mindfulness of in and out breathing? There is the case where a monk — having gone to the wilderness, to the shade of a tree, or to an empty building — sits down folding his legs crosswise, holding his body erect, and setting mindfulness to the fore. Always mindful, he breathes in; mindful he breathes out.</i> \n \n
        <b>Dīghaṃ vā assasanto dīghaṃ assasāmīti pajānāti. Dīghaṃ vā passasanto dīghaṃ passasāmīti pajānāti. Rassaṃ vā assasanto rassaṃ assasāmīti pajānāti. Rassaṃ vā passasanto rassaṃ passasāmīti pajānāti. Sabbakāyapaṭisaṃvedī assasissāmīti sikkhati. Sabbakāyapaṭisaṃvedī passasissāmīti sikkhati. Passambhayaṃ kāyasaṅkhāraṃ assasissāmīti sikkhati. Passambhayaṃ kāyasaṅkhāraṃ passasissāmīti sikkhati. Passambhayaṃ kāyasaṅkhāraṃ passasissāmīti sikkhati.</b> \n \n
        <i>[i] Breathing in long, he discerns, I am breathing in long; or breathing out long, he discerns, I am breathing out long. [ii] Or breathing in short, he discerns, I am breathing in short; or breathing out short, he discerns, I am breathing out short. [iii] He trains himself, I will breathe in sensitive to the entire body. He trains himself, I will breathe out sensitive to the entire body. [iv] He trains himself, I will breathe in calming bodily fabrication. He trains himself, I will breathe out calming bodily fabrication.</i> \n \n
        <b>Pītipaṭisaṃvedī assasissāmīti sikkhati. Pītipaṭisaṃvedī passasissāmīti sikkhati. Sukhapaṭisaṃvedī assasissāmīti sikkhati. Sukhapaṭisaṃvedī passasissāmīti sikkhati. Cittasaṅkhārapaṭisaṃvedī assasissāmīti sikkhati. Cittasaṅkhārapaṭisaṃvedī passasissāmīti sikkhati. Passambhayaṃ cittasaṅkhāraṃ assasissāmīti sikkhati. Passambhayaṃ cittasaṅkhāraṃ passasissāmīti sikkhati.</b> \n \n
        <i>[v] He trains himself to breathe in sensitive to rapture, and to breathe out sensitive to rapture. [vi] He trains himself to breathe in sensitive to pleasure, and to breathe out sensitive to pleasure. [vii] He trains himself to breathe in sensitive to mental processes, and to breathe out sensitive to mental processes. [viii] He trains himself to breathe in calming mental processes, and to breathe out calming mental processes.</i> \n \n
        <b>Cittapaṭisaṃvedī assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Cittapaṭisaṃvedī passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Abhippamodayaṃ cittaṃ assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Abhippamodayaṃ cittaṃ passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Samādahaṃ cittaṃ assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Samādahaṃ cittaṃ passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Vimocayaṃ cittaṃ assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Vimocayaṃ cittaṃ passasissāmī ti sikkhati.</b> \n \n
        <i>[ix] He trains himself to breathe in sensitive to the mind, and to breathe out sensitive to the mind. [x] He trains himself to breathe in satisfying the mind, and to breathe out satisfying the mind. [xi] He trains himself to breathe in steadying the mind, and to breathe out steadying the mind. [xii] He trains himself to breathe in releasing the mind, and to breathe out releasing the mind.</i> \n \n
        <b>Aniccānupassī assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Aniccānupassī passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Virāgānupassī assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Virāgānupassī passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Nirodhānupassī assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Nirodhānupassī passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Paṭinissaggānupassī assasissāmī ti sikkhati. Paṭinissaggānupassī passasissāmī ti sikkhati. Ayaṃ vuccatānanda, ānāpānassati.</b> \n \n
        <i>[xiii] He trains himself to breathe in focusing on inconstancy, and to breathe out focusing on inconstancy. [xiv] He trains himself to breathe in focusing on dispassion,[1] and to breathe out focusing on dispassion. [xv] He trains himself to breathe in focusing on cessation, and to breathe out focusing on cessation. [xvi] He trains himself to breathe in focusing on relinquishment, and to breathe out focusing on relinquishment. This, Ananda, is called mindfulness of in andout breathing.</i> \n \n
        <b>Sace kho tvaṃ, ānanda, girimānandassa bhikkhuno imā dasa saññā bhāseyyāsi, ṭhānaṃ kho panetaṃ vijjati yaṃ girimānandassa bhikkhuno imā dasa saññā sutvā so ābādho ṭhānaso paṭippassambheyyā ti.</b> \n \n
        <i>Now, Ananda, if you go to the monk Girimananda and tell him these ten perceptions, its possible that when he hears these ten perceptions his disease may be allayed.</i> \n \n
        <b>Atha kho āyasmā ānando bhagavato santike imā dasa saññā uggahetvā yenāyasmā girimānando tenupasaṅkami; upasaṅkamitvā āyasmato girimānandassa imā dasa saññā abhāsi. Atha kho āyasmato girimānandassa dasa saññā sutvā so ābādho ṭhānaso paṭippassambhi. Vuṭṭhahi cāyasmā girimānando tamhā ābādhā. Tathā pahīno ca panāyasmato girimānandassa so ābādho ahosī ti.</b> \n \n
        <i>Then Ven. Ananda, having learned these ten perceptions in the Blessed Ones presence, went to Ven. Girimananda and told them to him. As Ven. Girimananda heard these ten perceptions, his disease was allayed. And Ven. Girimananda recovered from his disease. That was how Ven. Girimanandas disease was abandoned.</i> \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textPatimokhaParajika1"> \n
        Pàr 1: (Methunadhammasikkhàpadam): \n
        <i>       The rule about sexual intercourse.</i> \n \n

        <b>Yo pana bhikkhu bhikkhūnaṃ sikkhāsājīvasamāpanno</b> \n
        <i>If any monk who has taken monastic vows leads a holy life</i> \n \n

        <b>sikkhaṃ appaccakkhāya dubbalyaṃ anāvikatvā methunaṃ dhammaṃ paṭiseveyya,</b> \n
        <i>The rules are not to leave, without declaring weakness, to commit a sexual act</i> \n \n

        <b>antamaso tiracchānagatāya pi; pārājiko hoti, asaṃvāso.</b> \n
        <i>even with a female animal, the affected one is not a member of the sangha</i> \n \n

        \n \n This rule arose as a result of three different events: \n \n
         The first event is related to the story of the young Sudinna Kalandaki.
         Who had sexual intercourse with his ex-wife. \n \n
         The second event is related to the story of a monk who had sexual intercourse with a female monkey. \n \n
         The third rule is associated with the Waji monks, who performed sexual acts without renouncing monasticism and without admitting their offense. \n \n \n

         <b>Note:</b> \n \n

         This rule arose 20 years after the launch of the Wheel of Dhamma \n \n

<b>There are six cases when parajika 1 is not performed:</b> \n \n
1. Ajānantassa - A monk does not commit any crime if he is raped during deep sleep or in an unconscious state, since he is not aware of the sexual act. Moreover, the same applies when his penis is inserted into any of the 30 nimittas until he is aware of the act. \n \n
2. Asādiyantassa - When a monk does not agree. \n \n
3. Ummattakassa - When the monk has fallen into unconsciousness or is in a state of madness. \n \n
4. Khittacittassa - When a monk, being possessed by another spirit, can no longer control himself. \n \n
5. Vedanaṭṭa - A monk who suffers from severe pain and feels nothing but pain is also not guilty of committing sexual intercourse. \n \n
6. Ādikammikassa - The first criminal was acquitted of his misdeeds, since at that time there was no such training rule, called the first parajika. Therefore, the venerable Sudinna did not become a paredzic for his immoral act. But the monk who copulated with a female monkey and caused the first amendment to the rule was guilty of committing pārājikā. \n \n

         <b>Factors</b> \n \n
The following factors are necessary to find a monk guilty of committing the first parajika. \n \n
     1. Sevanacittaṃ – intention (mind with intention) to perform sexual intercourse. \n
     2. Maggena maggaṃ pavesanaṃ - insertion of the penis into one of the 30 organs (nimitta) \n \n
         It should also be noted that a monk loses monasticism if he receives pleasure from intercourse
         during rape or when his penis is forcibly inserted into one of the organs
         without his consent. This factor is known as sādiyanaṃ. \n \n

                    <b>Citta and saññā </b> \n \n
         The first parajika is the crime of sacittaka.
         This means that a monk commits a crime for an intentional act,
         in this case, for sex. All sacittaka crimes are also called saññāvimokkha crimes.
         Therefore, the first parājika is the sassāvimokkha crime. \n \n

                    <b>anāṇattika and sānaṇattika nature</b> \n \n
Not related to an order and related to an order\n
The first parajika anāṇattika violation. This means that if anyone forces you to have sex in any way,
         it does not lead to parajika. However, this is a misdemeanor (duccata)
         because it is contrary to the Vinaya and is called akappiya-samādāna (improper behavior). \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textPatimokhaParajika2"> \n
        \n
        Pàr 2: (Adinnàdànasikkhàpadam): \n
        Правило о воровстве. \n
        <i>       The rule about theft.</i> \n \n
        <b>Yo pana bhikkhu gāmā vā araññā vā \n </b>

        <i>if any monk from a city or village</i> \n \n
        <b>adinnaṃ theyyasaṅkhātaṃ ādiyeyya, yathārūpe adinnādāne \n </b>

        <i>takes what he has not stolen in a thievish way,</i> \n \n
        <b>yathārūpe adinnādāne rājāno coraṃ gahetvā haneyyuṃ vā bandheyyuṃ vā pabbājeyyuṃ vā: \n </b>

        <i>such that the kings of the thief are seized, put in chains, banished saying</i> \n \n
        <b>Coro’si, bālo’si, mūlho’si, theno’sī ti, \n </b>

        <i>“you are a thief, you fool, you fool, you thief”,</i> \n \n
        <b>tathārūpaṃ bhikkhu adinnaṃ ādiyamāno; ayam-pi pārājiko hoti, asaṃvāso. </b>

        <i>such a monk is considered stricken and no longer in the sangha.</i> \n \n

        \n \n This rule arose as a result of two different events: \n \n
The first event is related to the story of Dhaniya, the son of a potter. \n
Who took possession of building materials for his hut by deception. \n \n
The second event involves the monks from the group of six. \n
They stole valuables from dyers in the wilderness. \n \n

         <b>Factors:</b> \n \n
5 factors are required to perform the second parajika. \n
        1. A certain object or living creature (animal, slave) belonging to (another) person. \n
        2. The feeling (knowing) that this object or being does not belong to you\n
        3. The cost of a creature or object is at least 1 “pad”\n
        4. Selfish mind, desire, intention to steal, take possession. \n
        5. Theft in one of 25 ways. \n \n
         <b>Description:</b> \n \n
Although for monks sexual behavior is a violation of pārājikā,
         for the laity it is not so unacceptable. If lay people lead a correct sex life,
         they will not be punished in any way. While the monk will be expelled from the sangha.
         Theft, in turn, is an inappropriate act for both laymen and monks.
         Being an honest person who abstains from stealing is a valuable element in the moral life of a bhikkhu.
         The word `thief` is considered obscene. It is extremely unsuitable for a monk.
         Therefore, a monk must be a pure person who will not take even a piece of grass that is not given to him,
         out of self-interest. This must be a person you can trust. While, taking even the grass weed from
         self-interest, a person becomes a thief. Of course, the Buddha did not consider such insignificant matters as
         objects of parajika, establishing the rule of the second parajika, he designated “pada” as the lower boundary,
         which is the lowest measure used by righteous rulers such as King Bimbisara,
         to punish thieves. This rule of adinnadana parrajika training is one of those which is very difficult to judge.
         It is also difficult to judge the measure of pada that is covered by the teaching rule adinnādāna pārājikā.
         It is also difficult to determine the value of some objects. Since there is
         twenty-five ways of committing theft, a bhikkhu who is not very well versed in the Vinaya,
         may unknowingly commit a parajika crime. Therefore bhikkhus should instill good
         crime knowledge base adinnadan pararajika. \n \n
         <b>25 types of theft</b> \n
         The disciplinary code specifies twenty-five ways of performing adinnādāna. If an item worth pādā is taken in any of the twenty-five ways, it will result in defeat. Knowledge of this rule will be complete only if these twenty-five methods, called avahāra, are known. Those who do not know them may fail unknowingly. \n \n
avahāra are divided into five groups \n \n
     1. Nānābhaṇḍa pañcakā\n
     2. Ekabhaṇḍa pañcakā\n
     3. Sāhatthika pañcakā \n
     4. Pubbapayoga pañcakā\n
     5. Theyyāvahāra pañcakā \n \n
<b>Nānābaṇḍa pañcaka</b> \n
As the name suggests, Nānābhaṇḍa pañcakā is fivefold. \n
     1. Ādiyeyya – acquisition of someone else’s property through legal proceedings\n
     2. Hareyya - taking someone else`s thing with the intention of stealing, during delivery. \n
     3. Avahareyya - acquisition through non-return of a thing taken for storage. \n
     4. Iriyāpathaṃ vikopeyya - taking by changing the location of an object (so that the owner of the object thinks that it is not his.). \n
     5. Ṭhānācāveyya – taking a thing from its place. \n \n

<b>Ekabaṇḍa pañcaka</b> \n
(Nānābhaṇḍa pañcaka shows the acquisition of an object consciously or unconsciously through litigation and so on.) \n \n
         The Ekabaṇḍa pañcaka shows the acquisition of animals or slaves belonging to others through such means as
         like a lawsuit. Making false claims for the purpose of acquiring a slave, elephant, horse,
         cattle or any other animal owned by another will result in
         committing the offense dukkaṭa. Raising doubts in the owner will result in the offense of tulakkai.
         Defeat will come when the owner loses hope. The remaining four methods of theft follow
         be considered as given in nānābaṇḍa pañcaka. \n \n

<b>Sāhatthika pañcaka</b> \n
     1. Sāhattikāvahāra – theft with one’s own hand\n
     2. Āṇattikāvahāra – theft by impulse, order (for both) \n
     3. Nissaggiyāvahāra – theft by throwing away \n
     4. Atthasādhakāvahāra – stealing at the first opportunity\n
     5. Dhuranikkhepāvahāra – loss of hope (by the owner). \n \n

        <b>Pubbayoga pañcaka</b> \n
     1. Pubbayogāvahāra – theft by order\n
     2. Sahapayogāvahāra – land grab\n
     3. Saṃvidāvahāra – group theft\n
     4. Saṃketakammāvahāra – theft at a certain time\n
     5. Nimittakammāvahāra – theft by sign \n \n


         <b>Theyyāvahāra pañcaka</b>\n
     1. Theyyāvahāra – theft, scam, fake\n
     2. Pasayhāvahāra - robbery \n
     3. Parikappāvahāra - if this happens, I will take it or take what I can carry\n
     4. Paṭicchannāvahāra – hiding an object\n
     5. Kusāvahāra - fraud \n \n

         <b>Cases of violation</b> \n
<b>According to the value of the item</b> \n
1. If an item worth five māsaka, which is equal to one pada or more, is stolen, then the bhikkhu has committed a crime involving the couple. ($50 or more)\n\n
2. If an item worth 1 māsaka or more but less than five māsaka is stolen, the bhikkhu commits the crime of thullaccaya. (from 10 dollars) \n \n
3. If an item worth less than one masaka is stolen, the bhikkhu commits the crime of dukkata.(less than $10) \n \n

         <b>Cases not violation</b> \n
     1. Sakasaññissa - A Bhikkhu who takes something belonging to another, thinking it is his, does not commit a crime on the basis of taking. What is taken must be given back (bhaṇḍadeyya). If not given, the bhikkhu will perform pārājikā if the value of the item is equal to pāda or more \n \n
     2. Vissāsaggāhe (confidential) - if taken from the owner out of trust, no crime will be committed. \n
The Buddha spoke of five qualities that must be present in a person if he wants to take an object from the owner out of trust. \n
- Sandiṭṭho is a person with whom friendship was established at first sight. \n
- Sambhatto – with whom a strong friendship (brotherly relationship) was established \n
- Ālapito - a person who said: “If one of my things is pleasant, take it” - showing that asking permission is not necessary. \n
- Jīvati – he must be alive. Even with his last breath a person is considered alive. \n
- Gahite ca attamano - he rejoices at the taking. \n
Despite what was previously said about 5 qualities, three are enough to trust:\n
I Sandiṭṭho, Jīvati, Gahite ca attamano \n
II Sambhatto, Jīvati, Gahite ca attamano \n
III Ālapito, Jīvati, Gahite ca attamano \n
Even if something is taken from a living person, and the owner is not happy that he was taken; out of a sense of confidence, it needs to be returned back. If a domestic or ascetic person owns the wealth of a deceased person, then it should be returned to him. The wealth belonging to those with unhappy minds should be returned directly to them. A person who first says or thinks, “You did well to take what belongs to me,” and then for some reason becomes angry, cannot ask for it back. Even if he asks, the one who took the thing is not obliged to return it. The owner is not happy that his things were taken, but remains silent while they are taken. In this situation, the owner cannot demand it back. When someone says, `I took your things or used up your things,` if the owner states, `I kept them for this and that purpose. Therefore, it is better to return or replace them,` then the one who took the thing must replace it. \n \n
     3. Tāvakālikasaññissa – borrowing for a while with the thought “I will return it back” will not be considered a violation. \n \n
     4. Petapariggahe - Buddha said that taking from non-human beings will not lead to parajika \n \n
     5. Tiracchānagatapariggahe - Buddha said that taking creatures from animals will not lead to parajika \n \n
     6. Paṃsukūlasaññissa – if you take things with the thought: “This thing is Paṃsukūla, no one’s” this is not a violation. \n \n
     7. Ummattakassa\n\n
     8. Khittacittassa \n \n
     9.Vedanaṭṭassa\n\n
     10. Ādikammikassa \n \n \n \n
    </string>

    <string name="button_paritta">\n <b>paritta</b> \n</string>
    <string name="button_mora_paritta">mora paritta</string>
    <string name="button_girimananda">\n<b>Girimananda Sutta</b>\n</string>
    <string name="button_dhammapada">\n<b>dhammapada</b>\n</string>
    <string name="button_khanda">\n<b>Khanda Paritta</b>\n</string>


    <string name="textDiscribeGirimananda">
    This sutta is a teaching that the Buddha gave to the venerable Girimananda
    when he became seriously ill. From the earliest times, it came to be revered
    as a protective sermon — paritta — and was included in an ancient anthology of such sermons
    known as the Catubhāṇavāra.\n\n

    The Girimananda Sutta is both a protective sutta and a profound teaching.
    The best protection for a person is to understand this sutta and practice in accordance with it.
    If such a practitioner falls ill, by listening to or reading this sutta, he
    will recall his practice. This will awaken and strengthen his
    bojjhaṅga — the factors of enlightenment — and the illness may weaken or even recede completely.\n\n

    This sutta brings three kinds of well-being:\n\n

    The first well-being is when a person understands it and practices in accordance with its meaning.\n\n
    The second well-being is when, during an illness, reading this sutta helps in the healing of that person.\n\n
    The third well-being is born from listening with saddhā — faith, trust, openness to the Teaching.
    From listening to the paritta with saddhā, a person can find relief from illness and even recover.
</string>
    <string name="textDiscribeKhanda">
    The Paritta combines admonition and verses of goodwill:
    four kinds of "snake kings" are listed (Virūpakkha, Erāpatha, Chabyāputta, Kaṇhāgotamaka)
    and an intention of goodwill is established towards all kinds of beings —
    footless, two-footed, four-footed, and many-footed —
    with the wish that no one should cause harm. \n\n

    In the tradition, it is believed that sincere mettā pacifies hostile forces and prevents misfortunes;
    in practice, however, the main protection is the stable development of mettā and mindfulness (sati)
    in daily life.
</string>



    <string name="textViewParnieStrofy">PAIRED STANZAS</string>
    <string name="button1Dhammapada">1 \n Led by the mind of the dhamma, the mind governs them, the mind generates them. If a person with malice speaks or acts, Dukkha follows him, like a wheel following the trail of a driver.</string>
    <string name="button2Dhammapada">2 \n Guided by the mind of the dhamma, the mind controls them, the mind generates them. If a person with a purified mind speaks or acts, Happiness follows him like a persistent shadow.</string>
    <string name="textViev1Dhammapada">
       \n CHAKKUPALATTHERA VATTHU
        <b>\n \n Manopubbaṅgamā dhammā \n \n</b>
        <i>Led by the mind of the dhamma, \n \n</i>
        <b>Manoseṭṭhā manomayā \n \n</b>
        <i>the mind governs them, the mind generates them. \n \n</i>
        <b>Manasā ce paduṭṭhena \n \n</b>
        <i>If a person with malice \n \n</i>
        <b>Bhāsati vā karoti vā \n \n</b>
        <i>speaks or acts, \n \n</i>
        <b>Tato naṃ dukkham anveti \n \n</b>
        <i>Dukkha follows him, \n \n</i>
        <b>Cakkaṃ va vahato padaṃ \n \n</b>
        <i>like a wheel following the trail of a driver. \n \n \n</i>
        Related story: The Elder Cakkhupāla \n \n

Once there was a monk called Cakkhupāla who was determined not to lie down for the entire Rains Retreat. He developed an eye infection for which he need to lie down to take the medicine. But he refused to lie down, so the disease got worse and he became blind although he attained Arahantship, from his training. \n \n

As he was pacing up and down, he unintentionally killed many insects. The visiting monks noticed the quite a number of  insects were killed on the elder’s walking meditation path and told they told Buddha. about it.  The Buddha explained that the monk had killed them unintentionally and that he was an Arahant. (Intentional volition constitutes kamma whereas unintentional/involuntary/unconscious volition does not constitute kamma) \n \n

The monks then asked Buddha why he became blind? Buddha narrated how in a previous life as a doctor, Cakkhupala treated a poor woman’s eyes. She promised to become his servant if her eyesight came back but did not kept her promise when she regained her eyesight. So the doctor retaliated by giving her another medicine, which blinded her. Due to that evil action Cakkhupāla became blind. \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="textViev2Dhammapada">
        \n MATTHAKUNDALI VATTHU \n \n
        <b>\n \n Manopubbaṅgamā dhammā \n \n</b>
        <i>Guided by the mind of the dhamma,, \n \n</i>
        <b>Manoseṭṭhā manomayā \n \n</b>
        <i>the mind controls them, the mind generates them.\n \n</i>
        <b>Manasā ce pasannena \n \n</b>
        <i>If a person with a purified mind  \n \n</i>
        <b>Bhāsati vā karoti vā \n \n</b>
        <i>speaks or acts, \n \n</i>
        <b>Tato naṃ sukhamanveti \n \n</b>
        <i>Happiness follows him, \n \n</i>
        <b>Chhāyāva anapāyinī \n \n</b>
        <i>like a persistent shadow. \n \n \n</i>
        The parable of Matthakundali \n\n During his stay at the Jetavana monastery in Savatti, the Buddha recited this verse in connection with the story of the young brahmin Matthakundali. \n\n Matthakundali was a young brahmin. His father Adinnapubbaka was very greedy and never gave alms. He even made gold jewelry for his son himself to save money for work. When his son got sick, he didn`t call a doctor until it was too late. When he realized that his son was dying, he took him out onto the veranda so that people who came to him would not see what he had in the house. That morning, the Buddha, coming out early from a deep meditation of compassion, saw in the Web of his Knowledge that Matthakundali was lying on the veranda. Therefore, when the Buddha came to Savatti for alms, he stopped at the house of the brahmin Adinnapubbaki. The Buddha directed a beam of light forward to attract the attention of a young man who was lying facing the house. The young man saw the Buddha, but since he was too weak, he could only mentally express his faith. But that was enough. When he died, filled with faith in the Buddha, he was reborn in the heavenly world of Tavatims. \n\n From his heavenly home, the young Matthakundali, seeing his father grieving for him in the cemetery, appeared to him in his former form. He told his father that he had been reborn in the world of Tavatims and persuaded him to invite the Buddha for alms. \n\n In the house of Adannapubbaki, the question was raised about whether it is possible to be reborn in the heavenly world by simply being devoted to the Buddha in thought, but not making alms and not observing moral principles. Then the Buddha made Matthakundali himself appear there; he appeared in heavenly attire and told about his rebirth in the world of Tavatims. Only then did the listeners become convinced that the son of the brahmin Adinnapubbaki received such honors simply by believing in the Buddha. \n\n Then the Buddha recited this verse, Matthakundali and his father Adinnapubbaka reached Sotapatti Maga and Sotapatti Phala. Adinnapubbaka also donated almost all of his wealth to the cause of the Buddha`s Teachings. \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="buttonDigha">Digha Nikaya</string>
    <string name="buttonSuttasForMajhima">majjhima nikaya</string>
    <string name="textPatimokhaParajika3">
        Pàr 3: (Manussaviggahasikkhàpadam):\n
         The rule about the intentional killing of a person. \n
         <i>The rule about the intentional killing of a person.</i> \n \n \n

         <b>Yo pana bhikkhu sañcicca manussaviggahaṃ jīvitā voropeyya, </b> \n
         If any bhikkhu deliberately takes the life of a person,\n
         <i>If any bhikkhu deliberately takes the life of a person,</i> \n \n

         <b>satthahārakaṃ vāssa pariyeseyya, maraṇavaṇṇaṃ vā saṃvaṇṇeyya, maraṇāya vā samādapeyya:</b> \n
         hires a killer, or praises the attractiveness of death, incites death, [saying]:\n
         <i>hires a killer, or praises the attractiveness of death, incites death, [saying]:</i> \n \n

         <b>Ambho purisa, kiṃ tuyh’iminā pāpakena dujjīvitena? Matan-te jīvitā seyyo ti,</b>\n
         “Come on, friend, what good is this miserable life full of suffering to you? Death is better for you than life!” \n
         <i>“Come on, friend, what good is this miserable life full of suffering to you? Death is better for you than life!”</i> \n \n

         <b>iti cittamano cittasaṅkappo anekapariyāyena maraṇavaṇṇaṃ vā saṃvaṇṇeyya, maraṇāya vā samādapeyya;</b> \n
         If he, [having such] thoughts and intentions, will in every possible way praise death or incite it,\n
         <i>If he, [having such] thoughts and intentions, will in every possible way praise death or incite it,</i> \n \n

         <b>ayam-pi pārājiko hoti, asaṃvāso.</b> \n
         then he is also expelled and no longer in the sangha. \n
         <i>then he is also expelled and no longer in the sangha.</i> \n \n \n

     \n \n This rule arose as a result of two different events: \n \n
The first event is related to the story when the monks, after practicing meditation on the unattractiveness of the body, committed suicide by paying the man Megalandika to kill them. \n \n
The second event involves the monks from the group of six.
They persuaded the sick husband of a laywoman to commit suicide so that he would stop suffering from his illness. \n \n

                        <b>Factors</b> \n \n
For a manussaviggaha pārājikā crime to be committed, five factors must be present: \n
1. The creature to be killed is a human being. \n
2. Knowing that a creature is alive\n
3. Intent to kill the creature\n
4. Tactics, method, method of killing a creature\n
5. This tactic, method, method led to the death of a person. \n \n
        
        METHODS OF KILLING \n \n
There are six ways in which murder can be committed: \n \n
1. SĀHATTHIKA-PAYOGA is the act of beating with one`s own body or sticks, swords, etc. connected to the body. This also includes glorifying death. \n \n
2. NISSAGGIYA-PAYOGA - this is the throwing of stones, the release of arrows, bullets, etc. with one`s own body or through an object connected to the body. \n \n
3. ĀṆATTIKA-PAYOGA is a command to another, saying: “Kill this person.” \n \n
4. THĀVARA-PAYOGA is digging holes, setting traps, spikes, etc. for the purpose of killing another. \n \n
5. VIJJĀMAYA-PAYOGA is the practice of witchcraft for the purpose of killing another. \n \n
6. IDDHIMAYA-PAYOGA is the use of the kamma-iddhi powers bestowed at birth to kill living beings. According to the literature, this ability is bestowed mainly on non-human beings, but some humans can also be endowed with it. \n \n

                        CASES OF VIOLATION \n \n
1. A bhikkhu tries to kill a person. dukkaṭa for any efforts related to finding weapons and so on. If the person attacked suffers, the bhikkhu does thullaccaya. If a person dies, the bhikkhu performs pārājikā. \n \n
2. Bhikkhu tries to kill yakhs, petas, animals such as nagas in the form of humans. Trying to find weapons, etc., dukkaṭa. When non-human beings who are attacked suffer, the bhikkhu performs dukkaṭa. When these creatures die – thulaccaya. \n \n
3. A bhikkhu tries to kill an animal. All preliminary actions are dukkaṭa. If the attacked animal suffers - dukkaṭa. If the animal dies - pācittiya in accordance with the rule of teaching sañcicca. \n \n \n \n

                CASES OF NO VIOLATION \n \n
1. Asañcicca - If a bhikkhu performs an action without thinking that "as a result of this action a being may be killed", and yet the performance of this action actually results in the death of a person, parajika will not be performed.
On one occasion, when one bhikkhu was arranging the seats in the hall, another raised a pestle and the first bhikkhu took one of them. The second pestle fell to the floor and hit the child on the head, resulting in death. The Buddha instructed that the bhikkhu did not commit any crime because he did not know that his act could kill a being, or did not know about it at all. \n \n
2. Ajānantassa - if a bhikkhu does not know that "this object, instrument or thing can cause the death of a being" and commits an act in which a person dies due to such object, instrument or thing, no crime will be committed.
One day one bhikkhu served some of his food collected from the pindapata to another bhikkhu. Poison was mixed into the food, and the bhikkhu who donated the food did not know about it. The bhikkhu who ate it died. When the Buddha inquired, the donor bhikkhu stated that he did not know that poison had been mixed into the food. Therefore the bhikkhu is not guilty. \n \n
3. Namaraṇādhippāyassa - a certain action is performed without the intention of killing a creature. As a result, the person will die and no crime will be committed.
One day, a barren woman asked a bhikkhu for medicine to become pregnant. The bhikkhu gave the medicine that led to death. Since the bhikkhu had no intention of killing the woman, no crime will be committed. \n \n
4. Ummattakassa\n\n
5. Khittachittassa \n \n
6.Vedanaṭṭassa\n\n
7. Ādikammikassa \n \n


                        <b>original rule</b> \n \n
The Buddha once taught the benefits of the practice of asubha meditation (contemplation of the lack of attractiveness of the body) to bhikkhus who lived in thevillage Kūṭāgāra, located in the forests near the city of Vezali, enthusiastically began the practice. However, after some time, the bhikkhus began to suffer from disgust for their bodies and preferred death. Some bhikkhus committed suicide. Some bhikkhus killed each other. Some bhikkhus approached a robes-wearer named Migalaṇḍika, who ate scraps in the temples, and hired him to take their own lives. The Buddha, upon learning of this situation, declared the third parajika, which stated that if a bhikkhu kills a person, he will commit the crime of parajika. \n
<b>"yo pana bhikkhu sañcicca manussaviggahaṃ jīvitā voropeyya satthahārakaṃ vāssa pariyeseyya, ayampi pārājiko hoti asaṃvāso"ti.</b> \n \n
                <b>addition</b> \n \n
At some point in time, a lay follower became ill. His wife was a famous beauty. Some bhikkhus from the Chabbaggiya group, fascinated by her krsata, came to him and spoke to him about the virtues of death. Having heard about the virtues of death, the layman ate unsuitable food and died. Because of this incident, the Buddha declared that proclaiming the virtues of death is the cause of pararajika and made the following addition:\n
<b>"maraṇavaṇṇaṃ vā saṃvaṇṇeyya maraṇāya vā samādapeyya `ambho purisa, kiṃ tuyihiminā pāpakena dujjīvitena mataṃ te seyyo`ti. Iti cittamano cittasaṅkappo anekapariy āyena maraṇavaṇṇaṃ vāsaṃvaṇṇeyya maraṇāya vā samādapeyya."</b> \n \n

         \n \n \n \n
</string>
    <string name="textPatimokhaParajika4"> \n
        Pàr 4: (Uttarimanussadhammasikkhàpadam): \n
        <i>the rule about superhuman abilities.</i> \n \n

        <b>Yo pana bhikkhu anabhijānaṃ</b> \n
        <i>if any monk does not know directly</i> \n \n

        <b>uttarimanussadhammaṃ</b> \n
        <i>superhuman abilities</i> \n \n

        <b>attūpanāyikaṃ alamariyañāṇadassanaṃ</b> \n
        <i>their own, with knowledge like a noble</i> \n \n

        <b>samudācareyya:</b> \n
        <i>declares</i> \n \n

        <b>Iti jānāmi, iti passāmī ti!</b> \n
        <i>So I know, so I see</i> \n \n

        <b>Tato aparena samayena</b> \n
        <i>then at another time</i> \n \n

        <b>samanuggāhiyamāno vā</b> \n
        <i>they`ll interrogate him</i> \n \n

        <b>asamanuggāhiyamāno vā</b> \n
        <i>they won`t interrogate him</i> \n \n

        <b>āpanno visuddhāpekkho evaṃ vadeyya:</b> \n
        <i>and he, seeking purification, could say:</i> \n \n

        <b>Ajānam-evāhaṃ āvuso avacaṃ: jānāmi.</b> \n
        <i>I said I know friends, I don`t really know</i> \n \n

        <b>Apassaṃ: passāmi.</b> \n
        <i>I see it, but I don`t see it.</i> \n \n

        <b>Tucchaṃ musā vilapin-ti. Aññatra adhimānā,</b>
        <i>I vainly have said stupid things. Overestimated himself,</i> \n \n

        <b>ayam-pi pārājiko hoti, asaṃvāso.</b> \n
        <i>Such a monk has been defeated and is no longer a member of the Sangkha.</i> \n \n

        \n \n This rule arose as a result of two different events: \n \n
The first event involves monks who decide to praise each other as if they have superhuman abilities. They did this so that during a bad harvest, the laity would give them more food. \n \n
The second event involved monks who overestimated their abilities and said that they had achieved something that they had not actually achieved. When these monks realized that they were mistaken, they declared it. \n \n \n

                        FACTORS \n \n
For uttarimanusadhamma pararajika to occur, five elements must be fulfilled. \n \n
1. Not possessing any of the higher human states \n \n
2. Claiming superior human qualities that a person does not actually possess, with the base intention of gaining fame and gain \n \n
3. Direct statement without subtext \n \n
4. A creature said to be human \n \n
5. Know right away, not later \n \n

                        CASES OF VIOLATIONS \n \n
The following are instances of violations associated with this training rule. \n \n
1. If someone directly says that he has higher human states, which he actually does not possess, and the person hearing this immediately thinks: “This bhikkhu claims to have acquired jhana, says that he is a supreme or noble being.” etc., then the crime pārājikā is committed. \n \n
This can happen as described below. Even if the one who hears does not know about jhana from the point of view of exclusivity or the study of dhamma, but only knows the words jhana and vimokha, and understands it as “This bhikkhu can obviously enter the state of jhana, he obviously achieves vimokha.” etc., the bhikkhu will still be pārājikā. \n \n
Here`s how to express this idea. \n \n
A knowingly false statement: “I have reached the first (second/third/fourth) jhana (or level of phala, etc.)” will lead to pārājikā. \n \n
A deliberately false statement “I have reached the first (second/third/fourth) jhana (or the level of phala, etc.)” will lead to pārājikā. \n \n
Knowingly false statement "I will reach the first second/third/fourth) jhāna (or phalā level, etc.)" will lead to pārājikā. \n \n
Knowingly false statement "I regularly achieve the first (second/third/fourth) jhāna (or level of phalā, etc.)" will result in pārājikā. \n \n
  A deliberately false statement “I have mastered the first (second/third/fourth) jhana (or the level of phala, etc.)” will lead to “parajika”. \n \n
A deliberately false statement, “I have fully comprehended the first (second/third/fourth) jhana (or level of phala, etc.)” will lead to pārājikā. \n \n
If the listener does not immediately understand the meaning of what was said, he will suspect: “What is he saying?” etc. or finds out about it much later by asking, then the bhikkhu will commit the crime of thullaccaya. For bhikkhus, pārājikā will not apply. \n \n
If it is indirectly mentioned: “He who lives in your temple obtains jhana,” etc., and the listener immediately understands this, then the bhikkhu commits the crime of tulacchaya. According to Kaṅkhāvitaraṇī Abhinavaṭīkā, since a bhikkhu does not directly say: “I have acquired jhāna,” etc., he is not a pārājikā. \n \n
If what is said indirectly is not immediately understood by the listener, the bhikkhu will commit the crime of dukkatta. The Abhinavaṭīkā notes that the crime of dukkaṭa will be committed because an attempt has been made to deceive others by making false statements. \n \n
If, with the intention of gaining respect from others, a bhikkhu walks and behaves in a certain way or lives in a forest monastery, then the crime of dukkatta is committed. \n \n
Wanting to mention his highest human state, a person mistakenly mentions another highest human state instead, knowing that this is a false statement, and if the listener instantly understands this, then there will be parājika. For example, wanting to say, “I attain the first jhana,” if one actually says, “I attain the second jhana,” and if the listener instantly understands this, then the bhikkhu pārājikā. \n \n
                CASES OF NO VIOLATIONS \n \n
The following are the illegal actions associated with the fourth rule of parajik. \n \n
1. Adhimanena - if you mention the highest states of a person without actually possessing them, from adhimana, there will be no violation. \n \n
2. Anullapanādhippāyassa - If one speaks without the intention of hinting to others about the superior human condition that one possesses, no crime will be committed. For example, when a Dhamma matter regarding an arahant is explained, and if a person says, "Consider that I am an arahant. Then those who scold me in this way will be guilty of aryopavada," etc. With the intention of continuing to explain a Dhamma matter, there is no violation . \n \n
3. Ummatakassa \n \n
4. Khittachittassa \n \n
5.Vedanaṭṭassa\n\n
6.Ādikammikassa \n \n

                        RULE DESCRIPTION \n \n
The wealth of a monk is spiritual values such as sīla, patience, compassion, samādhi, abhiññā, wisdom, etc. A monk who is truly spiritual will be revered not only by lay people but also by other monks. Therefore, if Monax says he has great achievements and qualities that he really does not have, this is a deception done in hopes of gaining respect. Of these achievements, jhāna, abhiññā, magga and phala are the most highly valued. They are called the highest states of man. A person who has achieved such states is a superior personality. He will be worthy of worship by all beings of the world, including all gods. A monk who claims to have achieved the highest human states when he has not is trying to gain the respect of other people through cunning and deception. Therefore, claiming to have the highest human states when in fact this is not the case is a grave mistake, which can lead to denying the status of the highest initiation proclaimed by the Buddha. \n \n
            TRANSLATION OF SOME TERMS \n \n
1. Yo pana bhikkhu anabhijānaṃ uttarimanussadhammaṃ attūpanāyikaṃ alamariyañāṇadassanaṃ samudācareyya `Iti jānāmi, iti passāmī`ti. \n \n
In the phrase "anabhijānaṃ uttarimanussadhammaṃ alamariyañāṇadassanaṃ attupanāyikaṃ katvā `iti jānāmi, iti passāmī`ti samudācareyya", the part "alamariyañāṇadassanaṃ uttarimanussadhammaṃ anabhi jānaṃ" means knowing that one does not possess any higher human states. The highest human states are jhāna, abhiññā, magga and phala. Since these are a series of pure states of wisdom capable of eradicating vices in the forms of suppression (vikkhambhana), eradication (samuccheda) and pacification (paṭippassaddhi), they are called (alamariyañāṇadassana). \n \n
The remaining words should be interpreted as follows: \n \n
"taṃ asantaṃ uttarimanussadhammaṃ anabhijānaṃ attūpaṇāyikaṃ katvā `iti jānāmi iti passamī`ti samudacareyya." Knowing that he does not possess any higher human states which have not been achieved by himself, if he implies that he possesses them or has achieved certain states, and proclaims “I know, I have seen,” and directly makes such false statements (lies) , this will lead to pārājikā. \n \n
                AÑÑATRA ADHIMĀNĀ \n \n
The phrase "aññatra adhimānā" means that the crime of pārājikā can only be committed if a person mentions higher human states that he does not possess, without deluding himself about his achievement. If a bhikkhu, without having received magga or phala, affirms in his mind the thought: “I have achieved,” this is known as having adhimana. A bhikkhu who has adhimana says that he has reached the highest human states only because he has a wrong idea of himself, and not with the intention of deceiving others. Therefore, a bhikkhu who claims to have the highest human states because of adhimāna, when in fact he does not, does not commit any crime according to this rule of teaching. This crime can only be committed if a person knowingly makes a false claim that he possesses higher human states which he does not actually possess. \n \n
                ADHIMĀNĀ \n \n
(excessive confidence in one`s own achievements) \n \n
Even if jhana or magga-phala has not been achieved, some may have the misconception that it has been achieved. This is called adhimana. Such overconfidence does not arise in immoral people who do not expect to achieve jhana or any other higher state of man. It also does not arise in virtuous people who do everything else except Samatha and Vipassana meditation. Meditators who follow pure virtue and meditate with great determination can sometimes develop such a wrong perception. Noble beings never experience adhimana. Therefore a person who has attained the state of sotāpanna can never think that he has attained the state of sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī or arahant. It is noted that those who have developed samatha or vipassana can develop adhimana regarding the lowest path and fruition and will never develop the delusion of thinking that they have become arahants, while those who have developed both samatha and vipassana can to experience adhimanu thinking that one has attained arhatship. The commentaries note that some Mahatharas in the early periods lived with adhimana for years, thinking that they had achieved arhatship. Since declaring higher human states due to adhimana does not involve deception, it will not lead to the commission of any crime. \n \n

                   FIVE GREAT THIEVES (MAHĀCORA) \n \n
The primary reason for the announcement of the fourth rule of parajika is the monks of Vaggumuda declaring that they had achieved the highest human states when in fact they had not, and obtaining benefits and treatment from people by deceiving them by claiming so. The Buddha sharply despised this disgusting act in his sermons and said that there are five great thieves in this world: \n \n
1. The first great thief is a bhikkhu who gathers many monks and creates a large group of which he becomes the leader; and, using such a group and thanks toits numbers, receives benefits and treatment from laymen and monks. \n \n
2. A bhikkhu who studies the Dhamma preached by the Buddha preaches it to the masses. In this case, people find it pleasant and say with reverence, “Venerable sir, your preaching of the Dhamma is admirable. From whom did you learn this Dhamma.” The bhikkhu refrains from mentioning his teacher and replies: “And who teaches us,” implying that the Dhamma was found by himself. Such a bhikkhu is considered the second great thief of sasana. \n \n
3. The third great thief is a bhikkhu who steals another`s values (such as morality) by accusing a noble being or bhikkhu kalyāṇa puthujjana, who is pure in virtue and celibate, of committing the first crime of pārājikā - sexual intercourse. \n \n
4. A monk who gives away property that cannot be distributed among the people (avebhaṅgiya garu bhaṇḍa), such as paddy fields, gardens, furniture, steel containers, etc., belonging to the Saṅgha, with the intention of making the lay people happy, is the fourth great thief. A bhikkhu who entertains lay people using objects belonging to the Saṅgha performs kuladūsana dukkaṭa. It will be suitable for pabbājanīyakamma.. This is the act of expelling a monk or nun from the temple. When objects belonging to the Saṅgha are given away against the will of the monk, if the monk has authority among the Saṅgha, the crime of thullaccaya is committed. If this is done out of secrecy (self-interest and the desire to hide), then pārājikā is committed. \n \n
5. A bhikkhu who deceives the world by saying that he has the highest human qualities when in fact he does not possess them is the greatest thief of words, including the deities. \n \n
     \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="buttonSuttasForSanyutta">samyutta nikaya</string>
    <string name="buttonSuttasForAnguttara">anguttara nikaya</string>
    <string name="buttonSuttasForKuddaka">khuddaka nikaya</string>
    <string name="buttonTextSuttasToByCategory">suttas by category</string>
    <string name="theravada_ru">The material was copied from the site: \n theravada.ru</string>
    <string name="mainButtonMonksAbhidhamma"><A>ABHIDHAMMA</A></string> />


</resources>