<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="mainButtonLiveBuddha">The Life of the Buddha</string>
    <string name="mainButtonStofiDlyaDeclomacii">Stanzas for recitation</string>
    <string name="mainButtonShortSuttas">Short Suttas</string>
    <string name="mainButtonMonksRules">Monastic rules</string>
    <string name="namerenie_sumedhi">1. Sumedha\'s Intention</string>
    <string name="son_mahamayi">2. Mahamaya\'s Dream</string>
    <string name="rogdenie_sidharthi">3. The Birth of Siddhartha</string>
    <string name="mudrec_asita">4. Sage Asita</string>
    <string name="pervoe_dostigenie_dgani">5. The first achievement of jhana</string>
    <string name="spasenie_lebedya">6. Saving the swan</string>
    <string name="demonstraciya_umenii">7. Demonstration of skills</string>
    <string name="sumedha">The first picture is a kind of prequel, the action takes place long before when\n         Siddhartha was born when a man named Sumedha set out to become a Bodhisattva\n         i.e. those who, over an unimaginably long period of time, improve their qualities\n         allowing in the last birth to become a Buddha who awakens independently at four\n         truth and unsurpassed teaches them to people and devas.\n \n\n\n         The figure depicts the Buddha Dipankara, accompanied by four hundred thousand Arhats,\n         going to the city of Ranma at the invitation of the townspeople to accept gifts, as well as a brahmin\n         Sumedha the bodhisattva vower prostrating himself before the Buddha.\n \n\n\n         Buddha Dipankara (lit. One who makes oil lamps, or giving light to the lamp) is a Tathagata who lived four Immeasurable Kalpas and a hundred thousand eons ago. The first Buddha of the twenty-four Tathagatas of the past, which Buddha Shakyamuni told his students about.\n         During the time of Buddha Dipankara, the future Buddha Shakyamuni reincarnated as the Brahmin Sumedha. Once he thought about the vicissitudes of reincarnation, about suffering, about old age and illness. His thoughts led to the decision to engage in ascetic practice in order to find a way to free himself from the shackles of rebirth. During this period, the fame of the Conqueror in Truth, Buddha Dipankara, began to spread in the world.\n         While visiting the city (Ramma), Sumedha saw people preparing the road for the visit of Buddha Dipankara. They told Sumedha that they were clearing the way for the Buddha, who had attained perfect Awakening, to pass. Wandering with a large community of disciples, Dipankara arrived in their city and stayed nearby in the monastery of Sudassana. The inhabitants of the city invited the Buddha and are now preparing the road along which he must pass.\n         When he learned about the appearance of the Buddha in this world, Sumedha was overwhelmed with supreme joy. He asked people to give him a section of the road so that he could take part in its preparation. He was given a section of the road with earth soggy with water, and then he began to drain it, thinking about the Buddha.\n         But before the road was fully prepared, the great sage Dipankara appeared, surrounded by four hundred thousand liberated ones. The ascetic Sumedha, seeing the Most Honored One, exclaimed:\n         Let the Buddha not step on the dirt, but together with his disciples, walk over me for my benefit.\n         Having loosened his long ascetic hair and covered the ground with it, Sumedha lay down on that muddy section of the road. And at that time Sumedha had these thoughts:\n         If I wanted to, I could enter the city of Ranmu as a newly converted monk who had destroyed all mental defilements. But I should not hide by achieving nibbana with the destruction of mental defilements. Instead, I should, like Dipankara, realize perfect Realization, and, boarding the ship of Dhamma, ferry many people across the ocean of samsara, and only then realize [ultimate] nibbana - that\'s what I should do. Then, after listing the eight conditions (required to achieve Buddhahood) and firmly determined to become a Buddha, he lay down.\n         When Dipankara approached Sumedha, he uttered a prophecy:\n         This person lying here has decided to become a Buddha, his wish will be fulfilled, after four asankhyas and one hundred thousand cycles, he will become a Buddha named Gotama. And in that life, his place of residence will be the city of Kapilavatthu, his mother will be Queen Maya, Raja Suddhodana will be his father, his main student will be the senior monk Upatissa, the second student will be the senior monk Kolita, the personal assistant of the Buddha will be Ananda, his main student will be the nun Khema , the second student will be the nun Uppalavanna. When he reaches the age of mature knowledge, he will renounce the world and make great effort.\n         Having received rice porridge at the foot of the banyan and eating it on the banks of the Neranjara River, he will then sit on a seat under the bodhi tree, after which he will attain Buddhahood at the foot of the fig tree [Bodhi].\n\n         In iconography, Dipankara is represented as a standing or seated Buddha.\n \n\n         Images where Dipankara stands are common in China, Thailand and Nepal.\n \n\n         It is believed that one of the Buddha statues in Bamiyan (Afghanistan), destroyed by the Taliban in 2001, depicted the standing Buddha Dipankara.\n \n\n         Sometimes Buddha Shakyamuni and Buddha Maitreya are depicted next to him. In this case, Dipankara (Buddha of the past), Shakyamuni (Buddha of the present) and Maitreya (Buddha of the future) symbolize together the Buddhas of the three times.</string>
    <string name="mahamaya">The picture depicts a dream that Mahamaya has, foreshadowing that she will give birth to a great man. \n \n\n Mahamaya, the wife of Raja Shuddhodana, Siddhartha\'s mother, was a princess from the kingdom of Koliyas. \n\nAfter the meeting of the brahman Sumedha with the Buddha Deepankara, during which Sumedha took bodhisattva vows, an incalculable number of years passed, during which the Bodhisattva developed the qualities necessary for enlightenment as a Sammasambudda. Before entering his last birth, the Bodhisattva arrived in the world of the Tusita (Contented), when the so-called Proclamation about the Buddha appeared in this world, the Devas of all ten thousand world systems gathered there together with their rulers, addressing the Bodhisattva as follows: Sir, when you developed the ten perfections, you did not do it for in order to take the place of Sakka, Mara, Brahma or the king of the world; you developed them in order to achieve omniscience in order to cross to the other side of the world! The time has come, sir, for Buddhahood, now, sir, that time has come!. But the Bodhisatta, as if the deities were not appealing to him, was thinking about five important issues in the following sequence, namely: time; country; family; mother and the duration of her life. \n\nAnd at first he thought about time, thinking: Is this the right time or not? And on this issue he thought: When life expectancy increases to a hundred thousand years, this is not the right time. Why? Because with such a long life, a person does not feel that living beings are subject to birth, old age and death, and when Buddhas talk about impermanence, dissatisfaction and impersonality, people do not listen and do not believe them, thinking: What are they talking about?. At such a time there can be no understanding, and without this, the teaching does not lead [to the goal]. That\'s why this is the wrong time. Also, the time when the life expectancy is less than a hundred years is not suitable. And why? Because when the evil between people increases, a remark addressed to vicious people cannot stand, like a twig that has fallen into a river. Therefore, such a time is also inappropriate. But when the life expectancy is less than a hundred thousand years, but more than a hundred years, then this is the right time. \n\nThen, thinking about which country is necessary for his birth and considering the four great continents with the islands surrounding them, he realized that Buddhas are not born on three continents, but they are born in Jambudip and so he made a decision about the country.\nThen reflecting on the family he thought: Buddhas are not born either in the Vaishya caste or in the Sudra caste - they are born either in the brahman caste or in the kshatriya caste, depending on which of these castes currently has the highest position. The kshatriya caste is higher now, I have to be born in it and Raja Suddhodana will be my father. So he decided on a family. \n\nReflecting on the question of his mother, he thought: The Buddha\'s mother cannot be lustful or a drinker, she developed Perfection for a hundred thousand cycles and from the moment of birth strictly observed the Five Rules. Queen Maha Maya is exactly like that, she will be my mother. Further reflecting on how long her life would last, he realized that her life would last ten months and seven days. \n\nHaving received answers to the five most important questions, he graciously agreed with the deities, saying: Gentlemen, it\'s time for me to become a Buddha.\nMeanwhile, a Midsummer festival was announced in the city of Kapilavatthu and a large number of people were having fun at the festival. For seven days before the full moon, Queen Maha Maya participated in the festival. On the seventh day, she got up early, washed her face and arranged a huge handout with a total value of four hundred thousand. Wearing her richest outfit, she took food. Rushing to the factors of the day of special prescriptions, she went into her room, lay down on the royal bed and when she fell asleep, she had a dream about a big white elephant approaching her, holding a white lotus flower in its silver trunk and making a mighty sound that resounded everywhere, he respectfully walked around Mahamaya\'s bed three times and entered her womb. \n\n\nWaking up the next day, the queen told her dream to the rajah. Sixty-four brahmanas were called, the raja told them the dream of the queen and asked: What does this portend? \n\nThe brahmanas said: Don\'t worry, great ruler! Your spouse conceived and in her womb is a boy, not a girl. You\'re going to have a son. And if he prefers the worldly life, he will become the king of the world, but if, after leaving home, he prefers the life of a hermit, he will become a Buddha and in this world he will tear off the veil [of passion, disgust, etc.].</string>
    <string name="birdth">The picture shows the last birth of a Bodhisattva. \n \n\n            According to legend, many miracles are associated with the birth of a Bodhisattva, some of them are described in the Buddhist canon of Tripitaka. \n \n\nHere is an excerpt from the Mahapadan Sutta Dn14: \n \n\n\"It is the law, bhikkhus, that while other women carry a child for nine or ten months before childbirth begins, in the case of a Bodhisattva, it is not so – his mother carries him for exactly ten months before childbirth begins. \n\nIt is the law, bhikkhus, that while other women give birth sitting or lying down, in the case of a Bodhisattva it is not so – his mother gives birth standing up. \n\nThis is the law, monks, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, the devas greet him first, and then people. \n\nIt is the law, bhikkhus, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, he does not touch the ground. Four devas pick it up and hand it to the mother, saying: \"Rejoice, Your Majesty, you have the greatest son!\". \n\nThis is the law, monks, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, he appears untainted by water, mucus, blood or any impurities – he is pure and flawless. If a gemstone is put on a muslin from Kasi, then the stone does not pollute the muslin, and the muslin does not pollute the stone. Why? Because both the fabric and the gemstone are clean. Similarly, a Bodhisattva comes out of his mother\'s womb untainted by water, mucus, blood or any impurities – he is pure and flawless. \n\nThis is the law, bhikkhus, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, two streams of water gush from heaven – one cold, the other warm, washing the Bodhisattva and his mother. \n\nSuch is the law, monks, that as soon as a Bodhisattva is born, he stands firmly on his feet and takes seven steps to the north, and then, under a white canopy (from the sun), he covers all four sides with his gaze and declares in a loud voice: \"I am the greatest in this world, the highest in the world, the first in the world. This is my last birth, there will be no more new rebirths.\" \n\nThis is the law, monks, that when a Bodhisatta comes out of the womb of the mother, then in this world with its devas, Maras and Brahmas, its ascetics and priests, kings and commoners, there is an immeasurable dazzling light that eclipses the radiance of the most majestic deities.\" \n \n\n\nAnd so the queen Maha Maya, for 10 months carefully carrying the Bodhisattva in her womb,\n            I realized that childbirth was approaching and wished to do it at home, in my family.\n            She went to Raja Suddhodana and said, Your Majesty, I want to go to Devadaha, the city of my relatives.\n            The Raja agreed and ordered to level the road from Kapilavatthu to Devadaha, and seated the queen in a golden palanquin,\n            carried by a thousand servants, he dismissed her with a large retinue. \n\nBetween the two cities there is a tallow grove for recreation, owned by residents of both cities and this grove is called Lumbini.\n            The whole Lumbini grove looked like a forest full of colorful vines or like a well-decorated reception hall of some\n            a powerful ruler. The queen was filled with a desire to stay in a grove of tallow trees and the servants carried her into the grove.\n            When she came to the foot of the royal tallow tree, she wanted to take hold of its branch and stretch out her hand,\n            she took hold of a branch and then the kamma-born winds shook her. The servants, having unfolded the veil around the queen, moved aside.\n            Standing and holding on to a branch of a tallow tree, she gave birth.Just at that moment, the four great brahmas came there,\n            having brought a golden net, they accepted the future Buddha on it. Then they put it in front of the mother, saying:\n            Rejoice, Queen! You have given birth to a powerful son!. From their hands, the Bodhisattva was accepted by people on a bundle\n            After leaving their hands, the Bodhisattva stood on the ground and looked to the east.\n            Thousands of world systems became visible to him as one open space.\n            Searching in ten directions and not finding anyone like himself, he took seven big steps, saying:\n            This is the best direction. Then, stopping at the seventh step, showing his majestic voice, he said with a lion\'s roar:\n            \"I am the greatest in this world, the highest in the world, the first in the world. This is my last birth, there will be no more new rebirths.\"</string>
    <string name="asita">In the drawing of Raja Suddhodan, Siddhardha\'s father shows his son to sage Asita. \n \n\n\"Asita: Sage and spiritual mentor of Sihahanu, Suddhodana\'s father. He was Suddhodana\'s teacher and later became his spiritual mentor. He came morning and evening to visit King Suddhodana, who showed him great respect even when he was his disciple.\"\nAccording to the Buddhaghosa (SnA.ii.483), Asita got his name because of his dark skin. He also had another name - Kanha Devala (SnA.ii.487). He was also called Kanha Siri (Sn.v.689) or Siri Kanha (SnA.487) or Kala Devala (J.I.54). He should obviously be distinguished from Asita Devala, who was also called Kala Devala.\nAfter the death of King Sihahanu, Asita left the worldly life. After some time, he developed various superpowers, and since then he has spent all day in the deva worlds. One day, while staying in Tavatims, he saw the whole city decorated, and the gods rejoiced. From them he learned that Siddhattha Gotama, the future Buddha, was to be born. He immediately went to King Suddhodana and asked to see the child.  \"I heard you had a son, O great Raja! Let me see him.\"\nThe Raja ordered his son to be dressed and brought so that he would bow to the sage.\nBut the future Buddha unfolded his feet and placed them on the tangled hair of the sage. It is noted that a Bodhisattva cannot worship anyone, and if the child\'s head touched the ascetic\'s feet, his head would split. The sage got up from his seat, saying: It would be wrong for me to follow the path of self-destruction, and he bowed to the Bodhisattva. And the rajah, seeing such a miracle, also bowed to his own son.\nLooking at the signs of future greatness on the Bodhisattva\'s body, he wondered: \"Will this baby become a Buddha or not?\". And it was revealed to the sage that the raja\'s son would definitely become a Buddha. Smiling, he said, \"What an amazing person.\" Then he thought, \"Will it be given to me to see him when he becomes a Buddha?\". And it was revealed to him that no. \"If I die before this happens, I will be reborn in a formless world; so at a time when hundreds, and possibly thousands of Buddhas appeared among people, I cannot become a disciple of one of them. And I won\'t be lucky enough to see this amazing man when he becomes a Buddha. Alas, my loss is great!\" And he began to cry. People who saw this asked: \"Our teacher was just smiling, and now he started crying! Tell me, venerable one, will any misfortune happen to our master\'s son?\".\n\"He\'s fine, he will definitely become a Buddha,\" was the answer.\n\"Then why are you crying?\"\n\"It will not be given to me,\" the sage replied, \"to see such a great man when he becomes a Buddha. Alas! Great is my loss! Feeling sorry for myself, I cry.\"\nThen he asked himself, \"Will it be given to any of my relatives to see him as a Buddha?\". And Asita discovered that his nephew, the boy Nalaki, would have such an opportunity. He went to his sister and asked her, \"Where is your son Nalaka?\".\n\"In the house, brother.\"\n\"Call him.\" When the nephew came up, Asita told him: \"A son, the future Buddha, was born in the family of Raja Suddhodana. He will become a Buddha at the age of thirty-five and you will be given to see him. Leave the worldly life today!\".\nKnowing that his uncle would not give instructions without a special reason, the young man, although he was born into a family with great wealth, immediately took yellow clothes and a clay alms vessel from the pantry, shaved his head and changed clothes. Having said: \"I am leaving the worldly life for the greatest man on earth,\" he folded his hands in a gesture of respect, bowed \"in five parts\" in the direction of the Bodhisattva. Then, putting the begging vessel in a bag and hanging the bag on his shoulder, he headed to the Himalayas, where he began to live as a hermit.\nWhen the Tathagata reached the highest Realization, Nalaka went to him and learned about the way of salvation. Nalaka then returned to the Himalayas and attained arhatship. After that, he lived for another seven months. Nalaka died, standing near the Golden Hill, by the final liberation without a trace.</string>
    <string name="pudja">Puja</string>
    <string name="sutta">Sutta</string>
    <string name="drugie_declomacii">Other recitations</string>
    <string name="karaniya_metta">Karania metta sutta</string>
    <string name="utrennaia_pudga">Morning Puja</string>
    <string name="decl_pered_priemom_pichi">recitation before meals</string>
    <string name="prosba_o_prochenii_nedostatkov">A request for forgiveness of shortcomings in front of senior monks</string>
    <string name="blagopogelaniya_pri_vzyatii_pichi">Well -wishes to the laity at the taking are given</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaPeredPrinyatiemPichi">" <b>RECITATION BEFORE LUNCH</b>\n \n <b><u>Paṭisaṅkhā yoniso piṇḍapātaṁ paṭisevāmi,</u></b>\n \n <i>Having thoughtfully considered this, I eat the food presented to me </i>  \n   \n <b><u>N’eva davāya na madāya na maṇḍanāya na vibhūsanāya,</u></b>\n  \n <i>Not for entertainment, not for intoxication, not for weight gain, not to be beautiful,</i> \n    \n <b><u>Yāvadeva imassa kāyassa ṭhitiyā yāpanāya vihiṁsuparatiyā brahma-cariyānuggahāya,</u></b>\n   \n <i>But just for survival, for the support of this body, for the cessation of its suffering, for the support of a holy life,</i> \n  \n <b><u>Iti purāṇañ-ca vedanaṁ paṭihaṅkhāmi navañ-ca vedanaṁ na uppādessāmi,</u></b>\n   \n <i> “This way I will destroy the old feeling of hunger and will not create new feelings from overeating.”</i>  \n \n <b><u>Yātrā ca me bhavissati anavajjatā ca phāsu-vihāro cāti.</u></b>  \n <i>I will try to be perfect</i>"</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaForgivennes">\n        <b>A REQUEST FOR FORGIVENESS OF SHORTCOMINGS IN FRONT OF SENIOR MONKS</b> \n \n \n\n<b><u>Okāsa vandāmi Bhante. Sabbam accayam kamatha me bhante.</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Allow me to honor you, venerable one. Forgive me all the mistakes, my dear.</i> \n \n\n <b><u>Mayākataṁ puññaṁ, sāminā anumodi tabbaṁ.</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Please, Bhante, let me share with you the merits that I have acquired.</i> \n \n\n<i>(Bhantes: Sādhu, Sādhu, anumodāmi! Okay, okay, I\'m happy!)</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Saminā kataṁ puññaṁ, mayhaṁ dātabbaṁ</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Please, Bhante, share with me the merits that you have acquired.</i> \n \n\n<i>(Bhantes: Sādhu, Sādhu, anumodetha! Okay, okay, I\'m happy!)</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Sādhu, Sādhu anumodāmi!</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Okay, okay, I appreciate it!</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Okāsa! Dvārattena kataṁ sabbaṁ accayaṁ khamatha me Bhante.</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Forgive me, O Bhante, for any mistakes I may have made in body, speech or mind.</i> \n \n\n<i>(Bhantes: Kamāmi kamitabbaṁ. I forgive.)</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Sadhu Okāsa khamāmi Bhante!</u></b> \n \n\n<i>I beg your pardon, O Bhanta.</i></string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaAlmsWish">"\n        <b>WELL -WISHES TO THE LAITY AT THE TAKING ARE GIVEN</b> \n \n \n\n        <u>OPTION 1</u> \n\n<b><u>Abhivadana silasa, niccam vuddhapacayino</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Constantly expressing respect for morality and those who should be honored</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Cattaro dhamma vaddhanti, ayu vanno sukham balam</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Let the four dhammas increase: longevity, success, well-being, health</i> "</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaMorningPuja"><b>MORNING PUJA</b> \n \n \n\n        <u>EXPRESSION OF RESPECT</u> \n\n<b><u>Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambuddhassa [3x]</u></b> \n\n<i>Reverence to the Blessed, worthy, comprehended in perfection.</i> \n \n\n        <u>APPEAL TO THE BUDDHA</u> \n\n<b><u>Ni`vedaya`mi sambuddham</u></b> \n\n<i>I appeal to Samasambudda</i> \n\n<b><u>Vi`tara`gam maha`munim</u></b> \n\n<i>To the great sage who destroyed passion</i> \n\n<b><u>Ni`mantaya`mi sugatam</u></b> \n\n<i>I appeal to Sugatta</i> \n\n<b><u>Lokajettham nara`sabam</u></b> \n\n<i>To the winner of the World, the highest of men</i> \n \n\n        <u>OFFERING OF LIGHT</u> \n\n<b><u>Ghanasārappadittena - dīpena tamadhaṃsinā</u></b> \n\n<i>By the light of flaming camphor, eliminating darkness</i> \n\n<b><u>Tilokadīpaṃ sambuddhaṃ - pūjayāmi tamonudaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>I pay my respects to the enlightener of the three worlds, who has comprehended and dispels darkness (ignorance).</i> \n \n\n        <u>OFFERING INCENSE</u> \n\n<b><u>sugandhikāya vadanaṃ - ananta guṇa gandhinaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>The one whose body and face are fragrant, from whom comes the smell of countless good qualities, </i> \n\n<b><u>sugandhināhaṃ gandhena - pūjayāmi tathāgataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i> I offer these incense - Tathagata.</i> \n \n\n        <u>FLOWER OFFERINGS</u> \n\n<b><u>Vaṇṇagandhaguṇopetaṃ - etaṃ kusumasantatiṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>Having beauty and a pleasant smell of this scattering of flowers,</i> \n\n<b><u>Pūjayāmi munindassa - sirīpādasaroruhe</u></b> \n\n<i>I bring the Supreme Sage to the lotus feet.</i> \n\n<b><u>Pūjemi buddhaṃ kusumenanena – puññena metena labhami mokkhaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>I honor the Buddha with these flowers (kusumena+anena), may I gain liberation through this boon.</i> \n\n<b><u>Pupphaṃ milāyāti yathā idamme - kāyo tathā yāti vināsabhāvaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>As these flowers wither, so this body of mine is subject to destruction.</i> \n \n\n        <u>OFFERING OF OTHER DISHES</u> \n\n<b><u>adhivāsetu no bhante - sabbaṃ saddhāya pūjitaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>Venerable one, show mercy to everything presented on the basis of trust to you</i> \n\n<b><u>anukampaṃ upādāya - patigaṇhātumuttamaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>accept, O greatest one, out of compassion for us.</i>    \n \n\n        <u>QUALITIES OF A BUDDHA</u> \n\n<b><u>Itipi so bhagavā arahaṃ sammāsambuddho</u></b> \n\n<i>The Blessed One really is like this: he is worthy, who has comprehended in perfection,</i> \n\n<b><u>Vijjācaraṇasampanno sugato lokavidū</u></b> \n\n<i>having knowledge and [good] behavior, having achieved the good, a connoisseur of the world,</i> \n\n<b><u>Anuttaro purisadammasārathi</u></b> \n\n<i>an incomparable guide of beings suitable for harnessing</i> \n\n<b><u>Satthā devamanussānaṃ buddho bhagavāti</u></b> \n\n<i>teacher of gods and people, comprehended, blessed.</i>   \n \n\n        <u>QUALITIES OF DHAMMA</u> \n\n<b><u>Svākkhāto bhagavatā dhammo</u></b> \n\n<i>The Blessed Dhamma is well explained, </i> \n\n<b><u>Sandiṭṭhiko akāliko ehipassiko</u></b> \n\n<i> visible directly, not requiring time, inviting you to come and see,</i> \n\n<b><u>Opanayiko paccattaṃ veditabbo viññūhīti</u></b> \n\n<i>leading to the goal, can be independently tested by the wise.</i>     \n \n\n        <u>SANGKHA QUALITIES</u> \n\n<b><u>Supaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>The community (Sangha) of the Blessed One\'s disciples has embarked on a good path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Ujupaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>the community of the Blessed One\'s disciples has entered the straight path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Ñāyapaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>the community of the Blessed One\'s disciples has embarked on the right path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Sāmīcipaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>the community of the Blessed One\'s disciples has entered the proper path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Yadidaṃ cattāri purisayugāni aṭṭha purisapuggalā</u></b> \n\n<i>namely, four pairs, eight types of personalities.</i> \n\n<b><u>Esa bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>This is a community of disciples of the Blessed One</i> \n\n<b><u>Āhuṇeyyo pāhuṇeyyo dakkhiṇeyyo añjalikaraṇīyo</u></b> \n\n<i> deserves gifts, deserves hospitality, deserves offerings, deserves a respectful greeting,</i> \n\n<b><u>Anuttaraṃ puññakkhettaṃ lokassati</u></b> \n\n<i>an incomparable field of merit for the world.</i> \n \n\n        <u>HOMAGE TO MONUMENTS</u> \n\n<b><u>Vandāmi cetiyaṃ sabbaṃ - sabbaṭṭhānesu patiṭṭhitaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>I honor all monuments in all places where they are installed, </i> \n\n<b><u>Sārīrikadhātu mahābodhiṃ - buddharūpaṃ sakalaṃ sadā</u></b> \n\n<i>relics, the Bodhi tree, I always revere all the images of the Buddha.</i> \n \n\n        <u>PAYING HOMAGE TO THE BODHI TREE</u> \n\n<b><u>Yassamūle nisinnova - sabbārivijayaṃ akā</u></b> \n\n<i>Sitting at the foot of which defeated all the enemies</i> \n\n<b><u>Patto sabbaññutaṃ satthā - vande taṃ bodhipādapaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>and our teacher gained omniscience - it is the very Bodhi tree that I revere.</i> \n\n<b><u>Ime ete mahābodhī - lokanāthena pūjitā</u></b> \n\n<i>These are the greatest Bodhi trees, revered by the protector of the world (Buddha), </i> \n\n<b><u>Ahampi te namassāmi - bodhirājā namatthu te</u></b> \n\n<i>I will also welcome you. My respects to the great Bodhi tree!</i> \n \n\n        <u>FORGIVENESS OF SHORTCOMINGS</u> \n\n<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>[If] my body, speech or thoughts were committed by me due to carelessness</i> \n\n<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me bhante - bhūripañña tathāgata</u></b> \n\n<i>offense - forgive me, venerable, deep-wise Tathagata.</i> \n\n<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>[If] my body, speech or thoughts were committed by me due to carelessness</i> \n\n<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me dhamma - sandiṭṭhika akālika</u></b> \n\n<i>offense - forgive me Dhamma, visible directly, does not require time.</i> \n\n<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>[If] my body, speech or thoughts were committed by me due to carelessness</i> \n\n<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me saṅgha supaṭipanna anuttara</u></b> \n\n<i>offense - forgive me the Sangha, who has entered on a good path, incomparable.</i> \n \n\n        <u>INVITATION OF THE DEVAS TO REJOICE</u> \n\n<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n\n<i>May the mighty deities and nagas who live on earth and in the sky</i> \n\n<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu lokasāsanaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>rejoicing in this boon, they defend the system [of the Buddha] in this world for a long time.</i> \n\n<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n\n<i>May the mighty deities and nagas who live on earth and in the sky</i> \n\n<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu desanaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>rejoicing in this boon, they defend the instruction of [the Buddha] for a long time.</i> \n\n<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n\n<i>May the mighty deities and nagas who live on earth and in the sky</i> \n\n<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu maṃ paraṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>rejoicing in this boon, they protect me and others for a long time.</i> \n \n\n        <u>DIVISION OF MERIT</u> \n\n<b><u>idaṃ no (me) ñātīnaṃ hotu - sukhitā hontu ñātayo [3x]</u></b> \n\n<i>Let it go to the benefit of our (my) relatives, let the relatives be happy.</i></string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaKaraniyaMettaSutta"><b>KARANIA METTA SUTTA</b>\n \n\n<b><u />Karaṇīyamatthakusalena, yanta santaṃ padaṃ abhisamecca;</b>\n \n\n<i>This is what one should do who is skilled in good things and wants to achieve a peaceful state:</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Sakko ujū ca suhujū [sūjū (sī.)] ca, sūvaco cassa mudu anatimānī.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let him be able, direct and honest, meek, gentle and not proud,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Santussako ca subharo ca, appakicco ca sallahukavutti;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>satisfied and unburdensome, with few responsibilities, content with little,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Santindriyo ca nipako ca, appagabbho kulesvananugiddho.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>with calm perception abilities, reasonable, humble, and not fawning over families.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Na ca khuddamācare kiñci, yena viññū pare upavadeyyuṃ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>And let him not do the slightest thing that the wise would condemn.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Sukhino va khemino hontu, sabbasattā [sabbe sattā (sī. syā.)] bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>[And let him think:] Joyful and safe, may all beings be joyful in heart.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Ye keci pāṇabhūtatthi, tasā vā thāvarā vanavasesā;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Whatever the creatures, fragile or strong, without exception,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Dīghā vā ye va mahantā [mahanta (?)], majjhimā rassakā aṇukathūlā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>long, large, medium, small, small, thick,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Diṭṭhā vā ye va adiṭṭhā [adiṭṭha (?)], ye va [ye ca (sī. syā. kaṃ. pī.)] dūre vasanti avidūre;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>visible and invisible, living near and far,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Bhūtā va sambhavesī va [bhūtā vā sambhavesī vā (syā. kaṃ. pī. ka.)], sabbasattā bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>those who have come into the world and strive for manifestation: may all beings be joyful in heart.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Na paro paraṃ nikubbetha, nātimaññetha katthaci na kañci [naṃ kañci (sī. pī.), naṃ kiñci (syā.), na kiñci (ka.)] ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let no one upset another or despise anyone anywhere,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Byārosanā paṭighasaññā, nāññamaññassa dukkhamiccheyya.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>and let no one wish another to suffer because of anger or an unpleasant impression.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mātā yathā niyaṃ puttamāyusā ekaputtamanurakkhe;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>As a mother, at the cost of her life, is ready to protect her child, her only child,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Evampi sabbabhūtesu, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>so without restrictions to all beings he should develop this thought.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mettañca sabbalokasmi, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>For the whole world, let it develop the boundless thought of friendliness:</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Uddhaṃ adho ca tiriyañca, asambādhaṃ averamasapattaṃ.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Up, down, and in between, without obstruction, malevolence, or foe.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Tiṭṭhaṃ caraṃ nisinno va, sayāno yāvatāssa vitamiddho [vigatamiddo (bahūsu)] ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Standing, walking, sitting or lying down while not drowsy</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Etaṃ satiṃ adhiṭṭheyya, brahmametaṃ vihāramidhamāhu.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let him strive for this remembrance. It is spoken of as being in the state of brahma [straight] here</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Diṭṭhiñca anupagamma, sīlavā dassanena sampanno;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Not confused with views, moral, he has insight,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Kāmesu vinaya gedhaṃ, na hi jātuggabbhaseyya punaretīti.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>With the elimination of greed for sensual pleasures, he will never again be in the womb.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mettasuttaṃ aṭṭhamaṃ niṭṭhitaṃ.</u></b></string>
    <string name="rukovodstvo_dlya_samaner">guide for samaneras</string>
    <string name="sekhiya_n">sekhiya rules for training</string>
    <string name="first_category">Category one 26 sekhiya on proper behavior:</string>
    <string name="clothing_wrapped_around_body">1-2.\nI will wear the lower garment [upper garment] wrapped around the body \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="sit_in_wheel_clothing">3-4.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] well covered \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="sit_strong">5-6.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] well restrained\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="eyes_looking_doun">7-8.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] with my eyes down \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="dont_up_clothes">9-10.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my robes pulled\nup — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="laughing_noisily">11-12.\n In a populated area, I won\'t walk [sit] laughing out loud \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="speak_noisily">13-14.\n In a populated area, I will walk [sit], talking in a lowered voice\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_body">15-16.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] rocking my body \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_urms">17-18.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk [sit], swinging my arms \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_head">19-20.\n In a populated area, I will walk [sit], shaking my head\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="hands_on_sides">21-22.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my hands on my hips \n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="covered_head">23-24.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my head covered \n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="walc_on_heels">25.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk only on my toes or on my heels \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="hugging_knees">26.\nIn a populated area, I will not sit with my knees clasped \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="pabaja_text">stanzas for ceremony becoming a samanera \n pabbajja</string>
</resources>