<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="mainButtonLiveBuddha">The Life of the Buddha</string>
    <string name="mainButtonStofiDlyaDeclomacii">Stanzas for recitation</string>
    <string name="mainButtonShortSuttas">A model of Buddhist Path practice</string>
    <string name="mainButtonMonksRules">Monastic rules</string>
    <string name="namerenie_sumedhi">1. Sumedha\'s Intention</string>
    <string name="son_mahamayi">2. Mahamaya\'s Dream</string>
    <string name="rogdenie_sidharthi">3. The Birth of Siddhartha</string>
    <string name="mudrec_asita">4. Sage Asita</string>
    <string name="pervoe_dostigenie_dgani">5. The first achievement of jhana</string>
    <string name="spasenie_lebedya">6. Saving the swan</string>
    <string name="demonstraciya_umenii">7. Demonstration of skills</string>
    <string name="sumedha">The first picture is a kind of prequel, the action takes place long before when\n         Siddhartha was born when a man named Sumedha set out to become a Bodhisattva\n         i.e. those who, over an unimaginably long period of time, improve their qualities\n         allowing in the last birth to become a Buddha who awakens independently at four\n         truth and unsurpassed teaches them to people and devas.\n \n\n\n         The figure depicts the Buddha Dipankara, accompanied by four hundred thousand Arhats,\n         going to the city of Ranma at the invitation of the townspeople to accept gifts, as well as a brahmin\n         Sumedha the bodhisattva vower prostrating himself before the Buddha.\n \n\n\n         Buddha Dipankara (lit. One who makes oil lamps, or giving light to the lamp) is a Tathagata who lived four Immeasurable Kalpas and a hundred thousand eons ago. The first Buddha of the twenty-four Tathagatas of the past, which Buddha Shakyamuni told his students about.\n         During the time of Buddha Dipankara, the future Buddha Shakyamuni reincarnated as the Brahmin Sumedha. Once he thought about the vicissitudes of reincarnation, about suffering, about old age and illness. His thoughts led to the decision to engage in ascetic practice in order to find a way to free himself from the shackles of rebirth. During this period, the fame of the Conqueror in Truth, Buddha Dipankara, began to spread in the world.\n         While visiting the city (Ramma), Sumedha saw people preparing the road for the visit of Buddha Dipankara. They told Sumedha that they were clearing the way for the Buddha, who had attained perfect Awakening, to pass. Wandering with a large community of disciples, Dipankara arrived in their city and stayed nearby in the monastery of Sudassana. The inhabitants of the city invited the Buddha and are now preparing the road along which he must pass.\n         When he learned about the appearance of the Buddha in this world, Sumedha was overwhelmed with supreme joy. He asked people to give him a section of the road so that he could take part in its preparation. He was given a section of the road with earth soggy with water, and then he began to drain it, thinking about the Buddha.\n         But before the road was fully prepared, the great sage Dipankara appeared, surrounded by four hundred thousand liberated ones. The ascetic Sumedha, seeing the Most Honored One, exclaimed:\n         Let the Buddha not step on the dirt, but together with his disciples, walk over me for my benefit.\n         Having loosened his long ascetic hair and covered the ground with it, Sumedha lay down on that muddy section of the road. And at that time Sumedha had these thoughts:\n         If I wanted to, I could enter the city of Ranmu as a newly converted monk who had destroyed all mental defilements. But I should not hide by achieving nibbana with the destruction of mental defilements. Instead, I should, like Dipankara, realize perfect Realization, and, boarding the ship of Dhamma, ferry many people across the ocean of samsara, and only then realize [ultimate] nibbana - that\'s what I should do. Then, after listing the eight conditions (required to achieve Buddhahood) and firmly determined to become a Buddha, he lay down.\n         When Dipankara approached Sumedha, he uttered a prophecy:\n         This person lying here has decided to become a Buddha, his wish will be fulfilled, after four asankhyas and one hundred thousand cycles, he will become a Buddha named Gotama. And in that life, his place of residence will be the city of Kapilavatthu, his mother will be Queen Maya, Raja Suddhodana will be his father, his main student will be the senior monk Upatissa, the second student will be the senior monk Kolita, the personal assistant of the Buddha will be Ananda, his main student will be the nun Khema , the second student will be the nun Uppalavanna. When he reaches the age of mature knowledge, he will renounce the world and make great effort.\n         Having received rice porridge at the foot of the banyan and eating it on the banks of the Neranjara River, he will then sit on a seat under the bodhi tree, after which he will attain Buddhahood at the foot of the fig tree [Bodhi].\n\n         In iconography, Dipankara is represented as a standing or seated Buddha.\n \n\n         Images where Dipankara stands are common in China, Thailand and Nepal.\n \n\n         It is believed that one of the Buddha statues in Bamiyan (Afghanistan), destroyed by the Taliban in 2001, depicted the standing Buddha Dipankara.\n \n\n         Sometimes Buddha Shakyamuni and Buddha Maitreya are depicted next to him. In this case, Dipankara (Buddha of the past), Shakyamuni (Buddha of the present) and Maitreya (Buddha of the future) symbolize together the Buddhas of the three times.</string>
    <string name="mahamaya">The picture depicts a dream that Mahamaya has, foreshadowing that she will give birth to a great man. \n \n\n Mahamaya, the wife of Raja Shuddhodana, Siddhartha\'s mother, was a princess from the kingdom of Koliyas. \n\nAfter the meeting of the brahman Sumedha with the Buddha Deepankara, during which Sumedha took bodhisattva vows, an incalculable number of years passed, during which the Bodhisattva developed the qualities necessary for enlightenment as a Sammasambudda. Before entering his last birth, the Bodhisattva arrived in the world of the Tusita (Contented), when the so-called Proclamation about the Buddha appeared in this world, the Devas of all ten thousand world systems gathered there together with their rulers, addressing the Bodhisattva as follows: Sir, when you developed the ten perfections, you did not do it for in order to take the place of Sakka, Mara, Brahma or the king of the world; you developed them in order to achieve omniscience in order to cross to the other side of the world! The time has come, sir, for Buddhahood, now, sir, that time has come!. But the Bodhisatta, as if the deities were not appealing to him, was thinking about five important issues in the following sequence, namely: time; country; family; mother and the duration of her life. \n\nAnd at first he thought about time, thinking: Is this the right time or not? And on this issue he thought: When life expectancy increases to a hundred thousand years, this is not the right time. Why? Because with such a long life, a person does not feel that living beings are subject to birth, old age and death, and when Buddhas talk about impermanence, dissatisfaction and impersonality, people do not listen and do not believe them, thinking: What are they talking about?. At such a time there can be no understanding, and without this, the teaching does not lead [to the goal]. That\'s why this is the wrong time. Also, the time when the life expectancy is less than a hundred years is not suitable. And why? Because when the evil between people increases, a remark addressed to vicious people cannot stand, like a twig that has fallen into a river. Therefore, such a time is also inappropriate. But when the life expectancy is less than a hundred thousand years, but more than a hundred years, then this is the right time. \n\nThen, thinking about which country is necessary for his birth and considering the four great continents with the islands surrounding them, he realized that Buddhas are not born on three continents, but they are born in Jambudip and so he made a decision about the country.\nThen reflecting on the family he thought: Buddhas are not born either in the Vaishya caste or in the Sudra caste - they are born either in the brahman caste or in the kshatriya caste, depending on which of these castes currently has the highest position. The kshatriya caste is higher now, I have to be born in it and Raja Suddhodana will be my father. So he decided on a family. \n\nReflecting on the question of his mother, he thought: The Buddha\'s mother cannot be lustful or a drinker, she developed Perfection for a hundred thousand cycles and from the moment of birth strictly observed the Five Rules. Queen Maha Maya is exactly like that, she will be my mother. Further reflecting on how long her life would last, he realized that her life would last ten months and seven days. \n\nHaving received answers to the five most important questions, he graciously agreed with the deities, saying: Gentlemen, it\'s time for me to become a Buddha.\nMeanwhile, a Midsummer festival was announced in the city of Kapilavatthu and a large number of people were having fun at the festival. For seven days before the full moon, Queen Maha Maya participated in the festival. On the seventh day, she got up early, washed her face and arranged a huge handout with a total value of four hundred thousand. Wearing her richest outfit, she took food. Rushing to the factors of the day of special prescriptions, she went into her room, lay down on the royal bed and when she fell asleep, she had a dream about a big white elephant approaching her, holding a white lotus flower in its silver trunk and making a mighty sound that resounded everywhere, he respectfully walked around Mahamaya\'s bed three times and entered her womb. \n\n\nWaking up the next day, the queen told her dream to the rajah. Sixty-four brahmanas were called, the raja told them the dream of the queen and asked: What does this portend? \n\nThe brahmanas said: Don\'t worry, great ruler! Your spouse conceived and in her womb is a boy, not a girl. You\'re going to have a son. And if he prefers the worldly life, he will become the king of the world, but if, after leaving home, he prefers the life of a hermit, he will become a Buddha and in this world he will tear off the veil [of passion, disgust, etc.].</string>
    <string name="birdth">The picture shows the last birth of a Bodhisattva. \n \n\n            According to legend, many miracles are associated with the birth of a Bodhisattva, some of them are described in the Buddhist canon of Tripitaka. \n \n\nHere is an excerpt from the Mahapadan Sutta Dn14: \n \n\n\"It is the law, bhikkhus, that while other women carry a child for nine or ten months before childbirth begins, in the case of a Bodhisattva, it is not so – his mother carries him for exactly ten months before childbirth begins. \n\nIt is the law, bhikkhus, that while other women give birth sitting or lying down, in the case of a Bodhisattva it is not so – his mother gives birth standing up. \n\nThis is the law, monks, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, the devas greet him first, and then people. \n\nIt is the law, bhikkhus, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, he does not touch the ground. Four devas pick it up and hand it to the mother, saying: \"Rejoice, Your Majesty, you have the greatest son!\". \n\nThis is the law, monks, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, he appears untainted by water, mucus, blood or any impurities – he is pure and flawless. If a gemstone is put on a muslin from Kasi, then the stone does not pollute the muslin, and the muslin does not pollute the stone. Why? Because both the fabric and the gemstone are clean. Similarly, a Bodhisattva comes out of his mother\'s womb untainted by water, mucus, blood or any impurities – he is pure and flawless. \n\nThis is the law, bhikkhus, that when a Bodhisattva comes out of the womb of his mother, two streams of water gush from heaven – one cold, the other warm, washing the Bodhisattva and his mother. \n\nSuch is the law, monks, that as soon as a Bodhisattva is born, he stands firmly on his feet and takes seven steps to the north, and then, under a white canopy (from the sun), he covers all four sides with his gaze and declares in a loud voice: \"I am the greatest in this world, the highest in the world, the first in the world. This is my last birth, there will be no more new rebirths.\" \n\nThis is the law, monks, that when a Bodhisatta comes out of the womb of the mother, then in this world with its devas, Maras and Brahmas, its ascetics and priests, kings and commoners, there is an immeasurable dazzling light that eclipses the radiance of the most majestic deities.\" \n \n\n\nAnd so the queen Maha Maya, for 10 months carefully carrying the Bodhisattva in her womb,\n            I realized that childbirth was approaching and wished to do it at home, in my family.\n            She went to Raja Suddhodana and said, Your Majesty, I want to go to Devadaha, the city of my relatives.\n            The Raja agreed and ordered to level the road from Kapilavatthu to Devadaha, and seated the queen in a golden palanquin,\n            carried by a thousand servants, he dismissed her with a large retinue. \n\nBetween the two cities there is a tallow grove for recreation, owned by residents of both cities and this grove is called Lumbini.\n            The whole Lumbini grove looked like a forest full of colorful vines or like a well-decorated reception hall of some\n            a powerful ruler. The queen was filled with a desire to stay in a grove of tallow trees and the servants carried her into the grove.\n            When she came to the foot of the royal tallow tree, she wanted to take hold of its branch and stretch out her hand,\n            she took hold of a branch and then the kamma-born winds shook her. The servants, having unfolded the veil around the queen, moved aside.\n            Standing and holding on to a branch of a tallow tree, she gave birth.Just at that moment, the four great brahmas came there,\n            having brought a golden net, they accepted the future Buddha on it. Then they put it in front of the mother, saying:\n            Rejoice, Queen! You have given birth to a powerful son!. From their hands, the Bodhisattva was accepted by people on a bundle\n            After leaving their hands, the Bodhisattva stood on the ground and looked to the east.\n            Thousands of world systems became visible to him as one open space.\n            Searching in ten directions and not finding anyone like himself, he took seven big steps, saying:\n            This is the best direction. Then, stopping at the seventh step, showing his majestic voice, he said with a lion\'s roar:\n            \"I am the greatest in this world, the highest in the world, the first in the world. This is my last birth, there will be no more new rebirths.\"</string>
    <string name="asita">In the drawing of Raja Suddhodan, Siddhardha\'s father shows his son to sage Asita. \n \n\n\"Asita: Sage and spiritual mentor of Sihahanu, Suddhodana\'s father. He was Suddhodana\'s teacher and later became his spiritual mentor. He came morning and evening to visit King Suddhodana, who showed him great respect even when he was his disciple.\"\nAccording to the Buddhaghosa (SnA.ii.483), Asita got his name because of his dark skin. He also had another name - Kanha Devala (SnA.ii.487). He was also called Kanha Siri (Sn.v.689) or Siri Kanha (SnA.487) or Kala Devala (J.I.54). He should obviously be distinguished from Asita Devala, who was also called Kala Devala.\nAfter the death of King Sihahanu, Asita left the worldly life. After some time, he developed various superpowers, and since then he has spent all day in the deva worlds. One day, while staying in Tavatims, he saw the whole city decorated, and the gods rejoiced. From them he learned that Siddhattha Gotama, the future Buddha, was to be born. He immediately went to King Suddhodana and asked to see the child.  \"I heard you had a son, O great Raja! Let me see him.\"\nThe Raja ordered his son to be dressed and brought so that he would bow to the sage.\nBut the future Buddha unfolded his feet and placed them on the tangled hair of the sage. It is noted that a Bodhisattva cannot worship anyone, and if the child\'s head touched the ascetic\'s feet, his head would split. The sage got up from his seat, saying: It would be wrong for me to follow the path of self-destruction, and he bowed to the Bodhisattva. And the rajah, seeing such a miracle, also bowed to his own son.\nLooking at the signs of future greatness on the Bodhisattva\'s body, he wondered: \"Will this baby become a Buddha or not?\". And it was revealed to the sage that the raja\'s son would definitely become a Buddha. Smiling, he said, \"What an amazing person.\" Then he thought, \"Will it be given to me to see him when he becomes a Buddha?\". And it was revealed to him that no. \"If I die before this happens, I will be reborn in a formless world; so at a time when hundreds, and possibly thousands of Buddhas appeared among people, I cannot become a disciple of one of them. And I won\'t be lucky enough to see this amazing man when he becomes a Buddha. Alas, my loss is great!\" And he began to cry. People who saw this asked: \"Our teacher was just smiling, and now he started crying! Tell me, venerable one, will any misfortune happen to our master\'s son?\".\n\"He\'s fine, he will definitely become a Buddha,\" was the answer.\n\"Then why are you crying?\"\n\"It will not be given to me,\" the sage replied, \"to see such a great man when he becomes a Buddha. Alas! Great is my loss! Feeling sorry for myself, I cry.\"\nThen he asked himself, \"Will it be given to any of my relatives to see him as a Buddha?\". And Asita discovered that his nephew, the boy Nalaki, would have such an opportunity. He went to his sister and asked her, \"Where is your son Nalaka?\".\n\"In the house, brother.\"\n\"Call him.\" When the nephew came up, Asita told him: \"A son, the future Buddha, was born in the family of Raja Suddhodana. He will become a Buddha at the age of thirty-five and you will be given to see him. Leave the worldly life today!\".\nKnowing that his uncle would not give instructions without a special reason, the young man, although he was born into a family with great wealth, immediately took yellow clothes and a clay alms vessel from the pantry, shaved his head and changed clothes. Having said: \"I am leaving the worldly life for the greatest man on earth,\" he folded his hands in a gesture of respect, bowed \"in five parts\" in the direction of the Bodhisattva. Then, putting the begging vessel in a bag and hanging the bag on his shoulder, he headed to the Himalayas, where he began to live as a hermit.\nWhen the Tathagata reached the highest Realization, Nalaka went to him and learned about the way of salvation. Nalaka then returned to the Himalayas and attained arhatship. After that, he lived for another seven months. Nalaka died, standing near the Golden Hill, by the final liberation without a trace.</string>
    <string name="pudja">Vandana</string>
    <string name="sutta">Sutta</string>
    <string name="drugie_declomacii">Other recitations</string>
    <string name="button_karaniya_metta">Karania metta sutta</string>
    <string name="utrennaia_pudga">Morning Vandana in Chittaviveka</string>
    <string name="decl_pered_priemom_pichi">recitation before meals</string>
    <string name="prosba_o_prochenii_nedostatkov">A request for forgiveness of shortcomings in front of senior monks</string>
    <string name="blagopogelaniya_pri_vzyatii_pichi">Well -wishes to the laity at the taking are given</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaPeredPrinyatiemPichi">" <b>RECITATION BEFORE LUNCH</b>\n \n <b><u>Paṭisaṅkhā yoniso piṇḍapātaṁ paṭisevāmi,</u></b>\n \n <i>Having thoughtfully considered this, I eat the food presented to me </i>  \n   \n <b><u>N’eva davāya na madāya na maṇḍanāya na vibhūsanāya,</u></b>\n  \n <i>Not for entertainment, not for intoxication, not for weight gain, not to be beautiful,</i> \n    \n <b><u>Yāvadeva imassa kāyassa ṭhitiyā yāpanāya vihiṁsuparatiyā brahma-cariyānuggahāya,</u></b>\n   \n <i>But just for survival, for the support of this body, for the cessation of its suffering, for the support of a holy life,</i> \n  \n <b><u>Iti purāṇañ-ca vedanaṁ paṭihaṅkhāmi navañ-ca vedanaṁ na uppādessāmi,</u></b>\n   \n <i> “This way I will destroy the old feeling of hunger and will not create new feelings from overeating.”</i>  \n \n <b><u>Yātrā ca me bhavissati anavajjatā ca phāsu-vihāro cāti.</u></b>  \n <i>I will try to be perfect</i>"</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaForgivennes">\n        <b>A REQUEST FOR FORGIVENESS OF SHORTCOMINGS IN FRONT OF SENIOR MONKS</b> \n \n \n\n<b><u>Okāsa vandāmi Bhante. Sabbam accayam kamatha me bhante.</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Allow me to honor you, venerable one. Forgive me all the mistakes, my dear.</i> \n \n\n <b><u>Mayākataṁ puññaṁ, sāminā anumodi tabbaṁ.</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Please, Bhante, let me share with you the merits that I have acquired.</i> \n \n\n<i>(Bhantes: Sādhu, Sādhu, anumodāmi! Okay, okay, I\'m happy!)</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Saminā kataṁ puññaṁ, mayhaṁ dātabbaṁ</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Please, Bhante, share with me the merits that you have acquired.</i> \n \n\n<i>(Bhantes: Sādhu, Sādhu, anumodetha! Okay, okay, I\'m happy!)</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Sādhu, Sādhu anumodāmi!</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Okay, okay, I appreciate it!</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Okāsa! Dvārattena kataṁ sabbaṁ accayaṁ khamatha me Bhante.</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Forgive me, O Bhante, for any mistakes I may have made in body, speech or mind.</i> \n \n\n<i>(Bhantes: Kamāmi kamitabbaṁ. I forgive.)</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Sadhu Okāsa khamāmi Bhante!</u></b> \n \n\n<i>I beg your pardon, O Bhanta.</i></string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaAlmsWish">"\n        <b>WELL -WISHES TO THE LAITY AT THE TAKING ARE GIVEN</b> \n \n \n\n        <u>OPTION 1</u> \n\n<b><u>Abhivadana silasa, niccam vuddhapacayino</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Constantly expressing respect for morality and those who should be honored</i> \n \n\n<b><u>Cattaro dhamma vaddhanti, ayu vanno sukham balam</u></b> \n \n\n<i>Let the four dhammas increase: longevity, success, well-being, health</i> "</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaMorningPuja"><b>MORNING VANDANA</b> \n \n \n\n        <u>EXPRESSION OF RESPECT</u> \n\n<b><u>Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambuddhassa [3x]</u></b> \n\n<i>Reverence to the Blessed, worthy, comprehended in perfection.</i> \n \n\n        <u>APPEAL TO THE BUDDHA</u> \n\n<b><u>Ni`vedaya`mi sambuddham</u></b> \n\n<i>I appeal to Samasambudda</i> \n\n<b><u>Vi`tara`gam maha`munim</u></b> \n\n<i>To the great sage who destroyed passion</i> \n\n<b><u>Ni`mantaya`mi sugatam</u></b> \n\n<i>I appeal to Sugatta</i> \n\n<b><u>Lokajettham nara`sabam</u></b> \n\n<i>To the winner of the World, the highest of men</i> \n \n\n        <u>OFFERING OF LIGHT</u> \n\n<b><u>Ghanasārappadittena - dīpena tamadhaṃsinā</u></b> \n\n<i>By the light of flaming camphor, eliminating darkness</i> \n\n<b><u>Tilokadīpaṃ sambuddhaṃ - pūjayāmi tamonudaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>I pay my respects to the enlightener of the three worlds, who has comprehended and dispels darkness (ignorance).</i> \n \n\n        <u>OFFERING INCENSE</u> \n\n<b><u>sugandhikāya vadanaṃ - ananta guṇa gandhinaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>The one whose body and face are fragrant, from whom comes the smell of countless good qualities, </i> \n\n<b><u>sugandhināhaṃ gandhena - pūjayāmi tathāgataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i> I offer these incense - Tathagata.</i> \n \n\n        <u>FLOWER OFFERINGS</u> \n\n<b><u>Vaṇṇagandhaguṇopetaṃ - etaṃ kusumasantatiṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>Having beauty and a pleasant smell of this scattering of flowers,</i> \n\n<b><u>Pūjayāmi munindassa - sirīpādasaroruhe</u></b> \n\n<i>I bring the Supreme Sage to the lotus feet.</i> \n\n<b><u>Pūjemi buddhaṃ kusumenanena – puññena metena labhami mokkhaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>I honor the Buddha with these flowers (kusumena+anena), may I gain liberation through this boon.</i> \n\n<b><u>Pupphaṃ milāyāti yathā idamme - kāyo tathā yāti vināsabhāvaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>As these flowers wither, so this body of mine is subject to destruction.</i> \n \n\n        <u>OFFERING OF OTHER DISHES</u> \n\n<b><u>adhivāsetu no bhante - sabbaṃ saddhāya pūjitaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>Venerable one, show mercy to everything presented on the basis of trust to you</i> \n\n<b><u>anukampaṃ upādāya - patigaṇhātumuttamaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>accept, O greatest one, out of compassion for us.</i>    \n \n\n        <u>QUALITIES OF A BUDDHA</u> \n\n<b><u>Itipi so bhagavā arahaṃ sammāsambuddho</u></b> \n\n<i>The Blessed One really is like this: he is worthy, who has comprehended in perfection,</i> \n\n<b><u>Vijjācaraṇasampanno sugato lokavidū</u></b> \n\n<i>having knowledge and [good] behavior, having achieved the good, a connoisseur of the world,</i> \n\n<b><u>Anuttaro purisadammasārathi</u></b> \n\n<i>an incomparable guide of beings suitable for harnessing</i> \n\n<b><u>Satthā devamanussānaṃ buddho bhagavāti</u></b> \n\n<i>teacher of gods and people, comprehended, blessed.</i>   \n \n\n        <u>QUALITIES OF DHAMMA</u> \n\n<b><u>Svākkhāto bhagavatā dhammo</u></b> \n\n<i>The Blessed Dhamma is well explained, </i> \n\n<b><u>Sandiṭṭhiko akāliko ehipassiko</u></b> \n\n<i> visible directly, not requiring time, inviting you to come and see,</i> \n\n<b><u>Opanayiko paccattaṃ veditabbo viññūhīti</u></b> \n\n<i>leading to the goal, can be independently tested by the wise.</i>     \n \n\n        <u>SANGKHA QUALITIES</u> \n\n<b><u>Supaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>The community (Sangha) of the Blessed One\'s disciples has embarked on a good path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Ujupaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>the community of the Blessed One\'s disciples has entered the straight path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Ñāyapaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>the community of the Blessed One\'s disciples has embarked on the right path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Sāmīcipaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>the community of the Blessed One\'s disciples has entered the proper path,</i> \n\n<b><u>Yadidaṃ cattāri purisayugāni aṭṭha purisapuggalā</u></b> \n\n<i>namely, four pairs, eight types of personalities.</i> \n\n<b><u>Esa bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n\n<i>This is a community of disciples of the Blessed One</i> \n\n<b><u>Āhuṇeyyo pāhuṇeyyo dakkhiṇeyyo añjalikaraṇīyo</u></b> \n\n<i> deserves gifts, deserves hospitality, deserves offerings, deserves a respectful greeting,</i> \n\n<b><u>Anuttaraṃ puññakkhettaṃ lokassati</u></b> \n\n<i>an incomparable field of merit for the world.</i> \n \n\n        <u>HOMAGE TO MONUMENTS</u> \n\n<b><u>Vandāmi cetiyaṃ sabbaṃ - sabbaṭṭhānesu patiṭṭhitaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>I honor all monuments in all places where they are installed, </i> \n\n<b><u>Sārīrikadhātu mahābodhiṃ - buddharūpaṃ sakalaṃ sadā</u></b> \n\n<i>relics, the Bodhi tree, I always revere all the images of the Buddha.</i> \n \n\n        <u>PAYING HOMAGE TO THE BODHI TREE</u> \n\n<b><u>Yassamūle nisinnova - sabbārivijayaṃ akā</u></b> \n\n<i>Sitting at the foot of which defeated all the enemies</i> \n\n<b><u>Patto sabbaññutaṃ satthā - vande taṃ bodhipādapaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>and our teacher gained omniscience - it is the very Bodhi tree that I revere.</i> \n\n<b><u>Ime ete mahābodhī - lokanāthena pūjitā</u></b> \n\n<i>These are the greatest Bodhi trees, revered by the protector of the world (Buddha), </i> \n\n<b><u>Ahampi te namassāmi - bodhirājā namatthu te</u></b> \n\n<i>I will also welcome you. My respects to the great Bodhi tree!</i> \n \n\n        <u>FORGIVENESS OF SHORTCOMINGS</u> \n\n<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>[If] my body, speech or thoughts were committed by me due to carelessness</i> \n\n<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me bhante - bhūripañña tathāgata</u></b> \n\n<i>offense - forgive me, venerable, deep-wise Tathagata.</i> \n\n<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>[If] my body, speech or thoughts were committed by me due to carelessness</i> \n\n<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me dhamma - sandiṭṭhika akālika</u></b> \n\n<i>offense - forgive me Dhamma, visible directly, does not require time.</i> \n\n<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>[If] my body, speech or thoughts were committed by me due to carelessness</i> \n\n<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me saṅgha supaṭipanna anuttara</u></b> \n\n<i>offense - forgive me the Sangha, who has entered on a good path, incomparable.</i> \n \n\n        <u>INVITATION OF THE DEVAS TO REJOICE</u> \n\n<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n\n<i>May the mighty deities and nagas who live on earth and in the sky</i> \n\n<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu lokasāsanaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>rejoicing in this boon, they defend the system [of the Buddha] in this world for a long time.</i> \n\n<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n\n<i>May the mighty deities and nagas who live on earth and in the sky</i> \n\n<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu desanaṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>rejoicing in this boon, they defend the instruction of [the Buddha] for a long time.</i> \n\n<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n\n<i>May the mighty deities and nagas who live on earth and in the sky</i> \n\n<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu maṃ paraṃ</u></b> \n\n<i>rejoicing in this boon, they protect me and others for a long time.</i> \n \n\n        <u>DIVISION OF MERIT</u> \n\n<b><u>idaṃ no (me) ñātīnaṃ hotu - sukhitā hontu ñātayo [3x]</u></b> \n\n<i>Let it go to the benefit of our (my) relatives, let the relatives be happy.</i></string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaKaraniyaMettaSutta"> \n <b>KARANIA METTA SUTTA</b>\n \n\n<b><u />Karaṇīyamatthakusalena, yanta santaṃ padaṃ abhisamecca;</b>\n \n\n<i>This is what one should do who is skilled in good things and wants to achieve a peaceful state:</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Sakko ujū ca suhujū [sūjū (sī.)] ca, sūvaco cassa mudu anatimānī.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let him be able, direct and honest, meek, gentle and not proud,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Santussako ca subharo ca, appakicco ca sallahukavutti;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>satisfied and unburdensome, with few responsibilities, content with little,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Santindriyo ca nipako ca, appagabbho kulesvananugiddho.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>with calm perception abilities, reasonable, humble, and not fawning over families.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Na ca khuddamācare kiñci, yena viññū pare upavadeyyuṃ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>And let him not do the slightest thing that the wise would condemn.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Sukhino va khemino hontu, sabbasattā [sabbe sattā (sī. syā.)] bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>[And let him think:] Joyful and safe, may all beings be joyful in heart.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Ye keci pāṇabhūtatthi, tasā vā thāvarā vanavasesā;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Whatever the creatures, fragile or strong, without exception,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Dīghā vā ye va mahantā [mahanta (?)], majjhimā rassakā aṇukathūlā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>long, large, medium, small, small, thick,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Diṭṭhā vā ye va adiṭṭhā [adiṭṭha (?)], ye va [ye ca (sī. syā. kaṃ. pī.)] dūre vasanti avidūre;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>visible and invisible, living near and far,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Bhūtā va sambhavesī va [bhūtā vā sambhavesī vā (syā. kaṃ. pī. ka.)], sabbasattā bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>those who have come into the world and strive for manifestation: may all beings be joyful in heart.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Na paro paraṃ nikubbetha, nātimaññetha katthaci na kañci [naṃ kañci (sī. pī.), naṃ kiñci (syā.), na kiñci (ka.)] ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let no one upset another or despise anyone anywhere,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Byārosanā paṭighasaññā, nāññamaññassa dukkhamiccheyya.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>and let no one wish another to suffer because of anger or an unpleasant impression.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mātā yathā niyaṃ puttamāyusā ekaputtamanurakkhe;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>As a mother, at the cost of her life, is ready to protect her child, her only child,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Evampi sabbabhūtesu, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>so without restrictions to all beings he should develop this thought.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mettañca sabbalokasmi, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>For the whole world, let it develop the boundless thought of friendliness:</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Uddhaṃ adho ca tiriyañca, asambādhaṃ averamasapattaṃ.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Up, down, and in between, without obstruction, malevolence, or foe.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Tiṭṭhaṃ caraṃ nisinno va, sayāno yāvatāssa vitamiddho [vigatamiddo (bahūsu)] ;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Standing, walking, sitting or lying down while not drowsy</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Etaṃ satiṃ adhiṭṭheyya, brahmametaṃ vihāramidhamāhu.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Let him strive for this remembrance. It is spoken of as being in the state of brahma [straight] here</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Diṭṭhiñca anupagamma, sīlavā dassanena sampanno;</u></b>\n \n\n<i>Not confused with views, moral, he has insight,</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Kāmesu vinaya gedhaṃ, na hi jātuggabbhaseyya punaretīti.</u></b>\n \n\n<i>With the elimination of greed for sensual pleasures, he will never again be in the womb.</i>\n \n\n<b><u>Mettasuttaṃ aṭṭhamaṃ niṭṭhitaṃ. \n \n \n \n \n \n</u></b></string>
    <string name="rukovodstvo_dlya_samaner">guide for samanera</string>
    <string name="sekhiya_n">75 sekhiya \n rules for training</string>
    <string name="first_category">Category one \n26 sekhiya on proper behavior:</string>
    <string name="clothing_wrapped_around_body">1-2.\nI will wear the lower garment [upper garment] wrapped around the body \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="sit_in_wheel_clothing">3-4.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] well covered \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="sit_strong">5-6.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] well restrained\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="eyes_looking_doun">7-8.\nIn a populated area, I will walk [sit] with my eyes down \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="dont_up_clothes">9-10.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my robes pulled\nup — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="laughing_noisily">11-12.\n In a populated area, I won\'t walk [sit] laughing out loud \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="speak_noisily">13-14.\n In a populated area, I will walk [sit], talking in a lowered voice\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_body">15-16.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] rocking my body \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_urms">17-18.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk [sit], swinging my arms \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="uncoiling_the_head">19-20.\n In a populated area, I will walk [sit], shaking my head\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="hands_on_sides">21-22.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my hands on my hips \n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="covered_head">23-24.\n In a populated area, I will not walk [sit] with my head covered \n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="walc_on_heels">25.\nIn a populated area, I will not walk only on my toes or on my heels \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="hugging_knees">26.\nIn a populated area, I will not sit with my knees clasped \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="pabaja_text">pabbajja \n stanzas for ceremony becoming a samanera</string>
    <string name="secondCategory">Category two \n 30 sekkhiy with regards to food:</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_priznatelno">27.\nI will eat alms gratefully\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pishi_vnimanie_na_chashe">28.\nI will take food from alms, keeping my attention on the bowl \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_vnadlegaishey_proporcii">29.\nI will accept alms with bean curry in the proper proportion \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_vroven_skraem_chashi">30.\nI will take food from alms level with the edge of the bowl\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_est_priznatelno">31.\nI will eat food from alms gratefully\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_svnimaniem_nachashu">32.\nI will eat alms food with attention directed to the bowl \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_metodichno">33.\nI will eat alms food methodically \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_karri_vnadleg_proporcii">34.\nI will eat alms food with bean curry in the proper proportion \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_kuski_skuchi">35.\nI will not eat food from alms, taking pieces from the pile \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="priem_pichi_pryatat_karry">36.\nI will not hide bean curry and various types of food under rice out of a desire to get more \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_est_ris_kotor_prosil_za_sebya">37.\nNot being sick, I won\'t eat rice or bean curry that I asked for myself \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="smotret_vchashu_drugogo">38.\nI will not look into the bowl of another in order to find a flaw\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_brat_bolsh_kuski_pishi">39.\nI won\'t take very large chunks of food \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="rovnie_kuski_pishi">40.\nI will form even pieces of food\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="otkrivat_rot">41.\nI will not open my mouth until a piece of food has been brought to it yet \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="zasovivat_ruku">42.\nWhen eating, I will not put a whole hand in my mouth \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="govorit_snabitim_rtom">43.\nI won\'t talk with my mouth full of food \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="podnyatie_komki">44.\nI will not eat from raised lumps of food \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="pokusivat_kuski">45. \n I will not eat by biting pieces of food \n — training for compliance</string>
    <string name="nabivat_shoki">46.\nI will not eat while stuffing my cheeks\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="stryahivat_edu_sruk">47.\nI won\'t eat by shaking food off my hand \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="rasbrasivat_ris">48.\nI will not eat by scattering rice \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="visovivat_yazik">49.\nI will not eat by sticking out my tongue \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="chmokat_gubami">50.\nI won\'t eat by smacking my lips \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="prihlebivayshii_zvuk">51.\nI won\'t eat while making a slurping sound \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="oblizivat_ruki">52.\nI won\'t eat by licking my hands \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="oblizivat_chashu">53.\nI will not eat by licking the bowl \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="oblizivat_gubi">54.\nI won\'t eat while licking my lips \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="brat_sosud_gryaznoi_rukoi">55.\nI will not take a vessel of water with a hand dirty from eating \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="vilivat_vodu_v_naselennoi_mestnosti">56.\nIn a populated area, I will not pour out water to wash the bowl in which the drawings\nare left — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="tretiya_kategoriya_sekhiya">Category three \n 16 sekkhiy with regard to instruction in the Dharma:</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_szontom">57.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds an umbrella in his hand \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_sposohom">58.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds a staff in his hand\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_snogom">59.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds a knife in his hand\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_sorugiem">60.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, holds a weapon in his hand \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_skogobuvi">61 – 62 \n I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, wears leather [non-leather] shoes \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_vtransporte">63.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is on a vehicle \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_legachego">64.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is in a supine position\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_obhvativkoleni">65.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, sits with his knees clasped \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_sgolovnimuborom">66.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, wears a headdress \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_ssharfom">67.\nI will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is with his head covered (with a robe or scarf, etc.)\n- training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_nasidenii">68.\nSitting on the ground, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is sitting on a seat\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_boleevisokomsidenii">69.\nSitting on a lower seat, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, sits on a higher seat\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_vsidyachemesliyastou">70.\nBeing in a standing position, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, is in a sitting position\n— training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_iduchegovperedi">71.\nWalking behind, I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, walks in front \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="ne_obuchat_idushegopodoroge">72.\nWithout walking on the road (path), I will not teach the Dhamma to a person who, without being ill, walks on the road (path) \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="o_raznom">Category four \n 3 sekkhii about different things:</string>
    <string name="spravliat_nugdu_stoya">73.\nNot being ill, I will not relieve myself of small or large needs standing up \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="spravlyat_nugdu_naposevi">74.\nNot being ill, I will not spit and relieve small or large need for crops \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="spravliat_nugdu_vvodu">75.\nNot being ill, I will not spit and relieve myself of a small or large need in water \n — training for compliance.</string>
    <string name="taxt_pabaja">1. Triple bow before the abbot. The candidate bows and says: \n \n\n    <b>Okasa aham bhante</b> \n \n\n    2. The abbot cuts off a bunch of hair. The candidate repeats in the forward and reverse order: \n \n\n    <b>Kesa, loma, nakha, danta, tacho</b> \n\n    <i>Facial and head hair, body hair, nails, teeth, skin</i> \n \n\n    3. After cutting the hair and ablution, the candidate, taking the cassock with both hands, should approach the abbot and squatting down, put his palms together at face level (holding the cassock on the bends of the elbows) declare the desire to get a haircut: \n \n\n    <b>OkAsa kArunnam katvA pabbajjam detha me bhante aham bhante pabbajjam yAcAmi. \n\n    Dutiyampi…\n\n    Tatiyampi…</b> \n \n\n    4. Having declared, the cassock should be given to the abbot and the gatha should be declared: \n \n\n    <b>sabbe dukhE nissaranA nibbAna saccikaranattai etan kaasavan gahetva pabbajate man bhante anukampam upadai \n\n    Dutiyampi... \n\n    Tatiyampi...</b> \n\n    <i>For liberation from all suffering and achievement of Nibanna, taking this chivara, cut my hair with compassion.</i> \n \n\n    5. After it is necessary to declare, (Attention! In the first gatha, kanditat gives chivara to the mentor, in the second he asks for it.): \n \n\n    <b>sabbe dukhE nissaranA nibbAna saccikaranattai etan kaasavan datva pabbajate man bhante anukampam upadai \n\n    Dutiyampi \n\n    Tatiyampi</b> \n\n    <i>To be freed from all suffering and achieve Nibanna, by giving me this chivara, cut my hair with compassion.</i> \n \n\n    6.\n    Next, the candidate recites: \n \n\n    <b>PatisankhAyoniso civaram patisEvami, yAvadEva sitasa patighAntAya unhasa patighAtaya damsa makasa vatatape sirinsapa sampasano patighataya yAvadEva hiri kOpina paticchAdanattham.</b> \n \n\n    7. Next, the candidate goes to put on a cassock. \n \n\n    8. The candidate makes a nine-part bow: 3 standing with his palms folded over his head with the words okāsa vandāmi bhante, then standing with his knees, his palms are also folded over his head, the words are repeated. After that, the candidate makes a full bow and utters the phrase in full. \n \n\n    <b>okāsa vandāmi bhante</b> \n\n    <i>Let me honor you, honorable</i> \n\n    <b>sabbaṃ accayaṃ khamatha me bhante</b> \n\n    <i>Forgive me all mistakes, my dear</i> \n\n    <b>mayā kataṃ puññaṃ sāminā anumoditabbaṃ</b> \n\n    <i>Let the teacher rejoice in the good (deeds) I have done (them)</i> \n\n    <b>sāminā kataṃ puññaṃ mayhaṃ dātabbaṃ</b> \n\n    <i>Let the good deeds done by the Teacher be shared with me</i> \n\n    <b>sādhu sādhu anumodāmi</b> \n\n    <i>Good, good I rejoice</i> \n\n    <b>Okāsa! Dvārattena kataṁ sabbaṁ accayaṁ khamatha me Bhante</b> \n\n    <i>Allow me! Any and all misdemeanors committed, forgive me, honorable</i> \n \n\n    9. After the candidate expresses a desire to receive refuge and 10 vows: \n \n\n    <b>Okāsa ahaṃ bhante, tisaraṇena saddhiṃ</b> \n\n    <i>Let me venerable with triple refuge together</i> \n\n    <b>pabbajjā dasasīlaṃ dhammaṃ yācāmi.</b> \n\n    <i>I am going to take the vows of 10 vows</i> \n\n    <b>Anuggahaṃ katvā sīlaṃ detha me bhante.</b> \n\n    <i>Support by providing training give me the honorable</i> \n\n    <b>anukampaṃ upādāya</b> \n\n    <i>Compassion originated</i> \n\n    <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n\n    <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n\n    10. The mentor must answer: \n \n\n    <b>Yamahaṃ vadāmi taṃ vadetha</b> \n\n    <i>what I say, then repeat</i> \n\n    The candidate responds: \n \n\n    <b>āma bhante!</b> \n\n    <i>Yes venerable</i> \n \n\n    The candidate declares lines of respect. \n \n\n    <b>Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambhuddhassa(x3)</b> \n \n\n    After that, the mentor declares the lines of refuge with the ending in M, the kadidat repeats loudly and clearly: \n \n\n    <b>Buddham, saraṇam, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dhammam, saraṇam, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Saṇgham, saraṇam, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n\n    <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n\n    After that, the mentor declares the lines of refuge with the ending in ṃ, the kadidat repeats loudly and clearly: \n \n\n    <b>Buddhaṃ, saraṇaṃ, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dhammaṃ, saraṇaṃ, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Saṇghaṃ, saraṇaṃ, gacchāmi.</b> \n\n    <b>Dutiyampi...</b> \n\n    <b>Tatiyampi...</b> \n \n\n    <i>Note. There is no semantic difference in the translation. The formula of refuge can be pronounced in any language if it is accepted by a layman. If a monk, then it should be pronounced only in the Pali language. Because this is an official action in the produced within the framework of the Wine Pitaka. Therefore, all sounds should be pronounced as close as possible to the original. The pronunciation of the Refuge is duplicated in case of incorrect pronunciation. The pronunciation at the end of the \"am\" is called Makaranta sarana gamane. And with the ending on \"an\" Niggahitānta sarana gamana.</i> \n \n\n    After, the Mentor pronounces the end of the refuge: <b>Sarana gamana sampunnam!</b> \n\n    The candidate replies: <b>Ama bhante!</b> \n \n\n    From that moment on, the candidate ceases to be a layman and becomes a monk. Next, follows the adoption of 10 vows.  The mentor declares a list of vows! \n \n\\\n    <b>1.pāṇātipātā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from killing living beings abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>2.adinnādānā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from taking undone abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>3.abrahmacariyā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>The non-hermit life of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>4.musāvādā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from false abstinence speech</i> \n\n    <b>5.surāmerayamajjapamādaṭṭhānā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from the use of intoxicating substances leading to carelessness of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>6.vikālabhojanā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from eating at the wrong time of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>7.nacca gīta vādita visūkadassanā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>abstinence from dancing, singing, music, attending entertainment events</i> \n\n    <b>8.mālā gandha vilepana dhāraṇa maṇḍana vibhūsanaṭṭhānā veramaṇī</b>  \n\n    <i>from wearing garlands, using perfumes and cosmetics to decorate the body of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>9.uccā sayana mahā sayanā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from high and large beds of abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>10.jāta rūpa rajata paṭiggahaṇā veramaṇī</b> \n\n    <i>from taking gold and silver abstinence</i> \n\n    <b>Imāni pabbajjā dasa sikkhāpadāni samādiyāmi (3x)</b> \n\n    <i>I accept these ten rules of tonsure</i> \n \n\n    <b>Ama bhante</b></string>
    <string name="sekhiya_about"><i> \n\n            75 Sekhiya (rules for training) \n \n\n        The term in Pali literally means to train in. \n \n\n        There are 75 rules in this section of the Vinaya, which are divided into four categories: \n \n\n        1. etiquette of wearing robes and etiquette of behavior in a populated area; \n\n        2. etiquette in accepting and eating food from alms; \n etiquette when teaching someone the Dhamma; \n\n        3. etiquette in relieving need. \n \n The sum of these rules is the person of samaner and bhikkhu,\n        and hence the appearance of the Sangha as a whole. \n \n\n        There are stories of how Bhante Sariputta was inspired by the manners of bhante Assaji and decided to join the community, as well as how King Ashoka converted to Buddhism under the impression of the manners of the young samanera.</i></string>
    <string name="djhana">The picture shows how at the festival of the first furrow, 5-year-old Siddhartha, sitting under the shadow of a tree, spontaneously entered jhana (deep meditative concentration), another miracle happened, the shadow of the tree remained in one place all the time, seeing this, Siddhardha\'s father bowed to him, this was the second time when the father bowed to his son. \n\nIn some sutta of the canon, the Buddha mentions this episode, here is an excerpt from the Maha sachchaka sutta mn36: \n\n\"I remember how once, when my father from the Sakya clan was working, I was sitting in the cool of a shady myrtle tree, and then, completely abandoning sensual pleasures and inept mental qualities, I entered and stayed in the first jhana: the delight and pleasure born of [this] abandonment was accompanied by the direction of the mind and the retention of the mind. \n \n\nAnd the story is as follows: \n\nOne day the Rajah was holding a celebration of the beginning of arable work. On this day, the city was decorated. All the slaves and servants in new clothes, decorated with flower garlands gathered in the palace.Thousands of ploughs were prepared for the royal ploughing works. The plows, reins and yoke of one hundred and seven oxen were decorated with silver. But the one hundred and eighth plow, intended for the rajah, was decorated with red gold, and the horns of oxen, reins and whip [rajah] were also decorated with gold.\nThe rajah, who came out of the palace with a large retinue, took his son and went to the clearing where the jambu tree grew with very dense foliage, giving dense shade. Under it, the rajah ordered to put a sofa for the child. Then, leaving the guard, the rajah in luxurious robes, accompanied by ministers, went to plow.\nThe minute the rajah took up the golden plow, his ministers took up the one hundred and seven silver plows, and the peasants took up the rest of the plows. Holding on to the plows, they began to burrow the field. Raja moved from one end of the field to the other, and then returned back.\nHe was clearly in a good mood; and the nurses sitting around the Bodhisattva thought: Let\'s go see how nicely the raja works, and, coming out from behind the veil, let\'s go. The future Buddha looked around and realizing that he was alone, quickly got up, sat cross-legged and, watching his breathing, entered the first jhana.\nThe nannies were attracted to the preparation of various types of dishes and they were a little late. The shadows of the trees moved and only the shadow of the jambu tree remained in its place and was round in shape. The nurses, remembering that the prince was alone, hurried to the tree. The Bodhisattva was sitting cross-legged under the miraculously stopped shade of a tree. The nurses ran to the rajah shouting: Your Majesty! the prince is sitting this way and that, and when the shadow of the other trees has gone, the shadow of the jambu tree remains in place in the shape of a circle!.\nThe Rajah hurried to the tree, saw this miracle and bowed to his son with the words: Dear, this is the second time I\'ve paid my respects to you.</string>
    <string name="button_morning_vandana_with_laymans">morning vandana with layman at Cittawiveque Monastery</string>
    <string name="deklomation_after_evening_meditation">Recitation after evening meditation at Cittawiveque Monastery</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaOfterEveningMeditationO">
        <b>RECLAIMATION AFTER EVENING MEDITATION AT CHITTAVIVEKA MONASTERY</b> \n \n \n
<b><u>Imaya dhammanu dhamma patipattiya buddham pujemi.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this practice be an offering to the Buddha.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Imaya dhammanu dhamma patipattiya dhammam pujemi.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this practice be an offering to the Dhamma.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Imaya dhammanu dhamma patipattiya sangham pujemi.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this practice be an offering to the Sangha.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Addha imaya patipattiya jati jara maranamha parimuccissami.</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this practice lead to liberation from birth, aging and death.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Idam me punnam kamma asavekkhaya vaham hotu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May the assavas be destroyed by this meritorious kamma.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sabbe dukha pamojjatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>All pain and pleasure</i> \n \n \n
<b>KARANIA METTA SUTTA</b> \n \n
<b><u></u>Karaṇīyamatthakusalena, yanta santaṃ padaṃ abhisamecca;</b> \n \n
<i>This is what one should do who is skilled in good things and wants to achieve a peaceful state:</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sakko ujū ca suhujū [sūjū (sī.)] ca, sūvaco cassa mudu anatimānī.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let him be able, direct and honest, meek, gentle and not proud,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Santussako ca subharo ca, appakicco ca sallahukavutti;</u></b> \n \n
<i>satisfied and unburdened, with few responsibilities, content with little,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Santindriyo ca nipako ca, appagabbho kulesvananugiddho.</u></b> \n \n
<i>with calm perception abilities, reasonable, humble, and not fawning over families.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Na ca khuddamācare kiñci, yena viññū pare upavadeyyuṃ;</u></b> \n \n
<i>And let him not do the slightest thing that the wise would condemn.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sukhino va khemino hontu, sabbasattā [sabbe sattā (sī. syā.)] bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b> \n \n
<i>[And let him think:] Joyful and safe, may all beings be joyful in heart.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ye keci pāṇabhūtatthi, tasā vā thāvarā vanavasesā;</u></b> \n \n
<i>Whatever the creatures, fragile or strong, without exception,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Dīghā vā ye va mahantā [mahanta (?)], majjhimā rassakā aṇukathūlā.</u></b> \n \n
<i>long, large, medium, small, small, thick,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Diṭṭhā vā ye va adiṭṭhā [adiṭṭha (?)], ye va [ye ca (sī. syā. kaṃ. pī.)] dūre vasanti avidūre;</u></b> \n \n
<i>visible and invisible, living near and far,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Bhūtā va sambhavesī va [bhūtā vā sambhavesī vā (syā. kaṃ. pī. ka.)], sabbasattā bhavantu sukhitattā.</u></b> \n \n
<i>those who have come into the world and aspire to appear: may all beings be joyful in heart.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Na paro paraṃ nikubbetha, nātimaññetha katthaci na kañci [naṃ kañci (sī. pī.), naṃ kiñci (syā.), na kiñci (ka.)] ;</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let no one upset another or despise anyone anywhere,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Byārosanā paṭighasaññā, nāññamaññassa dukkhamiccheyya.</u></b> \n \n
<i>and let no one wish another to suffer because of anger or an unpleasant impression.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Mātā yathā niyaṃ puttamāyusā ekaputtamanurakkhe;</u></b> \n \n
<i>As a mother, at the cost of her life, is ready to protect her child, her only child,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Evampi sabbabhūtesu, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ.</u></b> \n \n
<i>so without restrictions to all creatures he should develop this thought.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Mettañca sabbalokasmi, mānasaṃ bhāvaye aparimāṇaṃ;</u></b> \n \n
<i>For the whole world, let it develop the boundless thought of friendliness:</i> \n \n
<b><u>Uddhaṃ adho ca tiriyañca, asambādhaṃ averamasapattaṃ.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Up, down, and in between, without obstruction, malevolence, or foe.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Tiṭṭhaṃ caraṃ nisinno va, sayāno yāvatāssa vitamiddho vigatamiddo (bahūsu) </u></b> \n \n
<i>Standing, walking, sitting or lying down while not drowsy</i> \n \n
<b><u>Etaṃ satiṃ adhiṭṭheyya, brahmametaṃ vihāramidhamāhu.</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let him strive for this remembrance. It is spoken of as being in the state of brahma [straight] here</i> \n \n
<b><u>Diṭṭhiñca anupagamma, sīlavā dassanena sampanno;</u></b> \n \n
<i>Not confused with views, moral, he has insight,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Kāmesu vinaya gedhaṃ, na hi jātuggabbhaseyya punaretīti.</u></b> \n \n
<i>With the elimination of greed for sensual pleasures, he will never again be in the womb.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ētēna saccavajjêna sabbē dukkhā vinnasatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all your suffering disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ētēna saccavajjêna sabbē bhayā vinnasatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all your fears disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ētēna saccavajjêna sabbē rogā vinnasatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all your diseases disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>jayo munindassa subodhi mūle</u></b> \n \n
<i>"Buddhas victory under the great Bodhi tree</i> \n \n
<b><u>ahosi mārassa parajāyosi</u></b> \n \n
<i>Caused Maras defeat!</i> \n \n
<b><u>ugghosayuṃ devagaṇā pasannā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Various deities exclaimed in admiration.</i> \n \n
<b><u>etena saccena jayantu tuyhaṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this truth bring you victory.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>sabbe buddhā balappattā paccekānañca yaṃ balaṃ arahantānañca tejena rakkhaṃ bandhāmi sabbaso</u></b> \n \n
<i>By the power of all the Buddhas, by the power of all the self-awakened ones, by the power of the Arhats, may I be protected in every possible way.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā dēvā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let the gods and Nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ tam anumōditvā ciram rakkhantu lōka sāsanaṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>rejoice in our beneficence and long defend Buddhism in this world.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā dēvā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let the gods and Nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ tam anumōditvā ciram rakkhantu dēsanaṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>They will rejoice in our good deeds and defend the Teaching for a long time.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā dēvā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let the gods and Nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ tam anumōditvā ciram rakkhantu maṃ paraṃ</u></b> \n \n
<i>rejoice in our good deeds and protect me and others for a long time.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Iminā puññakammēna - mā me bālasamāgamō</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this merit never follow fools.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sataṃ samāgamō hōtu - yāva nibbāna pattiyā</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let me follow only the wise until I achieve Nibbana.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Idaṃ me puññaṃ - āsavakkhayā vahaṃ hōtu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May this merit lead me to cessation of cravings.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sabba dukkhā pamuccatu</u></b> \n \n
<i>May all suffering disappear.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Idaṃ no (me) ñātīnaṃ hōtu - sukhitā hontu ñātayō [3x]</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let this go to the benefit of our (my) relatives. May my relatives be happy.</i> \n \n \n
<b><u>Dēvo vassatu kālena</u></b> \n \n
<b><u>sassasampatti hētu ca</u></b> \n \n
<b><u>phito bhavātu lōko ca</u></b> \n \n
<b><u>Raja bhavatu dhammiko</u></b> \n \n
<i>Let it rain in its own time</i> \n \n
<i>let there be a rich harvest,</i> \n \n
<i>May the world prosper</i> \n \n
<i>Let the government be righteous.</i> \n \n \n

    </string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaVandanaWithLaiman">
        <b>VANDANA WITH LAID AT CHITTAVIVEKA MONASTERY</b> \n \n \n

     <b><u>1. Sadhukela namaskare kiane</u></b> \n
     <i>After saying the namaskara to the sadhu</i> \n \n

     <i>Laity say:</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Namō tassa bhagavatō arahatō sammā sambuddhassa [3x]</u></b> \n\n

     <i>2. The monk says, the laity repeats:</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Buddhaṃ saraṇaṃ gacchami</u></b> \n
     <i>I take refuge in the Buddha.</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Dhammaṃ saraṇaṃ gacchāmi</u></b> \n
     <i>I take refuge in the Buddhas Teachings (Dhamma).</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Saṅghaṃ saraṇaṃ gacchami</u></b> \n
     <i>I take refuge in the Sangha (noble disciples of the Buddha).</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Dutiyampi…</u></b> \n
     <i>For the second time...</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Tatiyampi…</u></b> \n
     <i>Third time...</i> \n \n

     <i>2. Monk says:</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Tisarana gamanamsumpunnam</u></b> \n
     <i>Triple Sanctuary Complete</i> \n \n

     <b><u>3. Pāṇātipātā vēramaṇī sikkhāpadaṃ samādiyāmi.</u></b> \n
     <i>I accept the rule to refrain from taking life.</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Adinnādānā vēramaṇī sikkhāpadaṃ samādiyāmi.</u></b> \n
     <i>I make it a rule to refrain from taking what is not given to me.</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Kāmesumicchācārā vēramaṇī sikkhāpadaṃ samādiyāmi.</u></b> \n
     <i>I accept the rule of abstaining from sexual promiscuity.</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Musāvādā vēramaṇī sikkhāpadaṃ samādiyāmi.</u></b> \n
     <i>I accept the rule to refrain from false speech.</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Surāmērayamajjapamādaṭṭhānā vēramaṇī sikkhāpadaṃ samādiyāmi.</u></b> \n
     <i>I make it a rule to abstain from the use of intoxicants that lead to carelessness.</i> \n \n

     <i>The monk recites (the laity are silent):</i> \n \n

     <b><u>Tisaraṇena saddhiṃ pañcasīlaṃ dhammaṃ sādhukaṃ surakkhitaṃ katvā</u></b> \n
     <i>Carefully following these 5 Rules with Three Refuges</i> \n \n

     <b><u>appamādena sampādetha</u></b> \n
     <i>try hard.</i> \n \n

     <i>laymen answer: </i> \n \n

     <b><u>āma bhantē</u></b> \n
     <i>Yes, sir</i> \n \n

     <b><u>4. Den api eketamevandena karemu</u></b> \n
     <i> Now we are going to make vandana. </i>\n\n

     <i>laymen answer: </i> \n \n

     <b><u>sadhu sadhu sadhu. </u></b> \n \n

     <u>SPEAKING TO THE BUDDHA</u> \n \n
<b><u>Nivedayami sambuddham</u></b> \n
<i>Perceiving the Samasambuddha</i> \n \n
<b><u>Vitaragam mahamunim</u></b> \n
<i>Great Sage Free from Passion</i> \n \n
<b><u>Nimantayami sugatam</u></b> \n
<i>I talk about the well-departed</i> \n \n
<b><u>Lokajettham narasabam</u></b> \n
<i>The best in the world among people</i> \n \n \n
         <u>OFFERING LIGHT</u> \n \n
<b><u>Ghanasārappadittena - dīpena tamadhaṃsinā</u></b> \n
<i>Light of burning camphor that removes darkness</i> \n \n
<b><u>Tilokadīpaṃ sambuddhaṃ - pūjayāmi tamonudaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>I pay homage to the enlightener of the three worlds, who has comprehended and dispels darkness (ignorance).</i> \n \n \n
         <u>OFFERING INCENSE</u> \n \n
<b><u>sugandhikāya vadanaṃ - ananta guṇa gandhinaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>To one whose body and face are fragrant, from whom the scent of innumerable good qualities emanates</i> \n \n
<b><u>sugandhināhaṃ gandhena - pūjayāmi tathāgataṃ</u></b> \n
<i>I offer these incense to the Tathagata.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>FLOWER OFFERS</u> \n \n
<b><u>Vaṇṇagandhaguṇopetaṃ - etaṃ kusumasantatiṃ</u></b> \n
<i>This scattering of flowers, endowed with beauty and pleasant smell,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Pūjayāmi munindassa - sirīpādasaroruhe</u></b> \n
<i>I offer to the lotus feet of the Supreme Sage.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Pūjemi buddhaṃ kusumenanena – puññena metena labhami mokkhaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>I worship the Buddha with these flowers (kusumena+anena), may I gain liberation through this boon.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Pupphaṃ milāyāti yathā idamme - kāyo tathā yāti vināsabhāvaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>As these flowers wither, so does this body of mine fall apart.</i> \n \n \n

        <b><u>Adhivāsētu no bhantē - pāṇīyaṃ parikappitaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>Venerable One, have mercy on this beautiful water we have prepared</i> \n\n

<b><u>Anukampaṃ upādāya - patigaṇhātu muttamaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>to accept out of compassion for us</i> \n\n

<b><u>Adhivāsētu no bhantē - bhōjanaṃ parikappitaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>Venerable One, have mercy on our fine food</i> \n\n

<b><u>Anukampaṃ upādāya - patigaṇhātu muttamaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>to accept out of compassion for us.</i> \n \n

        <u>OFFERING OTHER DISHES</u> \n \n
<b><u>adhivāsetu no bhante - sabbaṃ saddhāya pūjitaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>Venerable One, have mercy on all that is offered on the basis of trust</i> \n \n
<b><u>anukampaṃ upādāya - patigaṇhātumuttamaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>to accept, O great one, out of compassion for us.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>QUALITIES OF A BUDDHA</u> \n \n
<b><u>Itipi so bhagavā arahaṃ sammāsambuddho</u></b> \n
<i>The Blessed One really is like that: he is worthy, he has attained perfection,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Vijjacaraṇasampanno sugato lokavidū</u></b> \n
<i>possessing knowledge and [good] behavior, who has achieved good, a connoisseur of the world,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Anuttaro purisadammasārathi</u></b> \n
<i>A peerless guide to creatures fit to harness</i> \n \n
<b><u>Satthā devamanussānaṃ buddho bhagavāti</u></b> \n
<i>teacher of gods and people, comprehended, blessed.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>QUALITIES OF DHAMMA</u> \n \n
<b><u>Svākkhāto bhagavatā dhammo</u></b> \n
<i>Well explained by the Blessed Dhamma,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sandiṭṭhiko akāliko ehipassiko</u></b> \n
<i> directly visible, timeless, inviting to come and see,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Opanayiko paccattaṃ veditabbo viññūhīti</u></b> \n
<i>leading to the goal, can be tested by the wise on their own.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>QUALITIES OF SANGKHA</u> \n \n
<b><u>Supaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n
<i>The community (Sangha) of the disciples of the Blessed One has embarked on a good path,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ujupaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n
<i>The community of disciples of the Blessed One has set out on a straight path,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ñāyapaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n
<i>the community of disciples of the Blessed One has set out on the right path,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sāmīcipaṭipanno bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n
<i>the community of disciples of the Blessed One has entered upon the proper path,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Yadidaṃ cattāri purisayugāni aṭṭha purisapuggalā</u></b> \n
<i>namely, four couples, eight personality types.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Esa bhagavato sāvakasaṅgho</u></b> \n
<i>This is a community of disciples of the Blessed One</i> \n \n
<b><u>Āhuṇeyyo pāhuṇeyyo dakkhiṇeyyo añjalikaraṇīyo</u></b> \n
<i> deserves gifts, deserves hospitality, deserves offerings, deserves a respectful greeting,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Anuttaraṃ puññakkhettaṃ lokassati</u></b> \n
<i>An incomparable field of merit for the world.</i> \n \n \n

        <u>HONOR TO MONUMENTS</u> \n \n
<b><u>Vandāmi cetiyaṃ sabbaṃ - sabbaṭṭhānesu patiṭṭhitaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>I honor all monuments in all places where they are installed,</i> \n \n
<b><u>Sārīrikadhātu mahābodhiṃ - buddharūpaṃ sakalaṃ sadā</u></b> \n
<i>relic remains, Bodhi tree, I always revere all Buddha images.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>NOTE TO THE BODHHI TREE</u> \n \n
<b><u>Yassamūle nisinnova - sabbārivijayaṃ akā</u></b> \n
<i>Sitting at the foot of which defeated all enemies</i> \n \n
<b><u>Patto sabbaññutaṃ satthā - vande taṃ bodhipādapaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>and our teacher gained omniscience - this is the same Bodhi tree I revere.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ime ete mahābodhī - lokanāthena pūjitā</u></b> \n
<i>These are the greatest Bodhi trees, revered by the protector of the world (Buddha),</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ahampi te namassāmi - bodhirājā namatthu te</u></b> \n
<i>Ill greet you too. My respects to the great Bodhi tree!</i> \n \n \n
         <u>FORGIVENESS OF DEFECTS</u> \n \n
<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n
<i>[If] by my body, speech or thoughts, due to carelessness, was committed</i> \n \n
<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me bhante - bhūripañña tathāgata</u></b> \n
<i>Misdemeanor - forgive me, venerable, profound Tathagata.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n
<i>[If] by my body, speech or thoughts, due to carelessness, was committed</i> \n \n
<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me dhamma - sandiṭṭhika akālika</u></b> \n
<i>misdemeanor - forgive me Dhamma, seen directly, taking no time.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Kāyena vācā cittena pamādena mayā kataṃ</u></b> \n
<i>[If] by my body, speech or thoughts, due to carelessness, was committed</i> \n \n
<b><u>Accayaṃ khama me saṅgha supaṭipanna anuttara</u></b> \n
<i>Misdemeanor - forgive me Sangha, who has embarked on a good path, incomparable.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>INVITATION OF THE DEVAS TO REJOY</u> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n
<i>May the mighty deities and nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu lokasāsanaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>Rejoicing in this boon, they protect the system in this world for a long time.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n
<i>May the mighty deities and nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu desanaṃ</u></b> \n
<i>Rejoicing at this boon, they defend  instruction for a long time.</i> \n \n
<b><u>Ākāsatthā ca bhummaṭṭhā devā nāgā mahiddhikā</u></b> \n
<i>May the mighty deities and nagas living on earth and in the sky</i> \n \n
<b><u>Puññaṃ taṃ anumoditvā ciraṃ rakkhantu maṃ paraṃ</u></b> \n
<i>rejoicing in this beneficence, they protect me and others for a long time.</i> \n \n \n
         <u>SHARING OF MERIT</u> \n \n
<b><u>idaṃ no (me) ñātīnaṃ hotu - sukhitā hontu ñātayo [3x]</u></b> \n
<i>Let this be for the benefit of our (my) relatives, may the relatives be happy.</i> \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="button_sutta_mangala">Maha mangala sutta</string>
    <string name="button_sutta_ratana">ratana stta</string>
    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaMangala">
        \n <b>MAHA MANGALA SUTTHA</b> \n \n
         <i>A sermon on what best contributes to well-being</i> \n \n
         <b>Ēvaṃ mē sutaṃ ēkaṃ samayaṃ bhagavā sāvatthiyaṃ viharati jētavanē anāthapiṇḍikassa ārāmē</b> \n \n
         <i>So I heard: once the Perfect One was not far from Savatthi, in the Jeta grove, in the monastery of Anathapindika.</i> \n \n
         <b>Athakhō aññatarā dēvatā abhikkantāya rattiyā</b> \n \n
         <i>When the night was almost over, one deity,</i> \n \n
         <b>Abhikkantavaṇṇā kēvalakappaṃ jētavanaṃ ōbhāsetvā yena bhagavā</b> \n \n
         <i>appeared in the grove of Jeta, and, illuminating it with its radiance, to the Perfect</i> \n \n
         <b>Tenupasaṃkami upasaṅkamitvā bhagavantaṃ abhivādetvā ēkamantaṃ aṭṭhāsi</b> \n \n
         <i>approached. Approaching, it respectfully greeted him and stood aside</i> \n \n
         <b>Ēkamantaṃ ṭhitā kho sā dēvatā bhagavantaṃ gāthāya ajjhabhāsī</b> \n \n
         <i>And, standing aside, the deity then turned to the Perfect in verses:</i> \n \n
         <b>Bahū dēvā manussā ca maṅgalāni acintayuṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>"Many gods and people thought about what contributes to well-being,</i> \n \n
         <b>Ākaṅkhamānā sotthānaṃ brūhi maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>wanting to succeed. So tell me: what best contributes to it?"</i> \n \n
         <b>Asēvanā ca bālānaṃ paṇḍitānañca sēvanā</b> \n \n
         <i>"Dont deal with fools, deal with wise ones,</i> \n \n
         <b>Pūjā ca pūjanīyānaṃ ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and to honor those worthy of veneration is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Patirūpadēsavāsōca pubbē ca katapuññatā</b> \n \n
         <i>To live in a suitable area, having accumulated merit in the past,</i> \n \n
         <b>Attasammāpaṇidhi ca ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>being guided by right intentions is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Bāhusaccañca sippañca vinayo ca susikkhito</b> \n \n
         <i>Deep knowledge, skills, good discipline,</i> \n \n
         <b>Subhāsitā ca yā vācā ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Pleasant speech is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Mātāpitū upaṭṭhānaṃ puttadārassa saṅghahō</b> \n \n
         <i>Helping mother and father, taking care of wife and children,</i> \n \n
         <b>Anākulā ca kammantā ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Conflict-free work is what contributes best to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Dānañca dhammacariyā ca ñātakānañca saṅgahō</b> \n \n
         <i>Generosity, righteous living, caring for relatives,</i> \n \n
         <b>Anavajjāni kammāni ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>impeccability in deeds is what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Āratī viratī pāpā majjapānā ca saṃyamō</b> \n \n
         <i>Abstaining from the vicious, avoiding intoxicating substances,</i> \n \n
         <b>Appamādo ca dhammēsu ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>mindfulness of mental qualities is what best promotes well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Gāravō ca nivātō ca santuṭṭhi ca kataññutā</b> \n \n
         <i>Respect, humility, contentment and gratitude,</i> \n \n
         <b>Kālēna dhammassavanaṃ ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>listening to the Dhamma at the right time is what is most conducive to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Khantī ca sovacassatā samaṇānañca dassanaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Patience, complaisance, seeing ascetics,</i> \n \n
         <b>Kālēna dhammasākacchā ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Discussing the Dhamma at the right time is what is most conducive to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Tapo ca brahmacariyañca ariyasaccana dassanaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Self-restraint, chastity, realization of Noble Truths</i> \n \n
         <b>Nibbāna sacchikiriyā ca ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and the realization of Nibbana is what best promotes well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Phuṭṭhassa lōkadhammēhi cittaṃ yassa na kampati</b> \n \n
         <i>The mind that remains steady in contact with the mundane</i> \n \n
         <b>Asōkaṃ virajaṃ khēmaṃ ētaṃ maṅgalamuttamaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>carefree, pure, calm - thats what best contributes to well-being.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētādisāni katvāna sabbatthama′parā′jitā</b> \n \n
         <i>Those who do this are always invincible,</i> \n \n
         <b>Sabbattha sotthiṃ gacchanti taṃ tēsaṃ maṅgalamuttaman′ti</b> \n \n
         <i>always succeeding is what best contributes to their well-being."</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sotthi te hōtu sabbadā</b> \n \n
         <i>May all prosperity follow you through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna hōtu te jayamaṅgalaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>May you gain the benefit of victory through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabbarōgō vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all illnesses be healed through the power of this truth</i> \n \n \n \n \n \n
    </string>

    <string name="DeklomaciyaSuttaRatana">
        \n <b>RATANA SUTTA</b> \n \n
         <i>THE TREASURE SUTTA</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatānī</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial, -</i> \n \n
         <b>Sabbēva bhūtā sumana bhavantu</b> \n \n
         <i>may you all be happy</i> \n \n
         <b>Athopi sakkacca suṇantu bhāsitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and listen to the words.</i> \n \n
         <b>Tasmā hi bhūtā nisāmētha sabbē</b> \n \n
         <i>Listen, spirits!</i> \n \n
         <b>Mettaṃ karōtha mānusiyā pajāya</b> \n \n
         <i>be friendly to the human race,</i> \n \n
         <b>Divā ca ratto ca haranti ye baliṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>who brings his offerings day and night</i> \n \n
         <b>Tasmā hi ne rakkhata appamattā</b> \n \n
         <i>Zealously guard the people!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yaṃ kiñci vittaṃ idha vā huraṃ vā</b> \n \n
         <i>No treasure here or in the next world</i> \n \n
         <b>Saggēsu vā yaṃ ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>no jewels of heaven</i> \n \n
         <b>Na nō samaṃ atthi tathāgatēna</b> \n \n
         <i>will not equal the Ultimate.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi buddhē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure resides in the Buddha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Khayaṃ virāgaṃ amataṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>The destruction of passions, freedom from them, and then the highest immortality</i> \n \n
         <b>Yadajjhagā sakyamunī samāhitō</b> \n \n
         <i>which Sakyamuni attained in concentration</i> \n \n
         <b>Na tena dhammēna samatthi kiñci</b> \n \n
         <i>There is nothing equal to this state!</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi dhammē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure dwells in the Dhamma.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yambuddhaseṭṭhō parivaṇṇayī suciṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This path of purity, praised by the Supreme Buddha</i> \n \n
         <b>Samādhimānata rikaññamāhu</b> \n \n
         <i>invariably leads to concentration.</i> \n \n
         <b>Samādhinā tēna samō na vijjati</b> \n \n
         <i>Nothing compares to this concentration.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi dhammē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure dwells in the Dhamma.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ye puggalā aṭṭha sataṃ pasatthā</b> \n \n
         <i>Eight of them, glorified by the Righteous One,</i> \n \n
         <b>Cattari ētāni yugāni honti</b> \n \n
         <i>four pairs of them,</i> \n \n
         <b>Te dakkhiṇeyyā sugatassa sāvakā</b> \n \n
         <i>disciples of the Achieved Good, worthy of donation:</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēsu dinnāni mahapphalānī</b> \n \n
         <i>what is bestowed upon them will bear good fruit.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ye suppayuttā manasā daḷhēna</b> \n \n
         <i>Those who are steadfast and thorough</i> \n \n
         <b>Nikkāminō gōtamasāsanamhi</b> \n \n
         <i>Follow the teachings of Gotama, free from [mental defilements],</i> \n \n
         <b>Te pattipattā amataṃ vigayha</b> \n \n
         <i>achieved what they should have achieved by gaining the Immortal.</i> \n \n
         <b>Laddhā mudhā nibbutiṃ bhuñjamānā</b> \n \n
         <i>They are freely enjoying their attained Liberation.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yathindakhīlō pathaviṃsito siyā</b> \n \n
         <i>The pillars of Indra stand firmly in the ground,</i> \n \n
         <b>Catubhi vātēhi asampakampiyo</b> \n \n
         <i>not shaken by the four winds</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathūpamaṃ sappurisaṃ vadāmi</b> \n \n
         <i>Nothing can shake the righteous</i> \n \n
         <b>Yo ariyasaccāni avecca passati</b> \n \n
         <i>who has comprehended noble truths, who has clearly comprehended them.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ye ariyasaccāni vibhāvayanti</b> \n \n
         <i>Who has comprehended noble truths</i> \n \n
         <b>Gambhīrapaññēna sudēsitāni</b> \n \n
         <i>proclaimed in perfection by the Wise,</i> \n \n
         <b>Kiñcāpi te honti bhusaṃ pamattā</b> \n \n
         <i>no matter how careless he may be in the future,</i> \n \n
         <b>Na te bhavaṃ aṭṭhamamādiyanti</b> \n \n
         <i>will not experience the eighth rebirth.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Sahāvassa dassanasampadāya</b> \n \n
         <i>He who has gained insight</i> \n \n
         <b>Tayassu dhammā jahitā bhavanti</b> \n \n
         <i>got rid of three traits:</i> \n \n
         <b>Sakkāyadiṭṭhi vicikicchitañca</b> \n \n
         <i>belief in individuality, insecurity and </i> \n \n
         <b>Sīlabbataṃ vāpi yadatthi kiñci</b> \n \n
         <i>any attachment to rituals and ceremonies.</i> \n \n
         <b>Catūhapāyehi ca vippamuttō</b> \n \n
         <i>He is free from being reborn in the four bad realms,</i> \n \n
         <b>Chacābhiṭhānāni abhabbō kātuṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>and unable to commit the six heaviest offenses. </i>\n\n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Kiñcāpi so kammaṃ karōti pāpakaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>What a bad thing to do</i> \n \n
         <b>Kāyena vācā udacetasā vā</b> \n \n
         <i>the person who entered the stream did not commit the body, speech or thoughts,</i> \n \n
         <b>Abhabbō so tassa paṭicchādāya</b> \n \n
         <i>he is unable to hide it</i> \n \n
         <b>Abhabbatā diṭṭhapadassa vuttā</b> \n \n
         <i>because it s impossible for someone who sees the path.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Vanappagumbē yathā phussitaggē</b> \n \n
         <i>Like the tops of trees</i> \n \n
         <b>Gimhānamāsē paṭhamasmiṃ gimhē</b> \n \n
         <i>everything is in bloom at the beginning of summer</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathūpamaṃ dhammavaraṃ adesayī</b> \n \n
         <i>so is His exalted Dhamma,</i> \n \n
         <b>Nibbānagāmiṃ paramaṃ hitāya</b> \n \n
         <i>leading to the tranquility of Nibbana, striving for the highest good.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi buddhē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure resides in the Buddha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Varō varaññū varadō varāharō</b> \n \n
         <i>Incomparable, he is the one who sees Nibbana, gives Nibbana, brings the Noble Eightfold Path,</i> \n \n
         <b>Anuttarō dhammavaraṃ adēsayi</b> \n \n
         <i>told us this supreme Truth.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi buddhē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>This is what a precious treasure resides in the Buddha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Khīṇaṃ purāṇaṃ nava natthi sambhavaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Their past is exhausted, the new does not arise,</i> \n \n
         <b>Virattacittāāyatikē bhavasmiṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Their mind is not attached to future becoming.</i> \n \n
         <b>Te khīṇabījā avirūḷhicchandā</b> \n \n
         <i>Their seed has been destroyed and they have no more desire for a new life.</i> \n \n
         <b>Nibbanti dhīrā yathāyaṃ padīpō</b> \n \n
         <i>Such sages are extinguished like the flame of this lamp.</i> \n \n
         <b>Idampi saṅghē ratanaṃ paṇītaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>Such a precious treasure resides in the Sangha.</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccēna suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Let this truth bring prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatāni</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial,</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathāgataṃ dēvamanussapūjitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>A Tathagata honored by gods and men</i> \n \n
         <b>Buddhaṃ namassāma suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Lets glorify the Buddha too. Let there be prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatāni</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial,</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathāgataṃ dēvamanussapūjitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>A Tathagata honored by gods and men.</i> \n \n
         <b>Dhammaṃ namassāma suvatthi hōtu</b> \n \n
         <i>Lets glorify the Dhamma too. Let there be prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Yānīdha bhūtāni samāgatāni</b> \n \n
         <i>All the spirits that came here</i> \n \n
         <b>Bhummāni vā yāni va antalikkhe</b> \n \n
         <i>terrestrial and celestial,</i> \n \n
         <b>Tathāgataṃ dēvamanussapūjitaṃ</b> \n \n
         <i>A Tathagata honored by gods and men.</i> \n \n
         <b>Saṅghaṃ namassāma suvatthi hōtuti</b> \n \n
         <i>Lets glorify the Sangha too. Let there be prosperity!</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabba dukkhaṃ vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all your suffering disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabba bhayō vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all your fears disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n
         <b>Ētēna saccavajjēna sabba rōgō vinassatu</b> \n \n
         <i>May all your diseases disappear through the power of this truth</i> \n \n \n \n \n \n
    </string>
    <string name="rukovodstvo_dllya_bhikkhu">guide for bhikkhu</string>
    <string name="button_upasampada">upasampada \n Stanzas for the ceremony of becoming a Bhikkhu</string>
    <string name="button_patimokha">Rules of patimokkha</string>
    <string name="buttonAboutParajika">ABOUT THE RULES OF PATIMOKKHA</string>
    <string name="buttonaboutParajikaNakazanie">THE SYSTEM OF PUNISHMENTS PROVIDED FOR BY THE RULES OF PATIMOKKHA</string>
    <string name="buttonPatimokhaRazdelParajika">THE PARAJIKA SECTION</string>
    <string name="buttonParajika1">1\n If any monk participating in the training and lifestyle of monks, without refusing to study, without openly declaring his weakness, commits sexual intercourse with a woman or with a female animal, such a monk has been defeated and is no longer a member of the sangha.</string>
    <string name="textAboutPatimokha">\n The word "patimokkha" usually refers to a set of rules of conduct for Buddhist monks, established, according to Buddhist tradition, by the Buddha himself. These rules applied to almost all aspects of monastic life, according to these rules, all local Buddhist monastic communities functioned. The etymology of the word "patimokkha" (sancr. "pratimoksha") is not entirely clear. According to Mahavagga 2.3.4., this means the beginning, the head of all qualities. This term is used not only as the name of a set of rules of monastic behavior, but also the name of a sermon in which the Buddha outlined the basic principles common to the teachings of all Buddhas:"not doing all kinds of evil, doing all kinds of good, and purifying one's own heart: this is the message of all the Buddhas" (Dhammapada, 183) \n \n

In the early years of the Buddha s activity, there was no need to formulate any disciplinary rules. All the monks who followed him – the community of nuns did not exist then – were people of high personal achievements, those who succeeded in destroying all or many mental defilements. They knew the Buddhas teachings well and behaved accordingly. The canon tells how venerable Sariputta, one of the main disciples of the Buddha, asked the Buddha early enough to establish a Patimokkha, or set of rules. This set of rules could ensure the long life of the Buddhas teachings, just as the thread that binds together flower ornaments ensures that the flowers are not scattered by the wind. The Buddha replied that the time for such a code had not yet come, since even the most backward members of the community at that time already had the first experience of approaching the goal. Only when mental defilements (asava) make themselves felt in the community, there will be a need for the rules of Patimokkha. \n \n

As time passed, the conditions that allowed mental pollution to enter the community began to appear. In the Bhaddali Sutta (M. 67), the Buddha lists five such conditions: \n

"Bhaddali: "Why is it, dear sir, there were few rules of conduct before, and the number of monks who were established in the knowledge of Awakening was large? And why now, when there are many rules of conduct, fewer monks are confirmed in the knowledge of Awakening?" (Bhaddali, who did not want to live by disciplinary rules, suggests that an increase in the number of rules is the reason that fewer monks achieve Awakening. The Buddha, however, offers another explanation.)

Buddha: "So it is, Bhaddali. When living beings began to degenerate and the true Dharma began to disappear, many disciplinary rules appeared, and the number of monks who had established themselves in the knowledge of Awakening became small. The teacher (i.e., the Buddha himself) did not establish rules of conduct until conditions arose that contributed to the rise of mental pollution in the community. But when such conditions arose, the Teacher established rules of conduct as a means of countering such conditions. .. These conditions did not arise until the community became large. But when the community became large, conditions were created that contributed to the rise of mental pollution in the community. …When the community began to possess large material resources, ... a high status in society, ... a large body of teaching (texts), ... when the community had existed for a long time, ... then conditions were created that contributed to the rise of mental pollution in the community."

Thus, the rules themselves were not the cause of the degeneration of the community, and the conditions conducive to the rise of mental pollution were not in themselves pollution. Rather, the complication of the life of the community provided an opportunity for the monks to act on the basis of their pollution, and the rules – although they could not prevent any of these conditions – had to be complicated accordingly.

When establishing the rules of conduct, the Buddha justified the need for this with ten reasons: for the perfection of the sangha, for peace in the sangha, for abstinence from shamelessness, for the convenience of bhikkhus of good behavior, for the suppression of defilements related to the past life, for the prevention of defilements related to the future life, for raising faith in non-believers, for the growth of believers, for affirmations of the true dharma and for the education of students .

These causes fall into three types. The first two are external: to ensure peace and correct behavior within the sangha proper and to educate and protect the faith among lay followers of Buddhism. The third type of reasons are internal: to help control and prevent mental contamination within each individual monk. This last division quickly becomes the main one for anyone who seriously tries to follow the rules, as they help to develop mindfulness and concentration when performing any actions – those qualities that are necessary when training consciousness (mind).

The Buddha did not establish the whole set of rules at the same time. On the contrary, he formulated the rules one by one, in response to individual specific events. In the canon, all the cases about which a particular rule was formulated have been preserved, and often knowledge of these "origin stories" can help in understanding the meaning of a particular rule. For example, the history of the origin of the rule prohibiting sexually directed affectionate behavior between monks and women shows that the Buddha did not consider women as something unclean. On the contrary, this rule comes from the case when a monk gently touched the wife of a brahmin who came to visit his home, and the Buddha wanted the women to feel safe when coming to the monastery, knowing that no one would molest them.

Over time, the number of rules grew, and several followers of the Buddha, led by the pious Upali, collected the main rules into a complete set - the Patimokkha Sutta – which contained 227 rules. The Patimokkha sutta, as we know it now, is included in the text called the Vibhanga Sutta. It presents each rule preceding its origin story. It is followed by an explanation of what changes took place in this rule (if any) before it was fixed in its final form. The rule is then analyzed by its constituent elements to show how the factors of effort, object of action, perception, intention and result mitigate or do not mitigate the punishment prescribed by this rule. The discussion ends with a list of circumstances in which this action is not considered a violation, despite the rule.

The minor rules, which numbered several hundred, were collected into chapters distributed on topics called Khandaks. The Khandakas themselves are also divided into two parts: Mahavagga, or the Big Chapter, and Chulavagga, or the Smaller Chapter. Historians estimate that Vibhanga and Khandaki acquired their final form no later than the 2nd century BC. A little later, a Parivara was added to them – a text reviewing and systematizing the previous parts, and thus the canonical Vinaya pitaka was completed.

 The system of punishments applied by the Buddha in his disciplinary rules was based on two principles. Firstly, the goal of Buddhist practice is primarily the development of the mind. Thus, the factors of intention and conscious perception of committed actions often determined whether a particular action was a violation of the rules. For example, the accidental killing of an animal, in terms of the action of the mind, is very different from intentional killing, and is not considered a violation of the rule prohibiting the killing of animals.

There are very few rules where the factors of intention and conscious perception do not play a role at all – such as the rule forbidding monks to drink alcohol – but they almost always deal with situations where an individual is expected to retain attentiveness and perceptual ability sufficiently to understand what he is going to do, and thus these rules also help train the mind.

In any case, the system of analyzing each violation in terms of effort, object, conscious perception, intention and result shows how firm adherence to the rules leads to the development of concentration and understanding. If a monk gets used to being aware of his actions in terms of these factors, he will develop mindfulness, an analytical approach to reality (the present) and perseverance. These are the first three factors of Enlightenment (awakening), forming the basis for the other three: joy, nobility, concentration and equanimity of the spirit.

The second principle used in certain punishments is based on the Buddha's impressions of communication with Ananda, his main disciple. The Buddha became convinced that friendliness and sociability are extremely necessary in religious life. Anyone who approaches the Dharma seriously should be wise enough to understand that without the possibility of communication and learning from people who have already established themselves on the path, it is almost impossible to make progress on their own path. Thus, monks get used to appreciating their good reputation on the part of respected members of their group, and the whole system of punishments developed by the Buddha is built entirely on the impact on the status of the offender within the community.       \n \n \n</string>
    <string name="textAboutPunish">Patimokkha classifies the rules of conduct into eight sections: \n \n

1) parajika – defeat (exclusion from the community); \n

2) sanghadisesa – requiring an initial (adi) and subsequent (sesa) community meeting; \n

3) aniyata – indefinite (i.e. the result depends on the decision of the community); \n

4) nissagia pachittia – requiring reckoning and recognition; \n

5) pachittia – requiring recognition; \n

6) patidesania – requiring recognition a certain form; \n

7) sekhiya – instructions; \n

8) adhikarana samatha – rules for the consideration of controversial issues arising in the community. \n \n

Not all sections of Patimokkha are associated with certain types of punishments. Aniyatas rules give direction for solving uncertain cases. The rules of Sekhia relate primarily to the etiquette of behavior and simply state that one should behave in a certain way. The rules of the Adhikaran samatha are rather not rules, but principles according to which issues arising in the community should be resolved. \n \n

The system of punishments prescribed by the rules consists of four main types, varying from final and unconditional expulsion from the sangha to a simple confession in the presence of another monk. \n \n

A monk who has committed one of the four most serious offenses included in the section of the parajika is automatically considered deprived of the monastic title, even if no one knows about this offense. Therefore, there is no need to conduct any ceremony related to the deprivation of monastic dignity. The very act of committing a misdemeanor is an act of exclusion from the monastic community. A monk is considered to be excluded from the sangha completely and irrevocably, in this life he cannot re-enter the community. The same rules requiring exclusion from the community also applied to nuns. (there were four other rules of this category for nuns). In addition, nuns who returned to secular life as wives of householders were excluded from the community. \n \n

If a monk violates one of the following important rules – the rules of the sanghadises, he is obliged to notify one of the monks and ask the community of at least four monks to impose a six-day period of punishment on him. During the punishment, the monk is deprived of his status and must comply with a number of restrictions, the main of which are the following: \n

"he can't live under the same roof with fully ordained monks."; \n
– he cannot leave the monastery without being accompanied by fully dedicated monks; \n
– every day he must inform all the monks in the monastery what violation he has committed and what punishment has been imposed on him. If there are visiting monks in the monastery, he is also obliged to inform them. \n \n

After the term of punishment has ended, a monk can ask a community of at least twenty monks to rehabilitate him. After rehabilitation, he returns to his former status as a fully ordained monk of regular behavior. \n \n

If a monk has been hiding for some time that he has violated one of the rules of the sanghadises, he must observe an additional probation period of the same duration as he hid his offense. Only after that he can ask for a six-day punishment and subsequent rehabilitation. \n \n

Violations from the category of sanghadises are classified as severe – both because of their own seriousness, and because of the anxiety that the punishment and subsequent rehabilitation procedure brings to the community. \n \n

The following type of punishment is imposed for violating the rules of nisaggia pachittia, which can be translated as "requiring reckoning and recognition." Each of the rules in this section is related to an item that the monk acquired or used incorrectly. Before publicly admitting his mistake, a monk must give this item "as payback" to his fellow monk or a group of monks. After a public confession, he is released from the offense. In most cases, the payment is symbolic – after his confession, the monk receives the item back, and only in three cases he gives the item away forever. \n \n

A monk can make a confession of committing a violation in front of one or more monks or in front of the entire community. Only the violation of the rules regarding the receipt and use of money, as well as the receipt of an excessive bowl for collecting alms (NP No. 18, 19 and 22) requires mandatory recognition before the whole community. In the same three cases, incorrectly received or used items are not returned to the monk. In other cases, after receiving back his property, he must use it properly. \n \n

Violations of this and the following two types are classified as mild. The guilt for the commission of the last two violations (pacchitia and patidesania) is removed through a simple confession to one monk or the entire community. The difference between these two sections is only that in the last section the form of recognition is fixed in the text of the rules of Patimokkha itself. \n \n

In addition, there are also derivative punishments not specified in the rules of Patimokkha, but specified in the Vibhanga and in the comments. These derivative punishments deal with two kinds of cases: \n \n

– a monk tries to perform an action specified in the rules, but for some reason the action does not reach its final completion (for example, a monk tries to kill someone, but this person does not die); \n \n

– a monk performs an action not directly specified in the rules, but similar to that specified in the rules (for example, he strikes a layman – this case is not specified in the rules, but there is a clause when a monk strikes another monk). \n \n

Such derivative punishments include thullachiya (in more serious cases) and dukkata (in less serious cases). The derivative punishment for incorrect speech also includes dubbhasita. The guilt for committing such derivative violations is removed through a simple confession. \n \n

If these punishments do not correct the behavior of the violator, and he repeatedly violates the rules, the community can impose additional punishments on him. They may vary from the removal of certain privileges of seniority, expulsion from a separate community of monks or expulsion from the community as a whole. In all cases, the punishment is temporary, if the monk understands his mistakes and corrects his way of acting, the community returns him to his former status. The same temporary expulsion from the community occurs if the monk who committed the offense refuses to be punished. \n \n

It should be noted that there is a lot of evidence in the canon that the Buddhas attitude to observing the rules of behavior was not too formal. \n \n

"Once the Enlightened One was in Vesali, in a Great Grove. Then a certain monk came to the Enlightened One ... and he said:

– Sir, more than 150 rules of conduct have already been collected in order to repeat them every two weeks. I cant perfect myself according to them.

– Can you improve according to three rules: the rule of increasing virtue, the rule of increasing awareness, the rule of increasing wisdom?

– Yes, I can...

– Then improve yourself according to these three rules. When you improve according to these rules, passion will leave you, hatred will leave you, delusions will leave you. When passion, hatred and delusions leave you, you will not do anything wrong, you will not commit any evil." \n \n \n </string>
    <string name="buttonRiulesPatimokhaParajika2">2 \n If any bhikkhu should take what has not been given from a village or
wilderness, which is reckoned as theft, [and] the taking of what has
not been given is of the kind [that] on account of it kings, having
caught the robber, would physically punish or imprison or banish
[him, saying]: “You are a robber! You are a fool! You are insane! You
are a thief!,” a bhikkhu taking what has not been given of such a kind,
is also disqualified, not in communion.</string>
    <string name="buttonRiulesPatimokhaParajika3">3 \n If any bhikkhu should deliberately deprive a human being of life, or
should seek an assassin for him, or should praise the attractiveness of
death, or should incite [him] to death [saying]: “Dear man, what [use]
is this bad, wretched life for you? Death is better than life for you!”
should he, [having] such-thought-and-mind, [having such-] thoughtand-
intention, praise in manifold ways the beauty of death or incite
[him] to death, he also is disqualified, not in communion.</string>
    <string name="buttonRiulesPatimokhaParajika4">4 \n If any bhikkhu, [though] not directly knowing [it], should claim a
superhuman state pertaining to himself, [a state of] knowing and
seeing [that is] suitable for the noble [ones], [saying]: “Thus I know!
Thus I see!,” [and] then, on another occasion, [whether] being
interrogated or not being interrogated, having committed [the
offence], desiring purification, should say so: “Friends, [although] not
knowing [it,] I spoke thus [saying]: ‘I know,’ not seeing [it, I spoke,
saying:] ‘I see.’ I bluffed vainly [and] falsely,” except [when said] in
overestimation, he also is disqualified, not in communion.</string>
    <string name="textViewHintParajika">Click on the rule to see the rule in Pali.</string>

</resources>